<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Early piety, exemplified in the life and death of Mr. Nathanael Mather, who ... changed earth for heaven, Oct. 17. 1688 whereto are added some discourses on the true nature, the great reward, and the best season of such a walk with God as he left a pattern of.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1097A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12177739</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12177739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 817:27 or 1728:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Early piety, exemplified in the life and death of Mr. Nathanael Mather, who ... changed earth for heaven, Oct. 17. 1688 whereto are added some discourses on the true nature, the great reward, and the best season of such a walk with God as he left a pattern of.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Samuel, 1651-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition,</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[14], 60 [i.e. 62], [2], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Astwood for John Dunton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cotton Mather. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Samuel Mather. "The life and death of Mr. Nathanael Mather" signed: Cotton Mather.</note>
                  <note>"Several sermons concerning walking with God ..." has special t.p. and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 817:27 incorrectly identified as Wing M1097, and at reel 1728:4 as Wing M1097A.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 1728:4 lacks "Several sermons concerning ..."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mather, Nathanael, 1631-1697.</term>
               <term>Sermons, American --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:1"/>
                  <p>EARLY PIETY,
EXEMPLIFIED
IN THE
<hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi>
OF
Mr. <hi>Nathanael Mather,</hi>
WHO
Having become at the Age of
Nineteen, an Inſtance of more
than Common
<hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi>
Changed Earth for Heaven, <hi>Oct.</hi> 17. 1688.
Whereto are added,
Some Diſcourſes on the true Nature,
the great Reward, and the beſt
Seaſon of ſuch
A WALK WITH GOD
as he left a Pattern of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
With a <hi>Prefatory</hi> Epiſtle by Mr. <hi>Matthew Mead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>J. Aſtwood</hi> for <hi>Iohn Dunton</hi> at the
<hi>Black Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1689.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:2"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <p>OF all Reading, Hiſtory hath in it
a moſt taking Delight, and no Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
more delightfull than the Lives
of good Men, it being not only pleaſant,
but profitable; and ſo while other Pleaſures
become a <hi>Bait</hi> to Vice, this becomes a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
to Virtue. It may be ſaid of ſuch Lives
as that Excellent Mr. <hi>Herbert</hi> ſaid of
Verſes,
<q>
                        <l>A Life may find him who a Sermon flies,</l>
                        <l>And turn delight into a Sacrifice.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou haſt here a rare Hiſtory of a Youth,
that may be of great uſe and advantage
both to Old and Young: That the Aged ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
themſelves out-done by Green years, may
<hi>gird up their loyns,</hi> and mend their pace
for Heaven; and that Young ones may be
ſo wrought into the love of Religion, as it
is Exemplified in this holy Perſon, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
with all diligence to write after his
excellent Copy.</p>
                  <p>It is a great Work to <hi>die,</hi> and to <hi>die
well</hi> is a greater; and no Work calls for
<pb facs="tcp:55562:3"/>
greater diligence than this, becauſe the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
of the firſt work can never be correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in a ſecond. One great reaſon why this
duty is ſeldom well done, is becauſe we grudge
Time to do it in, and leave it to be done
at once. It is never like to be well done,
unleſs it be always doing; and therefore we
ſhould, in Conformity to that great Apoſtle,
die daily.</p>
                  <p>This was the practice of this <hi>young Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi>
who among all his other Learning
(wherein for his time he excelled moſt) had
in <hi>Nineteen years</hi> ſo perfectly learned this
Leſſon, that the wiſe God ſaw it fit he
ſhould <hi>take out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>About <hi>Fourteen years</hi> old he did dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
himſelf wholly to God and his Service,
and entred into a <hi>Solemn Covenant</hi> with
God to that purpoſe: which as he did not
begin <hi>raſhly,</hi> and without great <hi>delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
ſo he did not tranſact it ſlightly,
but with great <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>ſeriouſneſs:</hi> The
Matter and Form of which <hi>Covenant</hi> you
have in this enſuing Narrative, ſigned with
his own Hand, according to that word of the
Prophet, <hi>(Iſa. 44. 5.) One ſhall ſay, I am
the Lords, and another ſhall call himſelf
by the name of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and another ſhall
ſubſcribe with his hand to the Lord.</hi>
And with what care and Conſcience he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>formed
<pb facs="tcp:55562:3"/>
this Covenant, in Faſting, in Prayer,
in Watchings, in Self-Examination, in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation,
in Thanksgiving, in Walking with
God in all, is fully witneſſed in what follows,
which ſhews that he was a true <hi>Nathanael,
an Iſraelite indeed in whom was no guile.</hi>
Not like thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> which the Prophet
reproveth, for that <hi>they flattered God with
their Mouth,—lied to him with their
tongues, their hearts not being right
with him, nor ſtedfaſt in his Covenant.</hi>
For having once given up himſelf to God,
<hi>He kept the ways of the Lord, and did
not wickedly depart from his God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When his worthy Father (my dear Friend)
was pleaſed to ſend this Narrative to me, I
confeſs I could not read it without great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection
and Shame: Thought I, God will not
gather his Fruit till it is ripe, and therefore
I live ſo long; nor will he let it hang till it
is rotten, therefore <hi>Nathanael</hi> dyed ſo ſoon.
We are not ſent into the World meerly
to fill up a Number of years, but to fill up
our Meaſures of Grace, and whenever that is
done, our time is done, and we have lived to
Maturity, and ſo did this Youth, and therefore
<hi>came to his Grave in a full Age</hi> (tho at
N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>teen) <hi>like as a Shock of Corn comes
in in his ſeaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55562:4"/>
The following Hiſtory is written by his own
Brother, (a worthy Miniſter) the fitteſt of
any for ſuch a Province, the nearneſs of
Relation occaſioning that In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>acy which others
could not eaſily have. In what he hath done
herein, he hath deſerved highly of all who love
Goodneſs and Virtue, having uſed great Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,
and great Modeſty: Great Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
and that both to the Dead and to the
Living; To the dead, in raiſing up the Name
of ſuch a Brother; and to the living, in giving
us a <hi>Narration</hi> of his Life, without an <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
in his Praiſe; which indeed was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
needleſs, when it was ſo fairly written by
himſelf, for his own works praiſe him in the
Gates. And he hath uſed great Modeſty, in
ſpeaking for the moſt part out of the Journal
of the Deceaſed, ſo that it is the <hi>dead</hi> who
ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> while the <hi>living</hi> writes. And ſince his
End is more to provoke to Imitation than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak
Admiration, How greatly doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
them into whoſe hands this <hi>Narrative</hi>
ſhall happily fall, to joyn earneſt Prayer and
diligent Endeavour together in following this
great Example, otherwiſe he that gave it,
and he that writes it, will both riſe up in
judgment againſt an unteachable Generation.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Matthew Mead.</signed> 
                     <dateline>London,
<date>June
17. 1689.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:4"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <p>IT is not for me to ſay much of
the Perſon who is the Subject of
the enſuing Hiſtory, for that I
am his younger Brother. I have read
a Letter (dated <hi>October 25. 1688.)</hi>
written to his and my ever honoured
Father, wherein are theſe Expreſſions.</p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>Never could Parent have cauſe of
more comfort in a Child, than you
have in that Son of yours. I have
ſeen his private Papers, and in them
ſuch an Inſtance of a Walk with
God, as few ancient Miniſters per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
have Experience of, eſpecially
for the three laſt years of his Life,
I find that he maintained a courſe
of wonderful Devotion, Supplication
and Meditation every day; that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
Humiliations and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
in ſecret, were no ſtrangers to
<pb facs="tcp:55562:5"/>
his Practice, that he would be often
thinking with himſelf, <hi>What ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
I do for God?</hi> And in a word, that
Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Book about <hi>Spiritual-Mindedneſs,</hi>
has been in a very rare
manner tranſcribed into his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
                     <p>He has bin for his years a great
Scholar, but a better Chriſtian. The
Life of the famous young <hi>Janeway,</hi>
I think, has not more of Holineſs
illuſtrious in it, than that of your
dear <hi>Nathanael</hi>'s.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I write theſe things, becauſe I
judge you have no greater Joy.
Some Eminent Miniſters here, have
maintained a pleaſant, intimate, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar
Converſation with him, and
the Character which they gave of
him, is very Extraordinary.</q> Thus
that Letter.</p>
                  <p>I have likewiſe heard my Father ſay,
that he was more grieved for the loſs
which the Church of God has ſuſtained
in the death of that my Brother, than
for his own loſs thereby.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55562:5"/>
When I parted from him not a year
ago, I hoped that would not have been
my <hi>Ultimum Vale;</hi> but I now lament
my unhappineſs, in that I gain'd no
more by him: And yet muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that the little underſtanding which
God has given me in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> or
<hi>Greek</hi> Tongues, was by that my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
as the inſtrument: So that I have
cauſe whilſt I ſhall live, to honour his
Memory. His Death makes me remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
the Poets words,
<q>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I cannot but know, that if I ſhould
not fear and ſerve the God of my
Brothers, and of my Fathers, and of
my Grand-Fathers, the neareſt Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
I ever had in the World, will be
Witneſſes againſt me at the laſt day.
The Lord give us a joyful meeting in
the day of Christ.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>London,
<date>February,
5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1689.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Samuel Mather.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:6"/>
                  <head>THE
INTRODUCTION.</head>
                  <p>MY Reader will quickly diſcern
<hi>what</hi> it is that I attempt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of; and I ſuppoſe he will
then ſee no occaſion of enquiring <hi>Why.</hi>
The <hi>Apology's</hi> wherewith Writers uſually
fill the <hi>Prefaces</hi> of their Books, <hi>Do come
of Evil;</hi> either the Vanity of the <hi>Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi>
is diſcovered, or the Candour of the
<hi>Peruſers</hi> queſtioned in them. That I
Write the <hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> cannot be
faulted by any one who Conſiders, That
the <hi>Lives</hi> of Pious Men have been juſtly
eſteemed among the moſt uſeful <hi>Hiſtories</hi>
which the Church of God Enjoyes; or
that the <hi>beſt Pens</hi> in the World have
been employ'd in thus helping the <hi>Juſt</hi>
unto <hi>Eternal Memory.</hi> Our Lord will
have as mean a thing as one Act of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion
and Charity, in a poor <hi>Woman,</hi>
to be mentioned wherever His <hi>Goſpel</hi>
comes. That I write the <hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55562:6"/>
will not be reckoned abſurd by them
who underſtand what <hi>Patterns</hi> I have,
both <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Modern,</hi> for my doing
ſo. <hi>James Janeway</hi> among the reſt has had
our Thanks for what an Account he has
given of his Brother <hi>John.</hi> Indeed; if I
ſhould not thus Raiſe up for my departed
Brother a Name in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I were not
worthy to <hi>Wear a Shoo,</hi> or to have a <hi>Face
unſpit upon.</hi> My <hi>Natural Relation</hi> to him
doth oblige me to beſtow an Epitaph up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
his Grave; that the Survivers may not
forget whoſe Duſt they tread upon: But
I am by (that which <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls) a
<hi>Greater and Better Fraternity,</hi> concerned
to Embalm the Memory of One, who
maintained ſuch a <hi>Walk with God,</hi> as he
did until <hi>God took him</hi> to Himſelf. It
has been obſerved, That they who <hi>Live
in Heaven while they are on Earth,</hi> often
<hi>Live on Earth after they are in Heaven.</hi> It
were lawful for me to deſire and Study
ſuch a thing on the behalf of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
whoſe <hi>Early Piety</hi> is at once my
own <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Joy:</hi> But I purſue an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
End than this, deſigning rather to
procure <hi>Followers,</hi> than to beſpeak <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi>
of this good Example: That this is
my <hi>Main Scope,</hi> in what I am now doing
of, I declare ſincerely and very ſolemnly.
<pb facs="tcp:55562:7"/>
And hence I have not here made an <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
in his <hi>Praiſe,</hi> but given barely a <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi>
of his Life, and this moſtly by
Tranſcribing of his own <hi>Memorials,</hi> in
all affecting the <hi>plain ſtyle</hi> of a Juſt <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian.</hi>
I do therefore Addreſs this <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary
Life</hi> unto the young People of <hi>New-England,</hi>
and eſpecially unto thoſe of <hi>North-Boſton,</hi>
who are the <hi>Lambs</hi> that I have
Received a peculiar Charge from the
Lord Jeſus about the <hi>Feeding</hi> of. To you
do I preſent this <hi>Mirrour,</hi> wherein you
may ſee the Exerciſes of a <hi>Virtuous Youth,</hi>
not only <hi>preſcribed,</hi> but alſo <hi>practiſed</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
your Eyes: You ſhall ſee, as what
<hi>ſhould</hi> be done, ſo what <hi>may</hi> be done by
a <hi>Young</hi> Perſon, in order to Everlaſting
Felicity; ſee him and hear him as <hi>One
come from the Dead,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Do as I have
done.</hi> The <hi>Father</hi> of him whom I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
has Laboured exceedingly for the
<hi>Converſion of the Riſing Generation in New-England;</hi>
and his CALL to them has been
Printed and Reprinted here among us.
Thô the News of a <hi>Sons</hi> Death muſt needs
be afflictive to him, when he ſhall have
the Report of it arriving to him in the
other <hi>England,</hi> yet I make no doubt, but
his Parental Griefs will be not a little
Mitigated, when he ſhall hehold <hi>that
<pb facs="tcp:55562:7"/>
Son</hi> thus Renewing his CALL by <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
after he is Dead. This Young Man
did <hi>pray</hi> much for <hi>you,</hi> while he was
Alive, that <hi>you</hi> might be truly Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto God; he does <hi>preach now</hi> to <hi>you,</hi>
from the <hi>Grave,</hi> or rather from the <hi>Sky,</hi>
that you would <hi>Remember your Creator
in the dayes of your Youth.</hi> I wiſh that
he may (to uſe <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> Phraſe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
a <hi>Brother</hi> to you by <hi>Faith,</hi> as he is
to me by <hi>Blood:</hi> And I extend this my
wiſh with a moſt Affectionate Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to the Young Gentlemen, who belong
to the <hi>Colledge</hi> which he was a Member
of. As you have had in his <hi>Father</hi> a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi>
whoſe Generous and Expenſive Cares
have not been for your diſadvantage; ſo
you have in his <hi>Diligence</hi> and his <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
a <hi>Copy</hi> which is not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
of your Imitation: I am ſetting
before you the <hi>Exerciſes</hi> and <hi>Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
of a <hi>Scholar,</hi> whoſe chief Study it
was, <hi>to be Wiſe unto Salvation;</hi> a <hi>Scholar,</hi>
who Laboured while he was Learning
all other things, not to be Ignorant of
Him, <hi>Whom to know is Life Eternal.</hi> I am
not without Hope, that ſome of you
will now reſolve as <hi>Jerom</hi> did when he
had read the Life of <hi>Hilarion,</hi> ſhutting
up the Book and ſaying, <hi>Well, here ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:55562:8"/>
be the Champion whom I will follow:</hi> When
you come to Dye, you will certainly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
ſuch a <hi>Life</hi> as his; god grant that
none of you may then have cauſe to ſigh,
<hi>Qualis Artifex pereo!</hi> Or to complain,
<hi>Surgunt Indocti &amp; rapiunt Coelum; Nos cum
nostris Doctrinis mergimur in Infernum.</hi> That
Great Man <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> near his End pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed,
That he would gladly give all his
Learning and Honour for the Integrity
of a <hi>poor Man</hi> in his Neighbourhood,
that ſpent <hi>Eights Hours</hi> of his Time i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Prayer, Eight</hi> in <hi>Labour,</hi> and <hi>Eight</hi> in <hi>Sleep</hi>
and other Neceſſaries; and unto ſome
that applauded his Marvellous <hi>Induſtry</hi>
he ſaid, <hi>Ah, Vitam perdidi operoſe nihi
Agendo!</hi> But unto ſome that asked, the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
Counſel which a Man of his Attainment
could give, he ſaid, <hi>Be ſerious.</hi> 'Tis with
this <hi>Counſel</hi> that I humbly offer you the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
Hiſtory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>Advertiſements.</head>
                  <p>THere is juſt now publiſht a Treatiſe entituled, <hi>Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
or <hi>Right Chriſtianity</hi> deſcribed, in its Excellent
and Uſefulneſs in the <hi>Whole Life of Man.</hi> Written by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Barker</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel. <hi>Price bound 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There will in a few days be publiſht <hi>A new Martyrology,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
the <hi>Bloody Aſſizes,</hi> now exactly methodized in <hi>one Volume,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
a compleat Hiſtory of the <hi>Lives, Sufferings</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Deaths</hi> of all thoſe Excellent Perſons who fell in the <hi>Weſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
elſewhere, from 1678. to 1689. with the Pictures of ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
the Chief of them in Copper-plates. To which is added, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
Life and Death of <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Jefferys.</hi>—Both ſold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55562:8"/>
                  <head>THE
LIFE and DEATH
OF
Mr. NATHANAEL MATHER.</head>
                  <p>I Write the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of a
Young Man, whoſe Ornament will
awaken in the Reader, an Enquiry
like that which the Atchievments of
<hi>David,</hi> produced concerning him, <hi>Whoſe
Son is this Youth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To Anticipate that Enquiry:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nathanael Mather</hi> had for his Grand-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
Two of <hi>New-England</hi>'s Fathers, the
Famous <hi>Richard Mather,</hi> and the not leſs
Famous <hi>John Cotton;</hi> whoſe <hi>Names</hi> have
been in the Church of God, as an <hi>Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
powred forth,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Lives</hi> bear
no little Figure in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55562:9"/>
of our <hi>Engliſh Iſrael.</hi> His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
being yet living, it's too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſoon, to gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
them their Character; yet I may ventu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
to ſay, It's no diſgrace unto him in the
Opinion of Men that love <hi>Learning</hi> and
<hi>Virtue,</hi> that he was the Son of <hi>Increaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Mather,</hi> the well known Teacher of a
Church in <hi>Boſton,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Colledge</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi> What <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory
Nazianzen</hi> judged not improper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
be ſaid about his yet ſurviving <hi>Father</hi>
in his Funeral Oration upon his Decea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<hi>Brother,</hi> I may without any culpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
Adulation on this occaſion, ſay of him
<hi>He is another Aaron or Moſes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
of his God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our <hi>Nathanael</hi> was born on <hi>July 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
1669.</hi> which I find him Recording <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
his <hi>Diary,</hi> when he was fourteen Year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Old, with ſuch an humble Reflection ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>upon,
<hi>How little have I improved this tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
to the Honour of God as I ſhould have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
He wanted not the Cares of his Father
to beſtow a good <hi>Education</hi> on him, which
God bleſſed for the <hi>Reſtraining</hi> him from
the lewd and wild Courſes by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
many Children are betimes reſigned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
to the poſſeſſion of the Devil, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
the <hi>Furniſhing</hi> him with the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
as give <hi>an Ornament of Grace</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55562:9"/>
                     <hi>the Head of Youth.</hi> He did <hi>Live</hi> where he
might Learn, and under the continual
Prayers and Pains, of ſome that looked af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
him, he became an Inſtance of unuſual
<hi>Induſtry,</hi> and no Common <hi>Piety;</hi> ſo that
when he dyed, which was <hi>Octob.</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1688.
he was become in leſs than twenty years,
<hi>An Old Man without Gray hairs upon him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To thoſe <hi>two</hi> Heads, with a ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Addition of a <hi>Third,</hi> I ſhall conſine
my account of this Young Man; in which
the <hi>Picture</hi> to be now drawn, has nothing
but the <hi>Truth,</hi> and at leaſt ſo much of
<hi>Life</hi> in it, as to look upon every Reader,
yea <hi>ſpeak</hi> unto him, ſaying, <hi>Go and do
likewiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>I. His INDUSTY.</head>
                     <p>He was an hard <hi>Student,</hi> and quickly
became a good <hi>Scholar.</hi> From his very
Childhood, his <hi>Book</hi> was perhaps as dear
to him as his <hi>Play,</hi> and hence he grew
particularly acquainted with <hi>Church-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi>
at a rate not uſual in thoſe that
were above thrice as Old as <hi>He.</hi> But
when he came to ſomewhat more of
<hi>Youth,</hi> his Tutor (who now writes) was
forced often to Chide him <hi>to</hi> his Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
but never that I remember <hi>for</hi>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55562:10"/>
them. To be <hi>Bookiſh</hi> was natural unto
him, and to be <hi>plodding</hi> eaſie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
rather than the contrary. Indeed he
afforded not ſo much a <hi>Pattern</hi> as a <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
to young Students; for it may be
truly written on his Grave, Study kill'd
Him. The <hi>marks</hi> and <hi>works</hi> of a Studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Mind were to be diſcerned in him,
even as he walked in the Streets; and
his Candle would burn after <hi>Midnight,</hi>
until, as his own Phraſe for it was, <hi>He
thought his bones would all fall aſunder.</hi>
This was among the paſſages once noted
in his Diary.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>10 M. 26 D.</hi> three quarters of an hour
after 12 at Night.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">After the many weariſom <hi>hours, days<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
months,</hi> nay, <hi>years,</hi> that I have ſpent it
humane Literature; and after my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
toilſom Studies in thoſe Hours
when the <hi>General ſilence</hi> of every Houſe
in Town, proclaimed it high time for
me to put a ſtop unto my workin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Mind, and urged me to afford ſome Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
unto my <hi>Eyes,</hi> which have been almo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
put out by my Intenſeneſs on my Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
after theſe, I ſay, and when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
am ready to do it: Oh how unwilling
am I to do it, conſidering; <hi>How litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
I have ſerved God in the day!</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55562:10"/>
While he thus <hi>devoured Books,</hi> it came
to paſs that <hi>Books devoured</hi> him. His
weak Body would not bear the <hi>Toils,</hi> and
Hours, which he uſed himſelf unto; and
his Neglect of <hi>Moderate Exerciſe,</hi> joyned
with his Exceſs of <hi>Immoderate Lucubrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
ſoon deſtroyed the <hi>Digeſtion</hi> which
his Blood ſhould have had in the laſt Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boration
of it: by that time ſixteen <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
had ſnow'd upon him, he began to
be Diſtempered, with many <hi>Pains</hi> and
<hi>Ailes,</hi> eſpecially in ſome of his <hi>Joynts,</hi>
which at laſt were the <hi>Gates of Death</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
him; not without ſuch very afflictive
touches of <hi>Melancholy,</hi> too, as made him
ſometimes to Write himſelf, <hi>Deodatus
Melancholicus.</hi> This was his way of <hi>liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
ſhall I ſay, or of <hi>Dying?</hi> And the
<hi>ſucceſs</hi> of this Diligence was according to
the <hi>Temper</hi> of it <hi>Great.</hi> When he was
but <hi>Twelve</hi> Years Old he was admitted
into the <hi>Colledge,</hi> by ſtrict Examiners:
And many Months after this paſſed not,
before he had accurately gone over all the
<hi>Old Teſtament</hi> in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as well as the
<hi>New</hi> in <hi>Greek,</hi> beſides his going through
all the <hi>Liberal Sciences,</hi> before many
other deſigners for Philoſophy do ſo much
as begin to look into them. He Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced
<hi>Batchelour of Arts,</hi> at the Age of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55562:11"/>
Sixteen, and in the <hi>Act</hi> entertained the
Auditory with an <hi>Hebrew Oration,</hi> which
gave a good Account of the Academical
Affairs among the ancient <hi>Jews.</hi> Indeed the
<hi>Hebrew Language</hi> was become ſo Familiar
with him, as if (to uſe the Expreſſion
which one had in an <hi>Ingenious Elegy</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
his Death) he had apprehended it
ſhould quickly become the <hi>only Language</hi>
which he ſhould have ocaſion for. His
<hi>Second</hi> Degree after ſeven years being in the
Colledge, he took juſt before Death gave
him a <hi>Third,</hi> which laſt was a promotion
infinitely beyond either of the former. He
then maintained for his Poſition, <hi>Datur Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuum;</hi>
and by his Diſcourſe upon it (as well
as by other <hi>Memorials</hi> and <hi>Experiments</hi> left
behind him in Manuſcripts) he gave a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
of his Intimate Acquaintance with the
<hi>Corpuſcularian</hi> (and only right) Philoſophy.
By this time he had informed himſelf like
another <hi>Mirandula,</hi> and was admirably ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of arguing about, almoſt every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
that fell within the Concernments of a
Learned Man. Not only <hi>Philoſophy</hi> but alſo
<hi>Divinity</hi> did he now own a <hi>Body</hi> of: The
Difficulties of the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> he had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
overcome, and the abſtruſe parts
both of <hi>Arithmetick</hi> and <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> were
graſped in his Knowledge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55562:11"/>
His Early <hi>Almanack,</hi> and <hi>Calculations</hi> do
ſomething, but the MSS. <hi>Adverſaria,</hi> left
behind him in his Cloſet, much more,
ſpeak ſuch attainments in him: His <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology</hi>
was exact unto a wonder, and the
State of <hi>Learning</hi> with the <hi>Names</hi> and
<hi>Works</hi> of Learned Men, in the World,
this <hi>American</hi> Wilderneſs hath few that
underſtand as well as he. Beſides all
this, for the vaſt Field of <hi>Theology,</hi> both
<hi>Didactick</hi> and <hi>Polemick,</hi> it is hardly Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
how little of it his Travel had left
<hi>unknown. Rabbinick learning</hi> he had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
no ſmall meaſure of; and the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
referring unto the <hi>Scriptures</hi> which
<hi>Phylology</hi> is converſant about, came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
a very Critical Notice with him.
Indeed he was a Perſon but of few words,
and his <hi>Words</hi> with his <hi>Looks</hi> made the
<hi>Treaſure</hi> in him wholly unſuſpected by
Strangers to him; yet they that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately
Acquainted with him, can atteſt
unto the Veracity of him that giveth this
Deſcription; and there are no mean Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
who will profeſs with Admiration,
<hi>That they could ſcarce encounter him in any
Theme of Diſcourſe which he was not very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
acquainted with.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the <hi>Bark</hi> is now ſplit in which all
theſe Riches were ſtowed. A Spaniſh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55562:12"/>
wrack hath not more <hi>Silver</hi> than the Grave
of ſuch a Young Man hath <hi>Learning</hi> buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in it. Indeed theſe things, <hi>Mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
Erunt;</hi> perhaps they dyed with him: Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
there is a more <hi>Immortal</hi> thing to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
in him; and that is,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>II. His PIETY.</head>
                     <p>Tho' a <hi>fine Carriage</hi> was the leaſt thing
that ever he affected, yet a <hi>Good Nature</hi>
made him dear to thoſe that were fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
with him. He was always very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging
and officious, and more ready to
<hi>do,</hi> than others could be to <hi>ask</hi> a good
turn at his hands: But he was above all
<hi>happy,</hi> by being <hi>Early</hi> in <hi>pure Religion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Common Effects of ſuch a <hi>Piou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
Education,</hi> as the Family in which he liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
afforded unto him, were ſeen even in
his Childhood; and <hi>ſecret Prayer</hi> became
very betimes one of his Infant Exerciſes.
He does in his MSs. particularly take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of a <hi>Scripture Copy</hi> ſet for him when
he learned to <hi>Write,</hi> as a thing that had
much Efficacy on him; but when he was
<hi>Twelve</hi> (or more) Years old, more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful
Convictions did the Spirit of God
ſet home upon him than he had been uſed
unto; ſome Records therefore I find in his
Papers, with this Clauſe in the Head of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55562:12"/>
the Account, <hi>Rejoyce O my Soul, for the
Lord has dealt bountifully with thee.</hi> Now
it was that he allowed his Pen to write
theſe, among other Expreſſions of his
Trouble about his Eſtate.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>
                                    <date>Feb. 19. 1682.</date>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>What ſhall I do? <hi>What ſhall I do to
be ſav'd?</hi> Without a Chriſt I am <hi>undone,
undone, undone</hi> for Evermore! O Lord,
let me have <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tho' I lye in the Mire
for ever! O for a Chriſt! O for a Chriſt!
a Chriſt! Lord, <hi>Give me a Chriſt or I dye!</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>It was now another of his Regiſtred
Meditations.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I have been in a Great Heſitancy,
whether I ſhould chooſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for
my Prophet, Prieſt and King, with all
his <hi>Inconveniencies,</hi> to take up my <hi>Croſs</hi>
and follow him: Wherefore I do now
take him as mine; my whole Chriſt, and
my only Chriſt; and I am reſolved to
ſeek him. All that I have ſhall be at his
<hi>Service,</hi> and all my <hi>Members,</hi> and all my
<hi>Powers,</hi> ſhall endeavour his Glory.</q>
                     <p>And yet again there were theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations
in his Mind.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Had I not better ſeek the Lord
Chriſt, while I have a <hi>Time</hi> of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
and Peace, while he offers himſelf
to me, ſaying, <hi>Come unto me, and I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55562:13"/>
will ſave thee, and lay all thy Burdens up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
me, and I will ſuſtain thee:</hi> Than in
Affliction to cry, and not be heard?
when he ſtretcheth forth his Hand and
ſays, <hi>Believe on me and thou ſhalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi>
and now <hi>to Day</hi> he offers himſelf,
ſhall I refuſe, and ſay, Lord, <hi>To Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row?</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>No ſurely. And theſe pathetical
<hi>Groans</hi> then likewiſe got a Room in his
Papers.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">O that I had a <hi>Chriſt!</hi> O that I had
Him who is the <hi>Delight</hi> of my Soul!
Then, O then I ſhould be perfectly
Bleſſed, and want no food that would
make me ſo!</q>
                     <p>This is a <hi>Copy</hi> of the Paſſages then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
in this Young Believers Diary.</p>
                     <p>Thus did he now Labour to affect his
<hi>own Soul</hi> with his <hi>own State,</hi> and leave things
no more at <hi>peradventures</hi> between God
and him. He read many ſavoury Books
about <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
and he Tranſcribed many Notes
therefrom, not reſting ſatisfied within
himſelf, until he had ſome experience of
a true <hi>Regeneration.</hi> Among other work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
of his Heart at this Age, his Papers
have ſuch things as theſe.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>Reaſons for my ſpeedy cloſing with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55562:13"/>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> It's the <hi>Command</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt,
that I ſhould come unto him.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> Invites <hi>me alſo
in</hi> Matt. 11. 28. Come unto me.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He hath laid me under ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<hi>Obligations,</hi> to turn unto him, in
that he hath recovered me from <hi>Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
ſo often, and now given me a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<hi>Study.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In that I have vow'd unto
the Lord, if he would do ſo and ſo for
me, I would make a ſolemn <hi>Covenant</hi>
with him, and endeavour to ſerve him.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>And again elſewhere.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">O that God would help me to ſeek
Him while I am <hi>Young!</hi> O that he
would give unto me His <hi>Grace!</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
I will lay my ſelf down at his
Feet. If he <hi>Save</hi> me, I ſhall be happy
for ever; if he <hi>Damn</hi> me, I muſt Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
him. <hi>O thou Son of God, have mercy
on me!</hi> I know not what to ſay, but I
will take thee at thy Word: Thou
ſayſt, <hi>Come unto me;</hi> my Soul anſwers,
<hi>Lord, at thy Command I will come.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>He thus continued <hi>following hard after
God,</hi> enjoying and anſwering many <hi>ſtrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
of his Holy Spirit until he was about
<hi>Fourteen</hi> Years Old.</p>
                     <p>In this time he did not a little acquaint
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55562:14"/>
himſelf with <hi>profitable Godlineſs,</hi> being fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
and fervent in his <hi>Prayers</hi> to God
upon all occaſions, and careful not only
to <hi>hear Sermons,</hi> but alſo to conſider af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
them <hi>what Improvement he ſhould make of
what he heard.</hi> Not only his <hi>Prayers,</hi> but his
<hi>Praiſes</hi> too now took notice of even the
ſmalleſt Affairs before him. I know not
whether you can ſee any thing <hi>Childiſh,</hi> I
am ſure I ſee ſomething <hi>ſerious,</hi> in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
or two that I ſhall fetch out of his
<hi>Diary,</hi> written when he was about <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen</hi>
years old: On <hi>March</hi> 13. he wrote,
<hi>This day I received of my Father, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Work, The</hi> Biblia Polyglotta, <hi>for which
I deſire to praiſe the Name of God:</hi> Again
on <hi>June</hi> 29 he wrote, <hi>This day my Brother
gave me</hi> Schindlers Lexicon, <hi>a Book for which
I had not only longed much, but alſo prayed
unto God: Bleſſed be the Lords Name for it.</hi>
The Thoughts of <hi>Death</hi> alſo now found
a Lodging in his Heart, and he Rebuked
himſelf becauſe he had been ſo much
without them. Tho' at this Age for the
moſt part, Perſons think of <hi>any</hi> thing, <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
thing more than of <hi>their dying day.</hi> And
his writings diſcovered him to be pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liarly
affected with that Ancient <hi>Hiſtory</hi> (or <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue)</hi>
of him who after a diſſolute and
ungodly <hi>Youth,</hi> going to repent in Age,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55562:14"/>
heard that Voice from Heaven to him,
<hi>Des illi Furfurem cui dediſti Farinam:</hi> The
Devil had thy <hi>Flower,</hi> and thou ſhalt not
bring thy <hi>Bran</hi> to me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Self-Examination</hi> was alſo become one of
his Employments; and once particularly
in one of his <hi>Diaries,</hi> he does thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
himſelf.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>
                                    <date>April 8. 1683.</date>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>This Morning I was much caſt down
with the ſenſe of my Vileneſs. I Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd,</p>
                                 <p>I. What <hi>Sins</hi> I had that were not
Mortified: 1. My ſin of <hi>Pride.</hi> 2. My
ſin of <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankfulneſs.</hi> 3. My not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
the <hi>means of Grace,</hi> as I ought
to do.</p>
                                 <p>II. What <hi>Graces</hi> I find need of. 1. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting</hi>
and <hi>Regenerating</hi> Grace. 2. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation</hi>
for my many Sins againſt ſuch
a good God as the Lord is.</p>
                                 <p>III. What <hi>Mercies</hi> I had received,
for which I deſire to bleſs the Lords
Name. 1. He hath given me to be
born of <hi>Godly Parents.</hi> 2. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
had the <hi>means of Grace</hi> lengthen'd
out unto me. 3. The Lord hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly
pleaſed to give me ſome <hi>anſwers
of Prayer.</hi> 1. As to the lengthning out
of my <hi>Health.</hi> 2. As to the Increaſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55562:15"/>
of my <hi>Library, What ſhall I render to
the Lord</hi> for all his loving kindneſs
towards me? I reſolved to <hi>Dedicate</hi> my
ſelf wholly to God and his Service.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>And he did accordingly.</p>
                     <p>This Year did not roll about, before he
had in a manner very ſolemn entred in
to <hi>Covenant</hi> with God. This weighty
and awful thing was not raſhly done by
him, or in a ſudden <hi>Flaſh</hi> and <hi>Pang</hi> of
Devotion: He <hi>Thought,</hi> he <hi>Read,</hi> he <hi>Wrote,</hi>
and he <hi>Prayed</hi> not a little before this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Tranſaction between God and him,
and upon Mature Deliberation, he judged
it moſt adviſeable for him to make his
<hi>Covenant</hi> with God as <hi>Explicit</hi> as <hi>Writing</hi>
and <hi>Signing</hi> could render it; that ſo it
might leave the more Impreſſion upon his
<hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and be an Evidence like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
which in Temptation or Deſertion
he might have recourſe unto: Wherefore
he ſet apart a <hi>Time</hi> for (I think) ſecret
<hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> before the Lord, and
then behold how this <hi>Young Man</hi> count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it high time for him to be <hi>bound</hi> out
unto ſome <hi>Service,</hi> took a courſe for it:
He ſubſcribed an holy <hi>Covenant,</hi> of which
this was the <hi>Matter,</hi> this the <hi>Form.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="covenant">
                                 <head>The <hi>Covenrnt</hi> between God and my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55562:15"/>
Soul, renewed; confirmed, and ſigned,
<hi>Nov.</hi> 22. 1683.</head>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Whereas</hi> not only the <hi>Commands</hi> of
God, [who hath often called upon me,
by his <hi>Word Preached,</hi> to give up my
ſelf, both Body and Soul, to be at his
Diſpoſal, which <hi>calls</hi> by the publick
Miniſtry, were enough to engage me
unto this] but alſo the <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi>
which I profeſs, and my <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in
which I took the <hi>Lord</hi> to be my God,
and promiſed to Renounce the <hi>World,</hi>
the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
my ſelf unto the <hi>Service, Work,</hi> and
<hi>Will</hi> of God, do bind me hereunto; <hi>In
that</hi> God is <hi>ſuch a God</hi> as deſerves this,
yea infinitely more than this, at my
hands; my <hi>Creator,</hi> the Fountain of my
Being; my <hi>Preſerver,</hi> my Benefactor,
my <hi>Lord,</hi> my Soveraign, my Judge;
He in whoſe Hands my <hi>Life,</hi> my Breath,
and all my concerns are; He that doth
<hi>protect</hi> me from all Dangers, and <hi>ſupply</hi>
me in all wants, <hi>ſupport</hi> me under all
Burdens, and <hi>direct</hi> me in all ſtreights;
He alone that can make me <hi>happy</hi> or
<hi>miſerable;</hi> He alone that can <hi>ſave</hi> me
or <hi>damn</hi> me; He alone that can give
inward <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> that is my
Friend, my God; In that, Self-Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55562:16"/>
is the Creatures Advancement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
theſe <hi>Firſt-fruits,</hi> if in Sincerity, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
upon me a Gloriouſneſs and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>In that</hi> Felicity hereafter depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
my dedicating of my ſelf unto God
now.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>In that</hi> this is the higheſt piec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
of <hi>Gratitude</hi> I am capable of expreſſing
unto God, and I know no better way
to Obey the <hi>Will</hi> of God, than firſt to
give up my <hi>ſelf</hi> unto him.</p>
                                 <p>And <hi>whereas</hi> the <hi>Mercies</hi> which the
Lord hath been pleaſed graciouſly to
beſtow upon me, are ſo many, that
even <hi>bare Morality,</hi> doth ſhew me that
I can never enough requite one that
hath done ſo much for me, except by
<hi>giving up my ſelf wholly to him.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <label>[1669]</label>
                                       <hi>Whereas</hi> God hath given me a Godly
Father and Mother.</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <label>[1674]</label>
                                       <hi>In that</hi> when I was like to dye, being
twice ſick of a <hi>Feaver,</hi> God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to bleſs means for my Recovery,
and lengthen out the Thread of my Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <label>[1675]</label>
                                       <hi>Whereas,</hi> when I by an Accident fell
down, and had like to have been depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55562:16"/>
of the uſe of my <hi>Tongue,</hi> God was
in his good Providence graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to give me the uſe of it.</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <label>[1678]</label>
                                       <p>
                                          <hi>Whereas,</hi> when I was ſick of the <hi>Small-Pox,</hi>
God was pleaſed to bleſs means
for my Recovery.</p>
                                       <p>
                                          <hi>Whereas,</hi> then I made Promiſes unto
God, that if he would give me my
<hi>Health,</hi> I would endeavour to become
a <hi>New Creature,</hi> and he hath done ſo
for theſe <hi>five Years:</hi> And <hi>whereas</hi> God
hath of late been beſtowing many and
wonderful mercies upon me, <hi>What can
I do leſs than give up my ſelf wholly to
him?</hi>
                                       </p>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                                 <p>Which now I do.</p>
                                 <p>And, O Lord God, I beſeech thee
to accept of thy Poor <hi>Prodigal,</hi> now
proſtrating of himſelf before thee. I
confeſs, O Lord, I have fallen from
thee by my Iniquity, and am by nature
a <hi>Son of Hell;</hi> but of thy Infinite Grace
thou haſt promiſed Mercy to me in
Chriſt, if I will but turn unto thee with
all my Heart: Therefore upon the Call
of thy Goſpel, <hi>I come in,</hi> and from
the bottom of my Heart I renounce all
thy <hi>Enemies;</hi> with whom I confeſs I
have wickedly ſided againſt thee, firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55562:17"/>
                                    <hi>Covenanting</hi> with thee, not to allo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
my ſelf in any known Sin, but co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ſcientiouſly
to uſe all means which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
know thou haſt preſcribed, for the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ter
deſtruction of all my Corruptions.</p>
                                 <p>And whereas I have inordinately I
out my Affections upon the World,
here reſign my Heart unto thee th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
made it; humbly Proteſting before t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
Glorious Majeſty, that it is the fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <hi>Reſolution</hi> of my Heart (and that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
unfeignedly deſire <hi>Grace</hi> from thee, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
when thou ſhalt call me thereunto,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> may put in <hi>practice</hi> my Reſolution
through thine Aſſiſtance, to forſake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
that is dear unto me in the World, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ther
than to turn from thee to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <hi>ways of ſin;</hi> and that I will watch again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
all it's <hi>Temptations,</hi> whether of <hi>Proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
or <hi>Adverſity,</hi> leſt they ſhould wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>draw
my Heart from thee, beſeechi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
thee to help me.</p>
                                 <p>I renounce all my own <hi>Righteouſneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                    </hi>
and acknowledge that of my ſelf I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
helpleſs and undone, and without Rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>teouſneſs.</p>
                                 <p>And whereas, of thy bottomleſs Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
thou haſt offer'd to accept of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
and to be reconciled to me, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
be my God, <hi>through Chriſt,</hi> if I woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55562:17"/>
accept of thee, I do this day <hi>avouch
thee to be the Lord my God.</hi> I do here
take the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> Father, Son, and
Holy Ghoſt, for my portion and chief
Good, and do give up my ſelf <hi>Body</hi>
and <hi>Soul</hi> for thy Servant, promiſing to
endeavour to ſerve thee in <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>
and <hi>Holineſs.</hi> I do here alſo on the
bended knees of my Soul, accept of
the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the only and
living <hi>Way,</hi> by which ſinners may have
acceſs to thee, and do here joyn my
ſelf in a <hi>Marriage-Covenant</hi> with him.
O Lord Jeſus, I come to thee, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,
poor, miſerable, blind, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
and a moſt loathſome Creature,
a condemned Malefactor: <hi>Who am I,
that I ſhould be Married unto the King of
Glory!</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>I do accept of thee for my <hi>Head</hi> and
<hi>Husband,</hi> and embrace thee in all thy
Offices. I renounce my own <hi>Worthineſs,</hi>
and do chooſe thee the <hi>Lord my Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
I do renounce my own <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi>
and do take thine for my Guide. I
take thy <hi>Will</hi> for my Will, and thy
<hi>Word</hi> for my Law. I do here willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
put my Neck under thy <hi>Yoke;</hi> I do
ſubſcribe to all thy Laws as <hi>Holy, Juſt,</hi>
and <hi>Good;</hi> and do promiſe to take them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55562:18"/>
as the <hi>Rule</hi> of my <hi>Thoughts, Words,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <hi>Actions;</hi> but becauſe I am ſubject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
many <hi>failings,</hi> through frailty; I do he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
proteſt, here before thee, that <hi>unallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ed
miſcarriages,</hi> contrary to the conſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent
of my Heart, ſhall not diſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
this everlaſting Covenant.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>Nathanael Mathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                    </signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>It may juſtly be taken for granted, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
ſuch a work as this, would have an infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ence
into his <hi>Converſation</hi> afterwards
and <hi>ſo it had,</hi> producing in him, a <hi>Conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſation
which became the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
kept waiting upon God, not only in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Family,</hi> but alſo under the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
that were near a-Kinn unto him; namely
his <hi>Father</hi> and his <hi>Brother,</hi> whereby th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Grace thus begun in him was not a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tle
cheriſhed and promoted: And unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
all <hi>known ſins</hi> he now kept ſaying, as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
find once in Short-hand written by him.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>To my Luſts.</head>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>I have had Communion with you all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>
while, but I dare not have ſo any longer
Wherefore I renounce all Communion with y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>
any more; I will cleave to the God that made m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                    </hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>But a Year or two after this, it was wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
him, as I have obſerved it is too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55562:18"/>
with ſuch as are <hi>Converted betimes</hi>
unto God. An unhappy gradual <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi>
carried him aſide from thoſe degrees
of ſeriouſneſs and intenſeneſs in divine
things, which he had been uſed unto:
'Tis poſſible an entanglement in a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity
with ſome that were no better
than they ſhould be, did abate of the
<hi>good ſavour</hi> which had been upon him, and
decoy him by <hi>inſenſible ſteps</hi> to ſome vanities
(tho' not to any ſcandalous immoralities)
that were diſadvantageous to him. For
divers <hi>Months</hi> he ſeemed ſomewhat, yet
not <hi>totally,</hi> much leſs <hi>finally,</hi> forſaken of
that <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
been an example of; but the good
Spirit of God will not let go his <hi>Intereſt</hi>
in a Soul of which he hath taken a
ſaving hold. This Young Man ſoon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained
juſt reſentments of his own
declenſions, and it was impoſſible for
the moſt <hi>Badger-tooth'd malice</hi> in the
World to aggravate any of his Errors
half ſo much as he did himſelf in his own
Repentance for them. In the Year 1685.
God viſited him with ſore Terrors and
Horrors in his <hi>wounded</hi> Soul, the anguiſh
whereof he thought intolerable; yet he
made not his condition known to any
Body all the while. He could ſay, <hi>My
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55562:19"/>
complaint is not to man,</hi> but he made it
unto the Lord; <hi>This poor man cryed and
the Lord heard, and delivered him out of
his diſtreſſes.</hi> He arrived in time unto
ſome ſettlement and renewal of his <hi>Peace</hi>
with God: He confeſſed and bewailed his
own ſins before the Lord, and declared
his deteſtation of them, and applyed
himſelf unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for
Salvation from them all. <hi>Good terms</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thus eſtabliſh't between the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Lord and this Immortal Soul, he
maintained, I think, a conſtant and an
even <hi>Walk with God,</hi> until he dyed. I
find now that Language in his MSS: <hi>Let
me be as active a Servant of Christ, as I
was of Satan heretofore.</hi> For more than the
<hi>three laſt years</hi> of his Life, he lived at a
ſtrange rate for Holineſs and Gravity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and retired Devotions. He read Mr.
<hi>Scudders</hi> Chriſtians <hi>daily walk,</hi> and Dr.
<hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Mindedneſs,</hi> and had a
reſtleſs raging Agony in his Mind unti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
the Methods of Religion adviſed by thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
worthy Men, were Exemplified in his
own Behaviour. 'Tis a note in one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
his Diaries,</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">O my great <hi>unprofitableneſs</hi> under th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
means of Grace! I have cauſe to bleſs God
for ever for the Writings of that never
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55562:19"/>
enough to be admired and loved by <hi>me,</hi>
Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> and for the Light I have
received thereby, concerning the <hi>ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of Sin;</hi> as alſo that excellent Book
of him whom I ſhall always honour, Dr.
<hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Spiritual-mindedneſs,</hi> and Mr.
<hi>Scudders</hi> Chriſtians <hi>daily Walk,</hi> by which
three Books I have profited more than
by any other <hi>(S. Scripturis exceptis)</hi> in
the World.</q>
                     <p>He was at firſt ſurprized, at the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of <hi>Spiritual-mindedneſs,</hi> without which
that <hi>great Saint,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen!</hi> apprehends
the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of Souls to labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
prejudice; and he thought a Mind
ſwallowed up in ſuch <hi>Heavenly</hi> Frames
and Works as were needful thereunto,
almoſt wholly to be deſpair'd of; until
(as himſelf a few hours before he dyed
ſaid unto me) he deem'd he ſaw an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
of ſuch a <hi>Walk with God,</hi> not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
far from the place of his abode: To
which purpoſe his reſerv'd Papers have
a large Diſcourſe, of which this is in the
Concluſion: <hi>There might be a greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs
in Religion, than is commonly thought
for. What have I Examples for, but to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
them?</hi> Abraham <hi>is fam'd for believing
ſo ſtrongly, when he had no Example before
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55562:20"/>
him: Let me try and ſee, whether I having
ſuch opportunities may not arrive to as high
a pitch in Chriſtianity, as any that I have
known.</hi> He then in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and thrô
the Love of God ſet himſelf into a vvay
of ſtrict, ſecret, laborious Devotion
vvhereby thô none but <hi>God</hi> and <hi>He</hi> fill'd
the <hi>Theatre,</hi> vvhich he acted upon, he
vvould be <hi>in the Fear of the Lord all the
day long.</hi> He withdrew from the delight
of this World, and gave himſelf up to
an aſſiduous <hi>Contemplation</hi> of God and
Chriſt, and a ſedulous endeavour after
utmoſt conformity unto him: Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
kept <hi>abounding in the Work of the Lord</hi>
until three Years of wonderful <hi>Holineſs</hi>
had ripened him for eternal <hi>Happineſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>My Account of him will be an <hi>unfiniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Piece,</hi> unleſs all the enſuing ſtroke
go to make it up. Theſe things he was
Exemplary for.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> He was one that <hi>walked by R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LE</hi>
He was very Studious to learn the <hi>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
of converſing with God in every Duty
and there vvas a <hi>Rule</hi> which he attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
ſtill unto.</p>
                     <p>In his private Papers, I find a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
Collection of <hi>Rules,</hi> by which he gover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed
himſelf in the ſeveral Duties of Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtianity,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55562:20"/>
and in all the <hi>Seaſons</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
of his Life. He conſulted the beſt
Authors for Inſtruction in the Affairs of
<hi>practical Religion,</hi> and not into <hi>Paper</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
but into <hi>Action</hi> to be tranſcribed
what he moſt approved; in all which
<hi>The Will of God</hi> was the bright Pole-Star
by which he ſteer'd his Courſe.</p>
                     <p>The Reader ſhall <hi>enjoy</hi> (and O that
he would <hi>follow)</hi> two of this Young Man's
<hi>Directories:</hi> One of them was this.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>I. O that I might lead a <hi>ſpiritual Life!</hi>
Wherefore let me regulate my Life by
the <hi>Word</hi> of God and by ſuch Scriptures
as theſe.</p>
                        <p>1. <hi>For regulating my</hi> Thoughts, <hi>Jer. 4.
14.</hi> Iſa. 55. 7. Mal. 3. 17. Pſal. 104. 34.
Phil. 4. 8. Prov. 23. 26. Deut. 15. 9. Eccleſ.
10. 20. Prov. 24. 9. Mat. 9. 4. Zech. 8. 17.</p>
                        <p>2. For regulating my <hi>Affections,</hi> Col.
3. 2, 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24.</p>
                        <p>For my <hi>Delight,</hi> Pſal. 1. 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 5.
For my <hi>Joy,</hi> Phil. 4. 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43. 4. My
<hi>Deſire,</hi> Iſa. 26. 8, 9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 16. My
<hi>Love,</hi> Mat. 22. 37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 97. My <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,</hi>
Pſal. 97. 10. My <hi>Fear,</hi> Luk. 12. 4, 5.
My <hi>Hope,</hi> Pſal. 39. 7. My <hi>Truſt,</hi> Pſal.
62. 8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 4.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi>For regulating my</hi> Speech, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55562:21"/>
29. Col. 4. 6. Deut. 6. 6, 7. Pſal. 119. 46.
Pſal. 71. 8, 24. Prov. 31. 26.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi>For regulating my</hi> Work, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 8.
2 Tim. 2. 12. 1 Tim. 5. 10. Titus 2. 14.
Mat. 5. 47. 1 Tim. 6. 8. Rev. 3. 2.
Rom. 13. 12. Act. 26. 20.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>Another of them was form'd into an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Hymn,</hi> the ſinging of which might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
freſher and ſtronger <hi>Efforts</hi> of Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
towards <hi>the thing that is good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It ſhall be here inſerted.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Lord,</hi> vvhat ſhall I return unto</l>
                           <l>Him from vvhom all thy mercies flow?</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>(I.) To me to <hi>live,</hi> it <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall be</l>
                           <l>For all I do I'le do for <hi>Thee.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>(II.) My Queſtion ſhall be oft beſide,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>How thou may'ſt moſt be Glorifi'd?</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>(III.) I will not any Creature Love,</l>
                           <l>But <hi>in the love</hi> of Thee above.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>(IV.) Thy <hi>Will</hi> I will embrace for <hi>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And every management of thine</l>
                           <l>Shall pleaſe me. (V.) A <hi>Conformity</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>To Thee ſhall be my <hi>Aim</hi> and <hi>Eye.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55562:21"/>
                           <l>(VI.) <hi>Ejaculations</hi> ſhall aſcend</l>
                           <l>Not ſeldom from me. (VII.) I'le attend</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Occaſional Reflections,</hi> and</l>
                           <l>Turn all to <hi>Gold</hi> that comes to hand.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>(VIII.) And in particular among</l>
                           <l>My Cares, I'le try to make my <hi>Tongue</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>A <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> by ſpeaking all</l>
                           <l>As be accountable who ſhall.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>(IX.) But <hi>laſt,</hi> nay <hi>firſt</hi> of all, I will</l>
                           <l>Thy <hi>Son</hi> my <hi>Surety</hi> make, and ſtill</l>
                           <l>Implore him, that he would me bleſs</l>
                           <l>With ſtrength as well as <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                     <p>Beſides theſe <hi>Rules</hi> which concerned his
<hi>whole Walk,</hi> he Treaſur'd up many more,
that referr'd to this and that <hi>ſtep</hi> in it;
and it was the predominant care and
watch of his Heart, not to <hi>tread awry:</hi>
Thus one might ſee a <hi>skilful Chriſtian</hi> in
him. And as he was deſirous to live by
<hi>Precept,</hi> ſo he was to live by <hi>Promiſe</hi>
too.</p>
                     <p>He fell into a particular conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
how to improve the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God in
all the <hi>Occaſions</hi> of life; which is indeed
one of the moſt <hi>ſanctifying Exerciſes</hi> in the
World.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55562:22"/>
It was a Propoſal vvhich I find he mad
unto himſelf.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>Let me ſalute theſe <hi>Promiſes</hi> once a
day.</p>
                        <p>1. For ſupplying the <hi>wants</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
day, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 19.</p>
                        <p>2. For Grovvth in <hi>Grace, Hoſ. 14. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. For ſubduing my <hi>ſins, Mic. 7. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>4. For <hi>ſucceſs</hi> in my undertakings
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
                        <p>5. For turning all the Events of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
day for <hi>good, Rom.</hi> 8. 28.</p>
                        <p>6. For Audience of my <hi>Prayers, Job<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
14. 13, 14.</p>
                        <p>7. For <hi>ſtrength</hi> to manage all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
vvork of the day, <hi>Zech.</hi> 10. 12.</p>
                        <p>8. For direction in <hi>difficulty, Pſal</hi>
32. 8.</p>
                        <p>9. For <hi>Life Eternal,</hi> Luke 12. 31. <hi>Job<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
3. 16.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Beſides theſe tvvo,</hi> Mat. 11. 28. <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
Iſa. 44. 3.</p>
                     <p>Certainly that Man muſt quickly gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
another <hi>Enoch,</hi> vvho does thus <hi>Walk wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> He vvas one that <hi>lived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
PRAYER.</hi> He vvas oft and long in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mount with God:</hi> It vvas his Cuſtom eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
day to <hi>enter into his Cloſet, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:55562:22"/>
his door, and pray to his Father in ſecret.</hi>
And I gueſs from ſome of his Writings,
that he did thus no leſs than <hi>thrice</hi> a
day, when he met with no Obſtruction
in it: Nor did he Slubber over his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
vvith haſty <hi>Amputations,</hi> but vvreſtle
in them for a good part of an hour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                     <p>It vvas a moſt refreſhing Communion
vvith God, vvhich his Devotions brought
him ſometimes unto. Thus in one of his
<hi>Diaries.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>
                                    <date>Dec. 10.</date>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>I <hi>prayed</hi> earneſtly unto God,<note place="margin">In the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin he wrote, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this.</hi>
                                    </note> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
Petitioning that Jeſus Chriſt
might be my <hi>compleat Redeemer.</hi> There
vvas immediately <hi>ſomething that did as
it were perſwade me it ſhould be ſo.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>Again, <date>Aug. 19.</date>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>My <hi>Thoughts</hi> vvere ſome little vvhile
buſied about the <hi>condeſcention of Chriſt
in taking of humane Nature on him;</hi> but
for the moſt part in <hi>Ejaculations,</hi> and
Acts of Faith on a <hi>crucified</hi> (ah! ſvveet
Word) <hi>Jeſus.</hi> I ſaw I gained not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55562:23"/>
much by thoſe: Wherefore I addre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
my ſelf to <hi>ſolemn Prayer,</hi> and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
ſome <hi>Aſſurance</hi> in it.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>Once more, <date>Aug. 20.</date>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>I was much affected in <hi>Prayer,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
exerciſed (I hope) many Acts of <hi>Faith</hi>
and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Delight</hi> in God. I ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>ral
times was breaking off, but I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
it were <hi>conſtrain'd</hi> to go on in the Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>
with much enlargement. <hi>Lord, anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>
me for the ſake of Chriſt.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Thus under the <hi>Fig-tree</hi> did our Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Jeſus often behold this <hi>Nathanael;</hi> yea un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
Prayer he became ſo habituated, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
while others can <hi>Sleep</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> he ſome
times would <hi>pray</hi> in <hi>ſleep.</hi> He records <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
among his Experiences, that upon aſſault
of <hi>imagined Temptations,</hi> when he has bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
aſleep, he has quickly been at Prayer; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
ſo cauſed the <hi>Phantaſms</hi> to leave annoy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
of him.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Extraordinary prayer</hi> was alſo wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
him not altogether <hi>extraordinary.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
he were a <hi>Bottle</hi> that ſeemed incapabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
of holding it, yet this <hi>Wine</hi> agreed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
him very well. As <hi>Young</hi> as he was, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
knew the Myſtery of a Soul <hi>fatning</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:55562:23"/>
                        <hi>faſting,</hi> and <hi>thriving</hi> by <hi>hungring and thirst<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
after Righteouſneſs.</hi> He was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive
after the right way to manage
a <hi>Day of Fasting and Prayer,</hi> and he would
ſometimes keep ſuch a day. On <hi>ſuch
a day</hi> it was his Cuſtom to make a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
particular and penitent <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of
all the Sins that he could perceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
guilty of; and renew his <hi>Covenant</hi>
with the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> to this
End, he had by him in writing a large
<hi>Catalogue</hi> of things forbidden and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
in the <hi>Commandments</hi> of God,
which was the <hi>Glaſs</hi> in which he then
viewed his wayes; and having found
what <hi>Achans</hi> might procure <hi>trouble</hi> to
him, he then fell to ſtoning of them.
One may ſhape ſome conjecture at his
<hi>Humiliations,</hi> by the <hi>Indignations</hi> with
which he ſpoke, and wrote of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities</hi>
which his <hi>Childhood</hi> had. <q rend="margQuotes">I came
into the World </q>(ſaith he in one of the
Papers penn'd by him on a <hi>day of ſecret
Faſting and Prayer, October</hi> the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1685.)<q rend="margQuotes">without the <hi>Image</hi> of the Holy God
on my Soul; my Underſtanding, my
Will, my Affections, and my <hi>whole Soul</hi>
were altogether depraved, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
When very <hi>Young</hi> I went aſtray
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55562:24"/>
from God, and my Mind was altogether
taken with <hi>vanities</hi> and <hi>follies;</hi> ſuch as
the remembrance of them doth greatly
abaſe my Soul within me. Of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold
Sins which then I was guilty of,
none ſo ſticks upon me, as that being
very young, I was <hi>whitling on the Sabbath-day;</hi>
and for fear of being ſeen, I did
it behind the door. A great Reproach
of God! A Specimen of that <hi>Atheiſm</hi>
that I brought into the World with
me!</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>This was more than the more meagre
and feeble ſort of Chriſtians, though much
older than he, are us'd to do. But <hi>paulo
majora!</hi> There was a Sublimer way of
<hi>drawing near to God,</hi> which he vvas not
willing to leave unattempted. He un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
that <hi>ſecret days of Thanksgiving</hi>
had not been unpractiſed by ſome vvhom
he deſigned to imitate; and therefore he
vvould make ſome <hi>Eſſays</hi> for ſuch an Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<hi>Fruition</hi> of God, and generous <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
to him, as vvould fill ſuch days as
theſe.</p>
                     <p>Hence this I find among the Records of
his Soul:—</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Reſolved,</hi> To ſet apart every two
Months, a <hi>Day</hi> for ſolemn Examination
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55562:24"/>
and Meditation, to <hi>humble</hi> my ſelf; and
every tvvo Months to keep a Day of
<hi>private Thanksgiving.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>But though his Prayers were chiefly <hi>in,</hi>
yet they were not confined <hi>to</hi> his Cloſet.
There vvere divers Private Praying <hi>Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
of younger People in <hi>North-Boſton,</hi>
vvhich he viſited as often as he could;
and one of thoſe might peculiarly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>His.</hi> Yea, it vvas his deſire, though
vvith as little aim <hi>to be ſeen of men</hi> as
could be, to ſupport all ſuch opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of Good among them, that vvere of
the ſame age with him.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore I find this among the Notes
in his <hi>Diary:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſhall I do for God?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> It vvas ſuggeſted to me, to get
ſome of my Acquaintance to ſpend ſome
vvhile every <hi>Friday</hi> night in Prayer, for
the Succeſs of the Work of Grace in
<hi>New-England,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>Boſton,</hi> on
the <hi>Souls of the Riſing Generation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let me propound this to ſome ſerious
devout young Perſons.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>Thus vvas his <hi>Prayer</hi> as it vvere his
<hi>Breath,</hi> and thus he vvas always fetching
of it, untll at laſt it expir'd in <hi>Praiſe,
Praiſe</hi> for evermore.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:55562:25"/>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He was one that <hi>Thought much
of his GOD, and his END.</hi> There was
a ſort of <hi>Heaven</hi> formed in the <hi>juſt Soul</hi> of
this Young-man, by the <hi>Thoughts</hi> that were
continually ſparkling there. He had an
unpacifiable Diſſatisfaction at himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
<hi>good Thoughts</hi> were lodg'd in him, and
<hi>vain ones</hi> were forced to <hi>gnaſh their teeth,
and melt away:</hi> Nothing would content
him, but the bringing of his <hi>Thoughts into
a Subjection to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he chew'd much on the excellent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
of Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> about <hi>Thoughts;</hi>
which he <hi>wrote out</hi> not only with his <hi>hand,</hi>
but in his <hi>heart,</hi> and made it the very
<hi>Mould</hi> of his gracious Mind. There are
none, but very <hi>Renew'd Souls,</hi> that are at
great pains in a courſe of <hi>Meditation</hi> on
the things of God. Yet this Young-man,
like another <hi>Iſaac,</hi> vvas grovvn very <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert</hi>
at it, and <hi>frequent</hi> in it. It was his
manner in the Morning to <hi>meditate</hi> very
ſeriouſly and fixedly upon ſome <hi>Truth,</hi> or
ſome <hi>Text,</hi> for a good part of an hour
together. He had collected a good va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
of <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Scriptures</hi> to handle in
thus <hi>communing with himſelf,</hi> and went
over more than a little <hi>Divinity</hi> in this
tranſcendent Exerciſe. Sometimes, when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55562:25"/>
thus he <hi>ſeparated himſelf to intermeddle with
all wiſdom,</hi> I find him committing his
<hi>Thoughts,</hi> or ſome <hi>breviate</hi> of them, unto
the durable cuſtody of his Papers; from
vvhich <hi>Memoirs</hi> I vvill produce but an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
or tvvo of many.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>
                                    <date>Auguſt 16. 1685.</date>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Med.</hi> about, <hi>The reaſon I have to love
God;</hi> becauſe of what he has been to
me, and what he is in himſelf. And I
thought, Is not God the <hi>Beſt Good?</hi>
Surely then he is worthy to be my
<hi>Laſt End.</hi> Has he not been ſhewing
many <hi>Mercies</hi> to me? and what! ſhall
I not reſign up my ſelf to <hi>Live</hi> unto
God, becauſe of his goodneſs to me?
<hi>Much affected with the thoughts of theſe
things:</hi> And, I hope, I cloſed with the
Motion.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>Again, October 1.</head>
                                 <p>Meditated <hi>on that;</hi> If a Man does in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to be truly Religious, he muſt expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but to ſave his Soul?</p>
                                 <p>But how can this be true?</p>
                                 <p>Muſt I loſe my <hi>Body</hi> altogether?</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55562:26"/>
Muſt I be vvilling that the <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
my <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> ſhould for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more
be looſed?</p>
                                 <p>Muſt I be willing to be for ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a <hi>Body?</hi> No, no.</p>
                                 <p>All that the Lord requires of me, is,
to have my <hi>Body</hi> for a <hi>few</hi> days or years
(a <hi>few</hi> I ſay, for they cannot be <hi>many,)</hi>
to be wholly at the <hi>ſervice</hi> of my <hi>Soul,</hi>
and to be willing that the <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between
thoſe two <hi>Mates,</hi> then ſhould be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
the <hi>Soul</hi> firſt taking its progreſs
into everlaſting Bliſs; the <hi>Body</hi> being
laid in the Duſt, to riſe at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
accompanying the <hi>Soul</hi> into its
eternal Felicity.</p>
                                 <p>My preſent Notion of this thing is
this:</p>
                                 <p>This <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the Union between
the Soul and Body, is but a <hi>Diſmiſſion</hi> of
the Spirit into its happineſs, after a
weariſom conflict here. And as long as
it ſhall be beſt for me to be here, here
I ſhall continue. Infinite <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is to
be the Orderer of this; and it will be
a grievous and ſhamefu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> reflection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon,
for me to ſay, <hi>It will be better for
me to live, than to dye,</hi> at ſuch a time
when I am called thereunto.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <pb n="37" facs="tcp:55562:26"/>
With my <hi>Body</hi> I muſt expect to loſe
all the pleaſant Enjoyments of this
World, <hi>Liberty, Library, Study,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</hi>
But yet neither ſhall I loſe theſe.
As for my <hi>Liberty,</hi> by True Religion,
and by Dying for it too, when need
requires, I ſhall gain the only <hi>Liberty,</hi>
even from the <hi>body of ſin.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>As for my <hi>Library,</hi> if I die <hi>for</hi> Chriſt,
or <hi>in the</hi> Lord, I ſhall have no need of
it. My Underſtanding ſhall be enough
<hi>enlarged,</hi> and I ſhall not need to turn
over <hi>Books</hi> for Learning. As for my
<hi>Study</hi> (my <hi>Paradice)</hi> I ſhall have a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
a larger, and a more compleat than
this.</p>
                                 <p>As for my <hi>Relations,</hi> thoſe of them
that are <hi>truly pious,</hi> I ſhall only <hi>go before</hi>
them; and if there ſhould be any of
them not <hi>pious,</hi> the longer I ſhould ſtay
with them here (if they continue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent)
it would but make my Grief
more intolerable, to think vvhen I leave
them, that <hi>I ſhall have no hopes to ſee
them again for ever.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>But this is not all neither.—</p>
                                 <p>My <hi>Body</hi> muſt be uſed as the <hi>Souls In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument;</hi>
and here all that <hi>ſtrength</hi> and
<hi>
                                       <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>aſe</hi> vvhich I have, muſt be uſed for the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55562:27"/>
Soul: And truly there is reaſon enough
for it, that ſo there may be eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
for <hi>both</hi> together.</p>
                                 <p>In <hi>Marriage,</hi> the Husband and Wife
ſhould have the <hi>ſame deſign.</hi> Would it
not be inhumane, for the one to have
a deſign which tends to the ruine of the
other? Juſt ſo my <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> ſhould
have the <hi>ſame deſign;</hi> and the <hi>Body</hi> being
the more vile of the <hi>two,</hi> ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
to the <hi>Soul.</hi> And it is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
disjunction, either the <hi>Body,</hi> the
<hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>eaſe,</hi> and <hi>members</hi> of it,
muſt be uſed for the good, or for the
<hi>hurt</hi> of the Soul; there is no <hi>medium
here.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>Let me then herein make my <hi>Body</hi>
uſeful to my <hi>Soul,</hi> in accompliſhing all
the <hi>good-deſigns</hi> of it, which it is capable
of being intereſted in.</p>
                                 <p>Nor is there any thing elſe worth
ſpeaking of that muſt be foregone, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<hi>health,</hi> and the <hi>momentaneouſneſs</hi> of
all bodily Torments, will make <hi>them</hi>
very tolerable.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>My Reſolutions be,
That</hi> I will not expect, by devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
my ſelf unto the Fear of God, to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55562:27"/>
gain any thing as to my <hi>Body</hi> in this
World.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>That</hi> through the Grace of Chriſt, I
will uſe the <hi>ſtrength, eaſe, health</hi> of my
<hi>Body,</hi> yea my <hi>whole Body,</hi> in Subordination
to my Soul, in the Service of the Lord
Jeſus.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>With ſuch <hi>Meditations</hi> as theſe, he kept
<hi>mellowing</hi> of his own Soul, and preparing
it for the ſtate wherein <hi>Faith</hi> is turned into
<hi>Sight.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But there was yet a more delightful and
ſurprizing way of <hi>Thinking,</hi> after which
he did aſpire. He conſidered, that the
whole <hi>Creation</hi> was full of God; and
that there was not a Leaf of <hi>Graſs</hi> in the
Field, which might not make an Obſerver
to be ſenſible of the Lord. He apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
that the <hi>idle Minutes</hi> of our Lives were
many more than a ſhort liver ſhould allow:
That the very Filings of <hi>Gold,</hi> and of <hi>Time,</hi>
were exceeding precious; and, that there
were little <hi>fragments of hours</hi> intervening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
our more ſtated buſineſſes, wherein
<hi>Thoughts</hi> of God might be no leſs plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
than frequent with us.</p>
                     <p>The Elegant and Excellent Meditations
of Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> had particularly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55562:28"/>
affected him unto a commendable Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of them; and hence he did attempt
to make even the more <hi>common</hi> and more
<hi>trivial</hi> occurrents of humane Life, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
of <hi>Great Thoughts</hi> within him. He
would with the <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> of <hi>Occaſional Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,</hi>
Diſtill <hi>ſublime Spirits</hi> from <hi>earthly
Bodies;</hi> and from the view of mean things,
fill his nobly imployed Mind with <hi>Leſſons</hi>
and <hi>Prayers,</hi> which only the <hi>Father of Spirits</hi>
was a Witneſs to.</p>
                     <p>Some of theſe his <hi>Occaſional Reflections</hi>
I find in his private Papers; and one or
two, for a <hi>taſte,</hi> I will beſpeak the Reader's
acceptance of.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>Jan. 8. A. M.</head>
                                 <p>Being about to riſe, I felt the <hi>cold</hi> in
a manner extraordinary; which inclin'd
me to ſeek more <hi>warmth</hi> in my Bed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I roſe; but ſo extream was the
<hi>cold,</hi> that this was not feaſible: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I reſolved to <hi>dreſs</hi> my ſelf without
any more ado; and ſo going to the
<hi>Fire</hi> in my Cloaths, I ſoon became warm
enough.</p>
                                 <p>Turn this, <hi>O my Soul,</hi> into an uſeful
Meditation. There is a neceſſity of my
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55562:28"/>
                                    <hi>riſing</hi> out of my Bed, the Bed of <hi>Security</hi>
which I am under the power of, and
to <hi>live</hi> unto Chriſt, and to <hi>walk</hi> in the
Light.</p>
                                 <p>In order hereunto, I muſt put on my
poor Soul the <hi>Garments</hi> which are to be
had from the Lord Jeſus. To awaken
me out of my <hi>ſleep,</hi> and my <hi>ſecurity,</hi> I
am to ſet before me the <hi>Sun,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel
of the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten
my Mind, and tell me, that I
was before muffled up in <hi>darkneſs;</hi> and
that if I continued therein, I ſhould
ſtarve and periſh. I am alſo taught, That
when Men are <hi>convinced</hi> of their miſerable
condition, they will rather endeavour
to Eaſe, and comfort and cheriſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
by ſomething <hi>in themſelves,</hi> than
put on the <hi>ſpiritual Garments</hi> which
the Lord Jeſus Chriſt has provided for
them. An Evil to be by me avoided.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>Again, another time.</head>
                                 <p>Upon <hi>Water</hi> taken from the <hi>Fire,</hi> I
ſaw a <hi>lukewarmneſs</hi> quickly ſeize; like
the frame of Spirit, which many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders
to Religion have after a glorious
and affectionate <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of it. Of this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55562:29"/>
ſort were ſome among the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> of
old; which is exceedingly diſpleaſing
to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Whence it is
that he ſaith, <hi>I will ſpew thee out of my
mouth.</hi> Let me endeavour to beware
of this hateful and odious frame of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
and let the contrary thereto be
my deſire, my endeavour.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>Once more.</head>
                                 <p>Among ſome Gentlemen that were
ſitting in a Room illuminated with a
Candle, one beginning to read unto us,
there was <hi>another Candle</hi> brought unto
him, for his aſſiſtance in it. Which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded
me ſuch a Meditation as this:</p>
                                 <p>That thoſe who are to be <hi>Teachers</hi> of
others, have need of <hi>as much light again</hi>
as ordinary Chriſtians have. They, if
any, need a <hi>double Portion</hi> of the <hi>Gifts</hi>
that are in other Men; and the helps
of Knowledge that other Perſons have,
they much more ſhould be furniſh'd
withal.</p>
                                 <p>It was not becauſe they had <hi>better Eyes</hi>
than him whoſe Office it was to Read,
that they needed but <hi>one Candle,</hi> when
he had <hi>two</hi> provided for him; but the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55562:29"/>
Work incumbent on him, and expected
from him was the occaſion of it.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>But I deſign little more than a <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi>
with an <hi>Illuſtration</hi> of my <hi>Hiſtory,</hi>
for which, a touch or two upon every
Article will ſerve. I am now to add,
That this Young Man had a Principal
regard unto the <hi>Scriptures</hi> for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
of his <hi>Meditations,</hi> and he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
expenſive of his Thoughts on the <hi>Book
of God.</hi> He was daily digging in the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
Mines,</hi> and with delight he fetched
thence Riches better than thoſe of both the
<hi>India</hi>'s; and he could ſay, <hi>O how I love thy
Law! it is my Meditation every day!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Even in the time of his mortal Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
he was very angry at himſelf if
he had not heard a Portion of the <hi>Bible</hi>
read unto him from day to day.</p>
                     <p>Once when he was near his End, a
good part of a day having paſs'd before
he had enjoyed his <hi>Meal</hi> of Scripture;
he ſaid unto his Siſter with ſome impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<hi>Alas! what an ungodly life do I lead!
pray come and read my Bible to me; and
read me the forty ninth Pſalm.</hi> Indeed he
read the Scripture not <hi>curſorily,</hi> but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
deliberately, and conſiderately; and
as an effect of his doing ſo, he could
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55562:30"/>
give ſuch an account of the <hi>Difficulties</hi> in it,
as the moſt not only of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but of
<hi>Divines</hi> too, would judge an <hi>Attainment ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.</hi>
Not long before he dyed,
he had read over all the large and great
<hi>Annotations</hi> on the Bible, lately publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> and ſome other Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt
Miniſters; but having diſpatched
thoſe two noble <hi>Folios,</hi> he ſaid unto one
that was intimate with him, <hi>Thus have
I read the Bible, but I have now learnt a
better way!</hi> And <hi>that way</hi> was this. He
would oblige himſelf in reading to fetch
a <hi>Note</hi> and a <hi>Prayer</hi> out of every <hi>Verſe</hi>
in all the Bible; to dwell upon every verſe
until it had afforded at leaſt one <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi>
and one <hi>Ejaculation</hi> to him.</p>
                     <p>He imagined that an incredible deal
both of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> would in this
way make its impreſſion upon his
Mind, (beſides what Exerciſe of <hi>Wit</hi> it
muſt have call'd for) and ſo moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
it would have done; but before
he had made much Progreſs in it, the
<hi>Chariots of God</hi> fetcht him away to that
place in which a <hi>Jeſus</hi> is a <hi>Bible</hi> to the
there <hi>perfect Spirits</hi> of the Righteous.</p>
                     <p>Such a <hi>thinking</hi> Perſon was he; and yet
after ſo many kind of <hi>Thoughts</hi> in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55562:30"/>
day, he could not reſt a Night quietly,
unleſs he compos'd himſelf for <hi>ſleeping</hi>
by <hi>thinking</hi> a little more.</p>
                     <p>He knew that no better a Man than
one of the <hi>Moral Heathens</hi> propounded a
<hi>Nocturnal Self-Examination,</hi> as a <hi>part</hi> and
<hi>cauſe</hi> of no little Wiſdom, and that much
more a <hi>ſober Chriſtian</hi> ſhould endeavour
to maintain a good <hi>underſtanding</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
by ſuch <hi>Nightly Recollections.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
before the <hi>Slumbers</hi> of the Evening,
this Young Man would put <hi>three General
Queſtions</hi> to himſelf, with divers <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi>
ones that were ſubordinate thereunto.
The Queſtions were,</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="questions">
                                 <div n="1" type="question">
                                    <head>Queſtion 1.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>What has God's Mercy to me been this
day?</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>Here he conſidered what <hi>favours</hi> God
had newly ſmil'd upon his <hi>inward,</hi> or his
<hi>outward</hi> man withal.</p>
                                 </div>
                                 <div n="2" type="question">
                                    <head>Queſtion 2.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>What has my Carriage to God been this day?</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>Here he conſidered what <hi>frames,</hi> and
<hi>words</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> and what <hi>ſnares</hi> and <hi>ſins</hi>
he had newly been concerned with.</p>
                                 </div>
                                 <div n="3" type="question">
                                    <head>Queſtion 3.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>If I dye this night, is my Immortal Spirit
ſafe?</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                       <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55562:31"/>
Of this he judged by his Cloſure wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <hi>God,</hi> as his <hi>beſt good,</hi> and laſt <hi>end,</hi> and wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <hi>Chriſt</hi> as his <hi>Prophet,</hi> and his <hi>Prieſt,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
his <hi>King,</hi> and by his Reſolution alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
to be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> for the Lord, and an <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>
                                          <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi>
to every Sin: Thô ſometimes he would
with a more large and long Attention
<hi>Examine</hi> his own <hi>Hopes</hi> of Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,
for which purpoſe he had in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
by him, his Bundles of <hi>Marks</hi> and
<hi>Signs,</hi> which teſtifie a Man to be born o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
God. When he had thought on theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
things, he was able to lay <hi>himſelf down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                             <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                          </gap>
peace and ſleep;</hi> but this was a way to
keep a Soul <hi>Awake.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>I begin to ſuſpect that my Readers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
is almoſt expir'd; and therefore
I ſhall cauſe the Remainder of this <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
to <hi>omit</hi> where it cannot <hi>contract,</hi> what
yet is well worthy to be the matter of
it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He was one that <hi>mortified</hi> and
<hi>conquer'd</hi> the SINS which were a <hi>Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
to him. There were ſome <hi>Sins</hi>
which gave to this Young Man a more
violent, and outragious diſturbance that
he could without much paſſion bear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
Theſe did he contrive and conflict much
in his <hi>Oppoſitions</hi> to, and gave not over
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55562:31"/>
till he had a certain Proſpect of a <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of all the things which ever troubled
him, I know not whether any were more
grievous than the <hi>Blaſphemous Injections</hi>
which like <hi>fiery</hi> venemous darts inflam'd
ſometimes his very Soul within him.</p>
                     <p>It may be ſome Teſtimony of <hi>Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
when Perſons are not a little <hi>affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi>
for, as well as aſſaulted with, <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Imaginations</hi> about God; which riſe
within us in contradiction to all that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
of him, which we know not how
to lay aſide.</p>
                     <p>This Perſon on his <hi>Death-bed</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to me, that <hi>Horrenda de Deo,</hi> Horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Conceptions of <hi>God,</hi> buzzing about
his mind, had been one of the bittereſt
of all his Tryals: and I find his <hi>private
Papers</hi> making ſad Lamentations over the
miſeries of this annoyance. You ſhall
read how he did encounter theſe <hi>Fiends,</hi>
as one that was no Stranger to the <hi>Wars
of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Once in his <hi>Diary,</hi> he ſays;</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <p>Troubled exceedingly with <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
Suggeſtions,</hi> my Soul bleeds at the
thoughts of them.</p>
                                 <p>O that Chriſt would deliver me from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55562:32"/>
them! they make my Life unpleaſant. I
do believe that <hi>Satan</hi> never ſtruggled ſo
hard to keep any one from Chriſt, as
he has done to keep me!</p>
                                 <p>From hence I learn, 1. My great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<hi>to,</hi> 2. My great need <hi>of,</hi> the
Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>At another time:</head>
                                 <p>Troubled with <hi>Blaſphemous Thoughts,</hi>
I learn from hence,</p>
                                 <p>1. Seeing theſe would have me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
a <hi>low Eſteem</hi> of Chriſt and God,</p>
                                 <p>I will endeavour to have a more high
and eminent <hi>Eſteem</hi> of God and Chriſt.</p>
                                 <p>2. Seeing theſe do ſo perplex me
<hi>continually,</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>I learn, that I am unable of my ſelf
to raiſe <hi>good Thoughts,</hi> much leſs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<hi>Good Acts</hi> of Obedience. I would
be deeply <hi>humbled,</hi> that my Soul ſhould
be thus <hi>defiled.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Seeing,</hi> I have often ſo much Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
and ſtirrings of Enmity in my
Soul to God, I would be excited
thereby more heartily to cleave unto
him.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55562:32"/>
                                 <head>Once more,</head>
                                 <p>I hope I have now got ſtrength over
my <hi>Blaſphemous Thoughts,</hi> after this
manner.</p>
                                 <p>1. <hi>Humbling</hi> my ſelf under a ſenſe of
my own vileneſs and wretchedneſs.</p>
                                 <p>2. <hi>Praying</hi> earneſtly for the removal
of the Enmity that is in my Soul to
the things of God; eſpecially as to this
matter.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Thus diſcreetly did he manage the
<hi>Shield of Faith</hi> againſt thoſe barbed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows
of Hell: Nor did his other Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
eſcape the <hi>Offenſive,</hi> as well as the
<hi>Defenſive</hi> Weapons of his Soul.</p>
                     <p>Under the moſt furious of their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults,
I find this to be one of his <hi>honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Retreats.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>For the Relief of my Soul under the
Power of <hi>Corruption;</hi> Let me by <hi>Faith</hi>
apply theſe <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> Rom. 6. 14.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> Ezck. 36. 26.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Mic. 7. 19.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Zech. 13. 1.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Beſides</hi> Zech. 9. 12. Mat. 16. 18. John
12. 31. <hi>and</hi> Rom. 16. 20. <hi>and theſe Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="50" facs="tcp:55562:33"/>
Firſt, <hi>Chriſt is a</hi> compleat Redeemer,
Heb. 7. 25. 1 John 1. 7. Heb. 9. 14.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> God's <hi>Infinite Power</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged
on my behalf, if I be in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
with him.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God will perfect <hi>Holineſs</hi> where
he hath begun it.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>In ſuch Engagements as theſe againſt
his <hi>Inviſible Adverſaries</hi> he continued, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
he is now a <hi>Conquerour, and more than
a Conquerour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He was one that wiſely prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
for the CHANGES that were before
him. It is a Remark in one of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers:
<q rend="margQuotes">
                           <hi>I think it convenient for me to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
the Temptations, I am, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>or ſhall be
obnoxious to, and get ſuitable Remedies
againſt them.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſeem'd indeed to have a ſtrange
<hi>Preſage</hi> of what he was to meet withal,
and O how he laid in that he might not
be <hi>unprovided</hi> for it! A <hi>prudence</hi> rarely ſeen
among the Children of Men, whoſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi>
is great upon them becauſe they <hi>know
not their Time.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There were eſpecially two Calamities
which he had a fore-boding of, Diſmal
<hi>Pain,</hi> and Early <hi>Death.</hi> As for his <hi>Pain,</hi>
he was it ſeems to undergo exquiſite An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55562:33"/>
for many Months before his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution;
but before ever it came upon
him, how ſtrangely did he fortifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
againſt it! He ſaid in his Diary ſome
Years before he left the World,</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>Sept. 2.</head>
                                 <p>I had not in the <hi>morning</hi> time enough
for <hi>ſolemn Meditation:</hi> Great deadneſs
and dulneſs was in my Heart, as to
<hi>Spiritual Thoughts</hi> afterwards; the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
was, becauſe I <hi>did not perform my ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
Meditation as I ſhould.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>I had now apprehenſions that I muſt
undergo ſore <hi>Tryals,</hi> and <hi>Conflicts,</hi> and
great Afflictions.</p>
                                 <p>Wherefore it did highly become me
to get as great a meaſure of <hi>Grace,</hi> as
the opportunities which I enjoy may
afford, and therefore I purpoſe to be
more ſerious in my Meditations, not
omitting other Duties therewithal.</p>
                                 <p>I ſee my Reſolutions muſt <hi>every day</hi>
be renew'd, as to great diligence in
my ſerving God.</p>
                                 <p>And ſince I muſt expect great <hi>Afflictions,</hi>
I muſt make it my daily work by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
<hi>Meditation</hi> to go over the whole
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55562:34"/>
                                    <hi>Body of Chriſtianity,</hi> and particularly to
have daily Thoughts on the <hi>Condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> I muſt alſo endeavour
to get a large meaſure of <hi>ſanctified know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi>
wherefore,</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is need of <hi>Earneſt Prayer;</hi>
and</p>
                                 <p>Secondly, <hi>Of very</hi> holy walking.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Of entertaining the <hi>Truth</hi>
with greateſt Affection; and</p>
                                 <p>Fourthly, <hi>Looking on it</hi> as it is in Jeſus;
<hi>and</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Solemn <hi>Meditation;</hi> and</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Much <hi>Reading;</hi> and</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Seventhly, Living</hi> upon the Truths
which I know, and <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> for the
Knowledge which I have already.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="diary_entry">
                                 <head>And at another time there was this
written in his Diary.</head>
                                 <p>This Morning I meditated about a
part of <hi>Self-denial;</hi> Namely, the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
of Bodily <hi>Health,</hi> and of <hi>eaſe</hi> from
Torment.</p>
                                 <p>My <hi>Reſolution</hi> was, that it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to part herewithall, than to <hi>ſin.</hi>
I hope there is a <hi>thorough purpoſe</hi> in my
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55562:34"/>
Heart to perform accordingly, when I
ſhall be call'd thereunto.</p>
                                 <p>I do feel the ſtirrings of <hi>ſelf</hi> in my ſelf
this day: <hi>It</hi> would fain be in the Throne
of God within me; but I am reſolved
<hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall be my <hi>King.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>And as he thus <hi>put on the whole Armour
of God,</hi> that he might be able to ſtand
when he ſhould be tryed, ſo he found the
benefit of it when he came into the <hi>Field.</hi>
Few in the World ever bore ſuch Dolors
with ſuch a ſilent and a quiet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<hi>Temper</hi> as he. Some that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate
with him, would ſay, <hi>He was one
of an Iron Patience,</hi> and <hi>they had rarely if
ever ſeen ſuch a patient</hi> Patient. But his
<hi>Death</hi> he ſeem'd all along moſt careful
to be ready for.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="papers">
                                 <head>In his Papers.</head>
                                 <p>Meditations on the four laſt things, was
a <hi>Title</hi> mentioning a <hi>Subject</hi> of his moſt
ſolicitous Contemplations. Above <hi>three
Years</hi> before his <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> his Diary hath
ſuch a Note as this.</p>
                                 <q rend="margQuotes">
                                    <p>Speaking to Day ſomething concerning
my <hi>Commencement,</hi>
                                       <note place="margin">In the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin he wrote, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</hi>
                                       </note> I was ſtrangely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized,
and had many Thoughts, yea
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55562:35"/>
Perſwaſions, <hi>That I ſhould not live.</hi> He
then—.</p>
                                    <p>Reſt. <hi>What may be the</hi> Import <hi>hereof
I cannot tell; yet I gather thus much:</hi>
That it is incumbent on me without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
delay, to make my Calling and Election
ſure.</p>
                                 </q>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                     <p>He hath alſo left behind him, <hi>ſome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations,
tending to the Exerciſe of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
and Faith, and Preparation for Death,</hi>
as he hath himſelf intituled them; but
the Reader by this time will eaſily pardon
my forbearing the Communication of them.</p>
                     <p>Indeed, <hi>Preparation for Death,</hi> in one
word, contains the ſubſtance of what he
had been doing divers years before the
<hi>King of Terrors</hi> took his <hi>Clay Houſe</hi> away.</p>
                     <p>And as he was deſirous to prepare for
what <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> he might be put
upon, ſo he was loath to have his Heart
not well ordered or furniſhed, when
<hi>active Obedience</hi> might be called for at his
hands. Tho he never liv'd to preach any
other than ſome <hi>private Sermons,</hi> yet he
was not unthoughtful of the Time when
<hi>publick ones</hi> might be expected from him.
It may not be unuſeful for me to inſert
one of his <hi>Meditations</hi> here; it runs in
ſuch terms as theſe.</p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="meditation">
                                 <pb n="53" facs="tcp:55562:35"/>
                                 <head>¶Whether I ſhould be a Miniſter?</head>
                                 <p>I conſidered all <hi>Objections</hi> which Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
might make againſt it, and anſwer'd
them every one. But one <hi>Objection</hi> ſtartled
me more than the reſt, to wit, <hi>Perſonal
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfitneſs,</hi> from my <hi>Hebetude,</hi> or want
of Invention. To which I anſwer'd,
with minding that Promiſe in <hi>Exod.
3. 12. Certainly I will be with thee.</hi> And
the beginning of <hi>ver. 18. They ſhall hearken
to thy voice.</hi> And where God finds <hi>work,</hi>
there he will give <hi>ſtrength.</hi> I likewiſe
conſidered <hi>1 Chron.</hi> 28. 10, 20. and
<hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. and <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. 9. and
<hi>Judg.</hi> 6. 12, 14.</p>
                                 <p>And then I thought with my ſelf, That
as for <hi>living in a remote part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi>
I ſhould be willing thereunto, if ſo
I might do Service for God, and bring
Glory to his Name. And whilſt I was
muſing on theſe things, I was melted
into a frame, that I thought heretofore
I ſhould never be in, namely, <hi>humble
Submiſſion to the good Pleaſure of God,
however he ſhould diſpoſe of me.</hi> I knew,
that though I were <hi>Reproached</hi> for what
<hi>meanneſs</hi> I ſhould this way be expoſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55562:36"/>
unto, there is an Anſwer in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16.
and in <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 38. and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 19. and
in <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 7. and in <hi>Pfal.</hi> 37. 5, 6. So
were the Apoſtles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3, 9. If I <hi>ſerve</hi>
Chriſt, God will <hi>honour</hi> me, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 26.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Every one muſt own, that however ſuch
things as theſe, in an <hi>old</hi> Man, may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
our Admiration; yet in a <hi>young</hi> Man,
that out-lived not the Years which the
<hi>Nodes</hi> of the <hi>Moon</hi> take to diſpatch a Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,
they deſerve a <hi>Memory</hi> among them
that may be Edified by ſuch <hi>Exemplary
Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ctices.</hi> Indeed, he was himſelf Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
unſenſible of the leaſt <hi>worth</hi> or
<hi>ſhine</hi> adorning of him; and in his whole
Deportment he diſcovered a modeſt, an
humble, and a deſerved <hi>mein;</hi> which might
be reck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ned to bear little <hi>proportion</hi> with
his other Accompliſhments, were it not
that the more <hi>gracious</hi> Men are, the more
humble they always are; and they are
the <hi>Fulleſt</hi> and <hi>Richeſt</hi> Ears of Corn, which
moſt hang down towards the Ground.
But while he in a ſort wronged himſelf,
to eſcape the <hi>bane</hi> and <hi>blame</hi> of <hi>Pride;</hi> it
is a piece of <hi>pure Juſtice</hi> in the Survivers,
to <hi>Embalm</hi> the Name of a Perſon thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable,
ſince he is gone thither where he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55562:36"/>
has no <hi>Chaff</hi> to take fire at the ſparks of
our Praiſes.</p>
                     <q>Sic oculos, ſic ille manus, ſic ora
ferebat?</q>
                     <p>Such a <hi>young</hi> Man as this it is that the
Church of God is now deprived of!
What a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> might his Living have
proved unto the World! But as the
<hi>Long-liv'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Patriarchs,</hi> before the Flood,
have ſtill that Clauſe introduced of them,
<hi>And he lyed;</hi> which Clauſe awakened and
Converted a Perſon of Quality, who came in
occaſionally while the Miniſter was read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the <hi>Fifth Chapter of Geneſis</hi> to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation;
ſo muſt I now ſay of the <hi>Short-liv'd
Perſon,</hi> whom we have been paying
out laſt Reſpect unto, He lived thus <hi>long</hi>
in a little time, <hi>And he died.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Before I break off, I muſt relate,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>III. His DEATH.</head>
                     <p>Too <hi>ſoon</hi> and too <hi>ſad</hi> a thing for me to
mention without Sighing, <hi>Ah my Brother,</hi>
in my Lamentation over it. He had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
an univerſal <hi>Ill Habit</hi> of Body;
which was attended with a particular ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55562:37"/>
of <hi>Ill Humours,</hi> where the <hi>Os Ileon</hi>
and <hi>Os Sacrum</hi> joyn; from whence it fell
into his <hi>Thigh,</hi> until there was a very large
collection of it there.</p>
                     <p>There was an <hi>Inciſion,</hi> with mature Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
made into the <hi>Tumour,</hi> about a Month
before his Expiration, which gave good
hopes of his Recovery into a capacity of
ſerving the Church of God; but the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation,</hi>
which was now given unto the
<hi>putrid Juices</hi> which his Blood, through his
continual and ſedentary Studies, had
been annoyed withal, ſoon enkinded a
Fever, which burnt aſunder the thread of
this pious Life.</p>
                     <p>One might ſuppoſe, that ſuch a <hi>Walk
with God</hi> as the Reader has newly had
Pourtrayed before him, ſhould End in
<hi>Raptures,</hi> and <hi>Extaſies</hi> of <hi>Aſſurance;</hi> but
I am to tell him, That this young Perſon
had them not. And there wanted not
Reaſon for it. For his <hi>Natural Diſtemper</hi>
diſpoſed him to what is contrary to <hi>Joy;</hi>
but his Deep Humility had a greater ſhare
in the <hi>Jealouſies</hi> and <hi>Suſpicions</hi> which he
would ſtill cheriſh of himſelf. He was
indeed ſo afraid of being an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi>
that he would ſcarce allow himſelf to be
called a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and he did not care ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55562:37"/>
much as to tell any of his own <hi>Experiences,</hi>
no, nor his <hi>Inclinations,</hi> unleſs to one or
two Divines, who kindly refreſhed him
with their daily Viſits; and with them too
he would uphold his Diſcourſe only in
<hi>Latin,</hi> if any one elſe were by.</p>
                     <p>Never did I ſee more Caution againſt
<hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> than what was in him; and a
certain <hi>Self-abhorrence</hi> accompanying of it,
cauſed to proceed from him no Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
but thoſe of an <hi>Abaſed Soul.</hi> When
his Brother having recited the Terms of
the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to him, with a deſign to obtain
from him a Renewal of his <hi>Explicit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi>
thereunto, asked him, <hi>Whether he did
not judge himſelf Sincere in that Conſent?</hi> He
only replied, <hi>I ſhould think ſo, if it were not for
the Seventeenth of</hi> Jeremiah, <hi>and the Ninth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He was <hi>Dejected,</hi> yet not <hi>Deſpairing;</hi>
and he diſcôvered a wonderfully <hi>Gracious,</hi>
when he had not a <hi>Joyful</hi> Frame. He was
all made up of Longings and Breathings
after <hi>all the fulneſs of God,</hi> when he could
not or would not pretend unto any Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of his <hi>Acceptance</hi> with the Lord.</p>
                     <p>In the time of his <hi>Health,</hi> he had not
been without the comfortable Perſwaſions
for which he <hi>follow'd hard after God.</hi> In
one place, I find him ſaying (on ſuch a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55562:38"/>
day) <hi>I had Fears leſt I did not love the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
God; but yet I was ſure I deſired to keep
his Commandments.</hi> Another time ſo; <hi>For
Three quarters of an Hour, I pleaded earneſtly
for aſſurance of the Love of God unto me, and
I ſaid,</hi> As many as received Chriſt Jeſus,
to them he gave power to become the Sons
of God; <hi>And I did receive Jeſus Chriſt, as
the Free Gift of God; and received him to
ſave me on his own Terms: I choſe him to be
my Prieſt, and Prophet, and King. Now I
begg'd of him that he would manifeſt his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance
of me, and give me the Spirit of
Adoption: I had then, I hope, ſome Aſſurance.</hi>
But when <hi>Sickneſs</hi> came, he was loth to
own a clear <hi>Title</hi> to the Reſt of God: Yet
before he died, he ſuffered ſome ſober In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timations
of his <hi>hopes</hi> to fall from him.
There was a good Man in this Land, whoſe
laſt words yet were, <hi>It had been good for
me that I had never been born.</hi> The words
of this humble Self-loathing Young-Man,
were of another ſtrain. In the laſt Night,
that we had him with us, he would have
his Watcher to read, <hi>The Song of Simeon,</hi>
unto him, <hi>Now letteſt thou thy Servant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
in Peace:</hi> And in the Morning after,
he ſaid, <hi>I have now been with Jeſus Chriſt!</hi>
which, from ſuch a little Speaker as he,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55562:38"/>
we could not have his Explication of.</p>
                     <p>In one of his laſt Minutes, a faithful
Miniſter ſaid unto him, <hi>Find you not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> To which he
made only this diſcreet and humble Anſwer,
<hi>I Endeavour to do thoſe things which will iſſue
in Comfort;</hi> and then he quickly ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
up his Redeemed and Renewed Soul
unto him who had <hi>loved him, and waſhed
away his ſins in his own blood.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus he went away to the heavenly So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
where he is beholding the <hi>Face of
God in Righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſolacing himſelf
in the Company not only of his bleſſed
<hi>Grandfathers,</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles,</hi> and all the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
of the Juſt;</hi> but of the amiable <hi>Jeſus</hi>
himſelf, which is by <hi>far the beſt of all.</hi> His
<hi>Tears</hi> are all dried up, his <hi>Fears</hi> vaniſhed
away, and his <hi>Hopes</hi> more than anſwered
in <hi>Joys unſpeakable, and full of glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His <hi>Elder Brother</hi> having thus written of
him, now ſatisfies himſelf in the Duty
therein done to God and Man; and would
keep <hi>waiting</hi> for his own <hi>Change,</hi> until,
<hi>Thy Free Grace, O my God, ſhall give unto
the moſt miſerable Sinner in the World, an
admiſſion into</hi> Emanuel<hi>'s Land.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Cotton Mather.</signed> 
                        <dateline>Finiſhed
<date>Octob. 29.
1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:55562:39"/>
                     <head>One that had an Acquaintance with him,
did him the Juſtice of weeping over his
Grave ſuch an <hi>Epitaph</hi> as this.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>INcloſed in this <hi>ſable Cheſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Hoſt once of an heavenly Gueſt</l>
                        <l>Here lyes: <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> Nathanael,</l>
                        <l>True Off-ſpring of God's <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Him <hi>Dead,</hi> how term we, from his Birth,</l>
                        <l>Who <hi>liv'd</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> whilſt on Earth?</l>
                        <l>His <hi>Head</hi> had Learnings Magazine,</l>
                        <l>His <hi>Heart</hi> the Altar, whence Divine</l>
                        <l>Whole <hi>Hecatombs,</hi> which Love had fir'd,</l>
                        <l>Of high <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and warm <hi>Pray'r</hi> aſpir'd:</l>
                        <l>His <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Decalogue</hi> unfolded;</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Meat-off'ring,</hi> his <hi>Speech</hi> well moulded;</l>
                        <l>His rare <hi>Devotion,</hi> ſuch now ſeen,</l>
                        <l>A ſign of <hi>Ninety</hi> at <hi>Nineteen.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Years</hi> but in Bloom, <hi>Grace</hi> at full growth;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Angels,</hi> you <hi>Know</hi> and <hi>Think</hi> his Worth.</l>
                        <l>Thus <hi>Time,</hi> Youth's Glaſs, Turn'd e're 'twas Run,</l>
                        <l>And Ages too, before begun.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Reſt, <hi>glorious Duſt,</hi> and let thy perfum'd Name</l>
                        <l>Sound in the <hi>Trumpets</hi> of Immortal Fame.</l>
                        <l>For thô <hi>Times</hi> Teeth <hi>Mauſolaean</hi> Monuments
deface,</l>
                        <l>They'll never gnaw thy <hi>Name</hi> which with the
Stars has place.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Poſ uit,
R. Hale</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:39"/>
                  <p>SEVERAL
SERMONS
CONCERNING
WALKING
WITH
GOD,
AND THAT
In the Dayes of Youth:
PREACHED
At <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi> By <hi>Cotton Mather,</hi> Paſtor of a Church there.</p>
                  <bibl>1 King. 18. 12.</bibl>
                  <q>—But I thy Servant fear the Lord
from my Youth.</q>
                  <bibl>1 Chron. 34. 3.</bibl>
                  <q>—While he was yet young, he began
to ſeek after the God of David his Father.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>J. Aſtwood</hi> for <hi>I. Dunton,</hi> at the <hi>Black
Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Compter.</hi> 1689.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55562:40"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55562:40"/>
                  <head>THE
WALK
OF
HOLY and HAPPY
MEN.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>GEN. V. 24.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
And Enoch walked with God.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>BEhold, in theſe words the <hi>Picture</hi>
of a great and a good Man, which
indeed, like a <hi>well-made</hi> Picture
<hi>looks</hi> upon, yea, more than ſo, <hi>ſpeaks</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
us all; nor is it a <hi>common</hi> Picture for
this alſo, that the <hi>Walk</hi> as well as the <hi>Face</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55562:41"/>
of the Perſon is repreſented in it. This
Chapter contains a Catalogue of thoſe
<hi>Antediluvian</hi> Patriarchs, in whom the
<hi>Church</hi> of God, and the <hi>Line</hi> of Chriſt
was continued from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah.</hi> The
ancient Heathens expreſſed their broken
Traditions of our <hi>Noah</hi> in rude Notions
of one <hi>Janus,</hi> a Man, a god, and I know
not what, with two Faces on him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<hi>Noah</hi> had the Proſpect of <hi>two World<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
before him: We may all ſhare with <hi>Noah</hi>
in this Priviledge; the Affairs of the <hi>Old
World</hi> as well as of the <hi>New</hi> do arrive to
our Notice; in this Chapter particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
we have a Muſter of renowned Men
that lived <hi>before the Flood.</hi> Indeed about
the moſt of them, there is little record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
beſides
their <hi>Age</hi> and their <hi>End.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical
Hiſtory relates, that a Perſon
of Quality accidentally coming into a
<hi>Meeting-houſe,</hi> where the Miniſter was read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the fifth Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> thoſe
words recurring ſo often in it, <hi>And he Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed!
And he Dyed!</hi> they ſtruck to, they
ſtuck in the Heart of him, and cauſed
him that was a <hi>mortal</hi> to become a very
<hi>ſerious</hi> Man: God grant that <hi>another</hi> clauſe
in the Chapter may have this day as good
an effect upon us all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55562:41"/>
One of the <hi>Worthies</hi> in this Roll <hi>(Enoch</hi>
by Name) can have no Report made of
his <hi>Death;</hi> but inſtead thereof, we find a
twofold Remark made upon him. <hi>Firſt,</hi>
We have the <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Enoch:</hi> 'Tis once
and again ſaid of him, <hi>He walked with God;</hi>
a <hi>peculiar ſanctity</hi>-he ſeems therein to be
ſet forth as an Inſtance of. <hi>Secondly,</hi> We
have the <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> of <hi>Enoch;</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>He
was not, for God took him:</hi> A <hi>Tranſlation</hi> is
intended by that Phraſe, as it is by the
Apoſtle elſewhere explained. It ſeems
that this notable <hi>Preacher</hi> of Truth; and
<hi>Witneſs</hi> for God, at laſt withdrew from
the ſight of Men: They asked, they won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,
what was become of him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
they ſought in all corners for him,
'till they underſtood that the <hi>Angels</hi> of God
had carried him away. Not only the
<hi>ſpirit,</hi> but the <hi>body</hi> too of this excellent
man, has now been among the Angels in
Heaven for ſome hundreds, above four
thouſand Years.</p>
                  <p>But it is now time to Obſerve,</p>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Doct.</hi> To walk with God is the ſingular Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Holy and Happy Men.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="proposition">
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55562:42"/>
                        <head>Prop. I.</head>
                        <p>To <hi>Walk with God</hi> is the Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and Attainment of ſome that <hi>live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
Earth:</hi> Here and there a Perſon is to be
met withal, whoſe Priviledge it is <hi>to walk
with God.</hi> It is to be enquired, <hi>What is
it to walk with God?</hi> What is that rare, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious,
laborious thing? in ſhort, we
then <hi>Walk with God,</hi> when we maintain
<hi>Communion</hi> with God in all the <hi>motions</hi> of
our Lives. Every Man has a <hi>Walk</hi> in the
World. The <hi>Life</hi> of Man is the <hi>Walk</hi> of
Man. It may be ſaid unto each Man,
as in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 10. Man, <hi>Thou art going.</hi>
A <hi>Walk</hi> is a progreſſive continued thing,
made up of many <hi>ſteps:</hi> Thus a <hi>Life;</hi> 'tis
made up of many <hi>thoughts,</hi> many <hi>words,</hi>
many <hi>deeds.</hi> A Man is <hi>with God,</hi> when he
<hi>ſees</hi> God, and <hi>owns</hi> God: Then therefore
do's a Man <hi>Walk with God,</hi> when he <hi>lives</hi>
in multiply'd Acts of <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Homage</hi>
unto the Lord. It is the Command in
<hi>1 Pet. 1. 15. Be ye holy in all manner of
Converſation;</hi> it may be rendered, <hi>Be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in every turn:</hi> While we <hi>Walk,</hi> we <hi>Turn</hi>
every day, now to one Object, now to
another: Well, when we are <hi>with God</hi>
                           <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55562:42"/>
in every <hi>Turn,</hi> then we <hi>Walk with God.</hi> A
<hi>Walk with God</hi> is in ſhort, that <hi>godly,</hi> that <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi>
that <hi>righteous</hi> Life which the <hi>Word of God</hi>
adviſeth us unto. It was the ſpeech of the
Pſalmiſt, in <hi>Pſal. 26. 11. I will walk in mine
Integrity;</hi> and in <hi>Pſal. 86. 11. I will walk
in thy Truth;</hi> and in <hi>Pſal. 116. 9. I will
walk before the Lord:</hi> All this is <hi>to Walk with
God.</hi> We read in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7. of a <hi>Walk
by Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> and in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. of a <hi>Walk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the Spirit;</hi> and in <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 16. of a <hi>Walk
according to Rule;</hi> this is a <hi>Walk with God.</hi>
Two things are comprized in it.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> In a <hi>Walk with God</hi> there is an
uninterrupted performing of <hi>Worſhip</hi> to
God. We ſhould be often <hi>with God</hi> in the
Exerciſes of his <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Inſtituted</hi>
Worſhip. There are certain <hi>Mountains</hi> of
Devotion, of which we ſhould ſay as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
in the Mount, <hi>It is good to be here!</hi> and
we ſhould be ever now and then Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
with the Almighty there; this 'tis to
<hi>Walk with Him!</hi> There is the Duty of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
to God, our <hi>Lives</hi> are to be filled with
it: We ſhould (may I ſo ſay) <hi>Walk</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
our <hi>Knees.</hi> To <hi>Talk</hi> much with God
is to <hi>Walk</hi> much with him. The <hi>Walker
with God</hi> may ſay with <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>2 Tim. 1. 3.
I ſerve God, and without ceaſing I have my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55562:43"/>
prayers Night and Day.</hi> There is again the
Duty of <hi>Hearing</hi> from God, our <hi>Lives</hi> are
to be fill'd with it. To <hi>Sit</hi> before God is
to <hi>Walk</hi> with him. We ſhould often <hi>Go
up to the Houſe of the Lord;</hi> that is, to take
a <hi>Walk</hi> in his bleſſed Company. The <hi>Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
with God</hi> will upon every occaſion ſay,
as the Pſalmiſt in <hi>Pſal. 85. 58. I will hear
what God the Lord will ſpeak.</hi> There is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
the Duty of <hi>Thinking</hi> on God, that is
a <hi>Walking</hi> with him. We ſhould not for
any long while together have God out of
our <hi>Mind,</hi> then he will not be out of our
<hi>Walk.</hi> The <hi>Walker with God</hi> may ſay as
<hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſal. 139. 17, 18. How precious are
thy thoughts unto me, O God! when I awake,
I am ſtill with thee.</hi> In a word, all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments
of God, wherein he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes
to us a <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with Himſelf, our
<hi>Walk</hi> it ſhould be, that is, our <hi>Courſe</hi> and
our <hi>Trade</hi> to be therein waiting upon the
Lord.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> In a <hi>Walk with God</hi> there is a
continual Acting of <hi>Grace</hi> on God. A
<hi>Walk</hi> with God lies in a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
upon the Soul. We ſhould be able
to ſay as he in <hi>Pſal. 16. 8. I have ſet the
Lord always before me;</hi> ſo ſhall we <hi>Walk</hi> with
the Lord. We are to <hi>Walk</hi> always under
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55562:43"/>
the <hi>Awe;</hi> and under the <hi>Eye</hi> of the great
God. As now, the <hi>Walker</hi> with God will
always be ſenſible of God as his <hi>laſt End.</hi>
It was becauſe <hi>Aſaph</hi> did <hi>Walk</hi> with God,
that he ſaid in <hi>Pſal. 73. 25. Whom have I
but God?</hi> The <hi>Walker</hi> will always be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of God as his <hi>beſt good:</hi> It was becauſe
<hi>Jeremiah</hi> did <hi>Walk</hi> with God, that he ſaid
in <hi>Lam. 3. 24. The Lord is my portion, ſaith
my Soul, I will hope in him.</hi> The <hi>Walker</hi> with
God will always be ſenſible of God, as
his <hi>only Helper.</hi> When a Man <hi>walks</hi> with
God, he is perpetually ſaying as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
in <hi>Pſal. 121. 2. My help cometh from
the Lord, which made Heaven and Earth:</hi>
His <hi>Ejaculations</hi> therefore particularly are
innumerable: And the <hi>Walker</hi> with God
cannot but be ſenſible of God as his <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient</hi>
and <hi>omnipreſent</hi> Judge. It will be an
apprehenſion always running in the Soul
of ſuch a Man, which we have in <hi>Pſal. 139.
7. Whither ſhall I flee from the preſence of
the Lord?</hi> In a <hi>Walk</hi> with God a Man has
evermore his Heart within him, admiring
and adoring the God of Heaven on ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts
as theſe: Theſe <hi>Notions</hi> of God, theſe
<hi>Viſions</hi> of God accompany ſuch a Man every
where, and influence all his <hi>Walk:</hi> Thus
does he <hi>Acknowledge God in all his ways.</hi>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55562:44"/>
'Tis ſaid in <hi>Prov. 23. 17. Be thou in the
fear of the Lord all the day long;</hi> even ſo
maintain thou a <hi>ſenſe of the Lord all the day
long:</hi> This 'tis to <hi>Walk with</hi> Him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="proposition">
                        <head>Prop. II.</head>
                        <p>They are both <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Happy</hi> Men that
thus <hi>Walk with God:</hi> This is the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
of them that have God with them in
all their <hi>Walk.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. The <hi>Walker with God</hi> is a very <hi>Holy</hi>
Man: What is true <hi>Holineſs?</hi> Many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes
have there been about that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
thing: A Man may be <hi>Orthodox</hi> in
his Perſwaſions, and yet not be <hi>Holy:</hi> A
Man may be very <hi>Auſtere</hi> and <hi>Severe</hi> in his
Practices, and yet not be <hi>Holy:</hi> You may
ſay of a Man, <hi>That he has a Righteouſneſs
equal to that of the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> and
yet the Man may be a ſtranger to true
<hi>Holineſs</hi> after all. O but when once it can
be ſaid of a Man, <hi>He walks with God!</hi> then,
then <hi>Holineſs</hi> is to be ſeen upon him.</p>
                        <p>To Walk <hi>with</hi> God, is to Walk <hi>like</hi> God.
Now the more <hi>like</hi> to God any Man is or
does, the more <hi>Holineſs</hi> there is in ſuch a
Man. 'Tis the Attribute of God in <hi>Exod.
15. 11. O</hi> Lord, <hi>Thou art glorious in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi>
                           <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55562:44"/>
and in <hi>Heb. 1. 13. Thou canſt not look
upon Iniquity.</hi> The Nature of <hi>Holineſs</hi>
lies in a <hi>Dedication</hi> unto God: A thing <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated
unto God,</hi> by the Diſpoſal of another,
has a <hi>Relative Holineſs</hi> belonging thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.
A Man <hi>Dedicated</hi> unto God by his own
hearty Reſignation and Conſecration of
himſelf unto the Lord, ſuch an one hath
in him a real Holineſs. Well, the <hi>Walker</hi>
with God is an <hi>Enoch: Enoch</hi> is in Engliſh
as much as to ſay, <hi>A Dedicated Man:</hi> The
Man that is <hi>with</hi> God, is alſo <hi>for</hi> God, and
him alone: This is <hi>Holineſs</hi> in the <hi>Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of it.</hi> The Holy Dr. <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
to write about <hi>Sanctification,</hi> with
Tears lamenting the defect of it in himſelf,
gave this Deſcription of it,—<hi>It is for a
Man to be in the offering up of his Soul continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
in the flames of Love, as a whole burnt-offering
to God in Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Now in a
<hi>Walk</hi> with God, a Man is every day do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſo. In fine, When <hi>Moſes</hi> had been
<hi>with</hi> God in the Mount, we read in <hi>Exod.</hi>
34. 35. It made his <hi>Face</hi> to <hi>ſhine.</hi> A Man
whoſe whole <hi>Walk</hi> is with God, muſt needs
derive much <hi>Grace</hi> from God, a <hi>ſhine,</hi> a
glory, a luſtre of <hi>Holineſs</hi> will be ſeen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ſuch a Man.</p>
                        <p>2. The <hi>Walker with God</hi> is alſo a very
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55562:45"/>
                           <hi>Happy</hi> Man: The Pſalmiſt hath well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
where <hi>Happineſs</hi> is to be found,
in <hi>Pſal. 73. 28. It is good for me to draw near
to God:</hi> By the ſame Reaſon we may eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
one ſay, <hi>It is good for me to walk with
God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Happineſs</hi> properly lies in the <hi>Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
of a <hi>Thing</hi> with ſuch a <hi>good</hi> as the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites
and Faculties of that thing are ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto. Well, <hi>Walking</hi> with God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be without an <hi>having</hi> of God: God
and Man do mutually <hi>poſſeſs</hi> each other in
this bleſſed thing. Now the Soul is in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi>
with ſuch a <hi>good</hi> as anſwers all the
boundleſs Cravings of it. The <hi>Soul</hi> of Man
hath placed in it by the <hi>Hand</hi> of God, a
reſtleſs raging deſire after an <hi>Infinite</hi> and
an <hi>Eternal</hi> good: Until it find this, it pines,
it frets, it is all on a light fire, like the
<hi>Hart panting after the water-brooks:</hi> When
it has got this, it is then at eaſe, and with
a wonderful delight it cries out, <hi>This is all
my Salvation, and all my Deſire.</hi> Behold then
the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of a <hi>Walk with God;</hi> it hath
no leſs than that vaſt thing <hi>Satisfaction</hi> in
it. All Men are ſeeking after <hi>ſatisfaction</hi>
every day; O but who finds this <hi>Pearl of
great price?</hi> Where is it? The voluptuous
<hi>Epicure,</hi> he thinks with <hi>Belſhazzar, It is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55562:45"/>
to be found in Cups and ſenſual Reliſhes:</hi> The
Covetous <hi>Muckworm</hi> he thinks with <hi>Achan
golden Wedges will rive into the bowels of it:</hi>
The Ambitious <hi>Hector</hi> he thinks with <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
An high Chair of ſtate will help a man to
reach unto it:</hi> And the contemplative <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi>
he imagines <hi>That it is folded up in the
leaves of his Books, which he knows no end of
looking into:</hi> Theſe are all deceived. In
the mean time the <hi>Walker</hi> with God ſays,
<hi>I have found it. Enoch</hi> has it. For,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> A <hi>Walk</hi> with God brings a Man to
the enjoyment of an <hi>Infinite</hi> good. The
Man has <hi>God</hi> with him now, and <hi>one</hi> God
is enough to ſupply all our <hi>Wants,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
all our <hi>Woes:</hi> It is ſaid in <hi>Phil. 4. 19.
God ſhall ſupply all your Need.</hi> When an
Immortal Soul has try'd all the Objects in
the World, it yet gapeth and gaſpeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
more, it ſtill cries, <hi>Give, Give,</hi> after
all: But there is enough in <hi>one God,</hi> enough
to feed and fill that Soul, whoſe <hi>Deſire is
enlarged like Heaven</hi> it ſelf. There is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<hi>Truth</hi> in God, there is Infinite <hi>Good</hi>
in God; he is the <hi>God of all Conſolation.</hi>
The <hi>Jews</hi> have a Fable of their <hi>Manna,</hi>
that whatever a Man had a mind to <hi>taſt,</hi>
the <hi>Manna</hi> ſtill had the <hi>taſt</hi> of that thing:
This is to be affirmed of our God; there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55562:46"/>
is in God <hi>all that we can ask or think,</hi> yea,
and infinitely more. He that <hi>walks</hi> with
God, <hi>walks</hi> with him that ſaith as in <hi>Gen.
17. 1. I am the Alſufficient God, walk before
me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> A <hi>Walk</hi> with God brings a Man
to the Enjoyment of an <hi>Eternal good.</hi> The
Man has now the <hi>Portion of the Righteous;</hi>
And what an one is that? We are told in
<hi>Pſal. 37. 18. Their Inheritance ſhall be for
ever.</hi> A virtuous young Man among the
Primitive Chriſtians, when there was <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick</hi>
and <hi>Feaſting</hi> in his Fathers Houſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired
from it, with ſuch Thoughts as theſe,
<hi>Here are delicate things, but they are ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived
things, they will be at an end anon; I
will therefore go to my God, who is the good
part can never be taken away.</hi> Truly what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
Creatures we ſhould content our ſelves
in the Preſence of, all thoſe Creatures are
like the <hi>Moon</hi> in the Increaſe; they ſhine
for a few Hours perhaps, but they go
down and all is dark before the Morning.
The <hi>Soul</hi> of Man is an <hi>Eternal</hi> thing, it
ſhall ſtand like a <hi>Rock</hi> in the Sea of <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi>
The things of this World ſhall <hi>periſh,</hi>
but thou, O Soul, ſhalt <hi>endure;</hi> they ſhall
<hi>wax old like a Garment,</hi> but <hi>thy years have
no end,</hi> O thou never-dying Soul. A Soul
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55562:46"/>
muſt have a more <hi>enduring ſubſtance</hi> than
any thing here below, for the refreſhment
of it, otherwiſe it is moſt wretchedly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
for; it will ſtarve, and languiſh,
and periſh for evermore. Now he that
<hi>Walks</hi> with God <hi>meets</hi> with that; all other
things that we <hi>Walk</hi> withal, will take
their <hi>leave</hi> of us: But God, our God hath
ſaid, as in <hi>Heb. 13. 5. I will never leave thee
nor for ſake thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>So <hi>Happy</hi> is the Man that <hi>Walks</hi> with
God. The excellent Miniſter of <hi>Nola,</hi>
when the <hi>Barbarians</hi> plundered him of all
he had in the World, he lifted up his
Eyes to Heaven, and ſaid, <hi>Domine, ne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crucier
ob Aurum &amp; Argentum, tu es mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi
omnia;</hi> Lord, I have <hi>All</hi> in <hi>Thee,</hi> ſo
that I am ſtill <hi>Happy</hi> enough, though I
have no <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> left unto me: <hi>This
is the Bleſſedneſs of the Man that walketh with
the Lord;</hi> his God and his Happineſs is
with him, though the World be laid all
in Aſhes before his Eyes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="application">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE I.</head>
                        <p>A Great <hi>Rebuke</hi> hence falls upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
Men: The Apoſtle could ſay, in
<hi>Phil. 3. 18. Many walk, of whom I tell you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55562:47"/>
weeping.</hi> Truly our <hi>Hearts</hi> are <hi>Flints,</hi> that
we do not with <hi>Tears</hi> from our <hi>Eyes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
on the <hi>Walk</hi> of the moſt of Men.
Do they <hi>Walk with God?</hi> No: They have
a <hi>Walk</hi> moſt oppoſite thereunto. Their
<hi>Walk</hi> is that in <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2. They <hi>Walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the courſe of this World, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Prince of the Power of the Air.</hi>
Their <hi>Walk</hi> is that in <hi>2 Theſ. 3. 11. They
walk diſorderly.</hi> Alas! How common is it for
men to leave the Bleſſed God, and <hi>Walk</hi> with
the <hi>World,</hi> yea with the <hi>Devil</hi> too inſtead
of him? We read of ſome in <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 37.
that <hi>VValk in Pride.</hi> We read of ſome in
<hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 14. that <hi>Walk in Lies.</hi> We
read of ſome in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3. that <hi>walk in
Laſciviouſneſs:</hi> Do theſe <hi>Walk with God?</hi>
'Tis declared of ſome, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 10.
that they <hi>walk in the Imaginations of their
own Hearts.</hi> Are there not many of thoſe
<hi>Walkers</hi> now before the Lord: <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
do thine Office: Go and find out
the Perſon that ſeldom <hi>Prays</hi> in his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi>
and more ſeldom in his <hi>Cloſet:</hi> Find
out the Perſon that has <hi>not God in all his
Thoughts:</hi> Find out the Perſon that can
indulge himſelf in thoſe <hi>abominable things
which the Soul of the Lord hates:</hi> O tell
that Man, that he doth not <hi>Walk with God,</hi>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:55562:47"/>
and ſet before him the diſmal Conſequences
of this ungodly <hi>Walk.</hi> Conſider, O Man,
the danger of all the wild, lewd Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
that vain Perſons do <hi>Walk</hi> and <hi>Run</hi>
into.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is a <hi>Curſe</hi> which thou doſt
<hi>Walk</hi> under. Hear the loud Voice of
God, in <hi>Lev. 26. 23, 24. If you will not
be Reformed, but will walk contrary to me,
then will I alſo walk contrary to you.</hi> All
the Imipety, all the Unrighteouſneſs of
thy <hi>Walk</hi> is <hi>contrary</hi> to God. The <hi>Curſe</hi>
of God therefore inflicts a <hi>Damage</hi> and
a <hi>Miſchief</hi> upon thee, in all his Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations,
that horrible <hi>Curſe</hi> accompanies
thee like thy <hi>Garment,</hi> like thy very <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi>
in all thy ways.</p>
                        <p>Moreover, <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is an Hell,
which thou doſt <hi>Walk</hi> unto. Methinks that
Speech of God is all Thunder, in <hi>Eccl.
11. 9. O Young man, walk in the wayes of
thine Heart, but know thou, that for all
theſe things, God will bring thee into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
This, even this is the warning of
the moſt High God, unto every Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
Sinner; Well, if that be thy
<hi>Walk</hi> take it; but <hi>know thou,</hi> that the
End of ſuch a <hi>Walk</hi> is <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Shame,</hi>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55562:48"/>
and <hi>Ruine</hi> for Evermore. <hi>Know thou,</hi>
that the Wrath, the Fiery <hi>Wrath of God
comes upon the Children of diſobedience</hi> for
ſuch a <hi>Walk</hi> as thine.</p>
                        <p>Now, <hi>Conſider of this, all you that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
God.</hi> The Pſalmiſt could ſay, as in
<hi>Pſal. 119. 59. I thought on my ways and
turned.</hi> Ah! <hi>Lord,</hi> That wandring Souls
may thus <hi>think</hi> and <hi>Turn!</hi> Poor Soul!
Thou art out of the way! O Stop! O
Turn! come back from that hideous
<hi>Walk,</hi> which leads down to the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
of the Dead!</hi> Come back into the
<hi>Walk,</hi> that thrô the <hi>Narrow way</hi> leads to
<hi>Life</hi> world without end. Hark! Thy
<hi>God</hi> calls after thee: <hi>Return, Return,</hi> O
Soul.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="application">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE II.</head>
                        <p>And a good <hi>Advice</hi> is hence therefore
given to every Man.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O Walk with God!</hi> What? would not
we gladly be as <hi>Enoch</hi> was? 'Tis ſaid of
him by <hi>Moſes, He walked with God.</hi> When
<hi>Paul</hi> comes to Paraphraſe upon it, he ſo
expreſſes it, in <hi>Heb. 11. 5. He pleaſed
God:</hi> O 'tis <hi>pleaſing</hi> to God, when he
ſees Men <hi>Walking</hi> with him. <hi>The Lord
hath ſhewed thee, O Man! the thing that is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55562:48"/>
good;</hi> and what is it? It is, <hi>Walk humbly
with thy God.</hi> 'Tis noted of <hi>Enoch,</hi> That
<hi>God took him:</hi> Men in their <hi>laſt Wills</hi> uſually
bequeath their <hi>Souls</hi> to God: But many a
Man may do well to examine, <hi>Will he take
it? will he take it?</hi> Except we are <hi>Walking</hi>
with God while we Live, we ſhall not
be <hi>taken</hi> by God when we Die. 'Tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the <hi>Walker</hi> with God, who can expire
with that Confidence, in <hi>Pſal. 49. 15.
He will receive me.</hi> Let us <hi>Walk</hi> with
God, and at our <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> we ſhall be
<hi>Taken</hi> by him up to the matchleſs and
endleſs Glories that are above; He will
ſend his Angels, our <hi>Guardians</hi> now, and
our <hi>Champians</hi> then, to <hi>take</hi> us unto the
<hi>Rivers of Pleaſures at Gods right Hand for
evermore.</hi> Doſt thou <hi>Walk</hi> with God?
Behold, that is it that thy <hi>Walk</hi> tends
unto. Soul, God and thou ſhalt never <hi>part.</hi>
Yea, let us <hi>Walk</hi> with God, and we ſhall
be taken by him, if the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of the
World ſhould now come upon it. There
will a Day come, when ſwift <hi>Lightnings</hi>
and hot <hi>Thunderbolts</hi> will conſume this
lower World: God knows when this
direful horrid Conflagration ſhall begin.
But whenever it is, all that <hi>Walk</hi> with
God ſhall becaught up to meet the Lord:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55562:49"/>
He will <hi>take</hi> you into the Clouds from
the reach of the Sulphureous Flames.
<hi>Enoch</hi> foretold the coming of this Fiery
Day: They that are like <hi>Enoch,</hi> ſhall
even like <hi>Enoch</hi> with a <hi>Tranſlation</hi> eſcape
the Terrors of it. O let us <hi>Walk</hi> as the
People that believed theſe awful things.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE I.</head>
                        <p>Let us Tread in the <hi>Steps</hi> of the Lord
Jeſus Chriſt, and we ſhall then <hi>walk with
God:</hi> Part of his Errand into the World,
was to ſet us an Example of ſuch a <hi>Walk.</hi>
Now we are told, in 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 6. We
<hi>ought ſo to walk, even as he walked.</hi> O
look upon the <hi>walk</hi> of him that kept
cloſe to God, without one <hi>wry</hi> Step, one
<hi>wrong</hi> Step, for above thirty Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in the World. What a ſort of a
<hi>Walk</hi> was His? We read in <hi>Act. 10. 38.
He went about doing good.</hi> He walked in
all manner of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity:</hi> He <hi>Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
in a perpetual endeavour to <hi>pleaſe</hi> and
<hi>ſerve</hi> His Father: <hi>Sic oculus, ſic ille manus,
ſic ora ferebat;</hi> That was his <hi>Walk;</hi> and
it is ſaid, in <hi>1 Pet. 1. 21. He has left us
an Example, that we ſhould follow his Steps.</hi>
Of late Years among the <hi>Mahometans,</hi>
                           <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55562:49"/>
even among the Barbarous <hi>Turks</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
there are ſprung up a vaſt Sect
of Men, who are called, <hi>The good Followers
of the Meſſiah.</hi> Theſe hold that Chriſt is
<hi>God,</hi> and that he is the <hi>Redeemer of the World;</hi>
and they are of ſuch Repute, that it is an
Applauſe among them, <hi>You are the Follower of
the Meſſiah.</hi> What ſhall be ſaid of us then,
if <hi>we</hi> are not the <hi>Followers</hi> of our Bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?
Verily, the Men of <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>
will condemn us in the Judgment of the
Lord.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE II.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>Walk with Good men,</hi> and we
do it with <hi>God</hi> himſelf. If our <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
be not fearfully ſtupified, it will tell
us, <hi>What ſort of men have moſt of God
among them.</hi> We are <hi>with God,</hi> when
we <hi>Walk</hi> with ſuch as <hi>Walk after the Lord.</hi>
Let us <hi>Walk</hi> with good Men in their
<hi>Principles:</hi> It was wiſe Counſel, in <hi>Prov.
2. 12. 20. To deliver thee from the man that
ſpeaks froward things, walk in the way of
good men.</hi> There may happen a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie
in ſome <hi>Article</hi> of Religion, which
perhaps thou haſt neither <hi>Time</hi> nor <hi>Skill</hi>
to ſettle thy own Mind about. Obſerve
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55562:50"/>
now, which way the generality of <hi>ſober
ſerious, praying</hi> People go: What grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<hi>good men</hi> is moſt likely to be the
<hi>Truth</hi> of God: Doſt thou ſee which way
the <hi>looſe, vile, carnal</hi> ſort of Men go?
Then, <hi>Come not into their ſecret, O my
Soul.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let us <hi>Walk</hi> with good Men in their <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices</hi>
too: Look upon their <hi>Mortification,</hi>
upon their <hi>Devotion,</hi> upon their <hi>Zeal,</hi> and be
able to ſay, as in <hi>2 Cor. 12. 18. Walked
not we in the ſame Spirit? Walked nor we
in the ſame Steps?</hi> There has been a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Tribe of <hi>Scholars</hi> in the World,
known by the Name of <hi>Walkers:</hi> 'Tis the
Name that all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may lay claim
unto; they are <hi>Walkers.</hi> O be of their
Society; ſay truly, <hi>I am a Companion of
them that fear God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE III.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>Eat</hi> well, that we may <hi>Walk</hi>
well. 'Tis written of <hi>Elijah,</hi> in <hi>1 Kings
19. 8. He did eat and drink, and went in
the ſtrength of that meat</hi> [eighty Miles]
<hi>unto the Mount of God.</hi> Would you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage
in a <hi>Walk with God?</hi> Let me then
ſay as the Angel to the Prophet, <hi>Ariſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55562:50"/>
and Eat, for the walk is too great for thee.</hi>
A twofold <hi>eating</hi> are we to be urg'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:
Let us by a <hi>Contemplative</hi> Eating
chew upon the <hi>Word</hi> of God. Never
do any Men <hi>Walk</hi> with God, like them
that can ſay, <hi>Meditation is ſweet unto me.</hi>
'Tis ſaid of <hi>Iſaac, He walked in the Fields
to Meditate:</hi> And indeed, <hi>He walked with
God,</hi> when he was alone at that Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <p>We ſhould after a <hi>Sermon,</hi> retire to
<hi>Ruminate</hi> thereupon. We ſhould in an
<hi>Evening</hi> reflect upon God's <hi>Mercy</hi> to us,
and our <hi>Carriage</hi> to him in the day fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going:
We ſhould often ſingle out ſome
<hi>Text</hi> or ſome <hi>Truth</hi> to Exerciſe our
Thoughts upon: This will ſtrengthen
us for our <hi>Walk.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Again, Let us by a <hi>Sacramental</hi> Eating
Feed upon the <hi>Bread</hi> of God. It is dreadful
to ſee what multitudes do turn their backs
upon the <hi>Table</hi> of the Lord. Alas! that ever
Men ſhould break the <hi>Laws</hi> of God, yea and
the <hi>Vows</hi> of God, as they do by this Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
Art not thou <hi>Baptized,</hi> and now Old
enough to be <hi>Confirmed?</hi> Then as often
as thou withdraweſt from the <hi>Supper</hi> of
the Lord, he ſets that mark upon thee,
<hi>There goes a Covenant-breaker out of Doors!</hi>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:55562:51"/>
Anſwer to this, <hi>Haſt thou a ſincere deſire to
Walk with God, or no?</hi> If thou haſt not,
how dareſt thou ſleep in that horrible
Perilous <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregeneracy?</hi> If thou haſt, then
come hither: Come lamenting all thy
Infirmities: Let thy weakneſs <hi>quicken</hi> thee;
and not <hi>hinder.</hi> O come for thy Food;
ſo thou ſhalt <hi>Walk and not faint;</hi> yea,
<hi>Run and not be weary.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE IV.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>be</hi> with God, that we may
<hi>Walk</hi> with Him. Be alwayes on <hi>God's
ſide</hi> againſt <hi>Sins</hi> ſide: All other <hi>ſiding</hi>
may be culpable, but this is <hi>Neceſſary,</hi>
this is <hi>Praiſe-worthy:</hi> Indeed <hi>Sin,</hi> that
calls like <hi>Jehu,</hi> in <hi>2. King. 9. 32. Who is
on my ſide? who?</hi> This is the outcry of
Superſtition and Profanity; <hi>Who is on my
ſide? who?</hi> But let me oppoſe that of
<hi>Moſes</hi> hereunto, in <hi>Exod. 32. 26. Who is
on the Lords ſide?</hi> Even ſo, Who is on the
<hi>ſide</hi> of Godlineſs and Honeſty? Who is
on the <hi>ſide</hi> of Holineſs and Sobriety?
Who will bear a Teſtimony to all the
<hi>Truths,</hi> and all the <hi>Wayes</hi> of the Lord?
Let us all be on that <hi>ſide,</hi> and <hi>Walk</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="rule">
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55562:51"/>
                        <head>RULE V.</head>
                        <p>Let us remember that we are <hi>Walking,</hi>
and it will be with God.</p>
                        <p>Keep up the frame of <hi>Mortals,</hi> and the
frame of <hi>Strangers</hi> in the World. O Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
as <hi>Joſhua,</hi> in <hi>Joſh. 23. 14. I am
going the way of all the Earth:</hi> Remember
thou art a <hi>Traveller.</hi> The Pſalmiſt ſays,
in <hi>Pſal. 39. 12. I am a Sojourner with God.</hi>
The way to be <hi>with God,</hi> is to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<hi>I am a Sojourner:</hi> O Remember this,
<hi>I am walking on the Borders of Eternity, every
day I am walking apace towards an eternal
home.</hi> This will make our <hi>Walk</hi> more ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
than that of the <hi>three things which go
well,</hi> or than that of the <hi>four things which
are comely in their going.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55562:52"/>
                  <head>THE
GOOD END
OF A
GOOD WALK.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>GEN. V. 24.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
And he was not, for God took him.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THe <hi>Walk</hi> of <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Happy</hi> Men, has
been the Subject of our Diſcourſe.
Behold the <hi>End</hi> of that <hi>Walk,</hi> now offering
it ſelf unto conſideration with us. The
Pſalmiſt hath ſaid unto us, in <hi>Pſal. 37. 37.
Mark the perfect, and behold the upright, for
the end of that man is peace.</hi> In the bleſſed
<hi>Enoch</hi> we may ſee ſuch an <hi>End</hi> of ſuch a
<hi>Man.</hi> Two little Clauſes comprize the
Account which <hi>Moſes</hi> has given of it; and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55562:52"/>
the double <hi>Eſtate</hi> of this Great Saint is
therein referred unto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>He was not.</hi> This points
at that <hi>Eſtate</hi> which he paſſed from. You
may conceive what <hi>he was,</hi> in regard of
his Condition and Employment here: But
now <hi>he was not</hi> that Sufferer, <hi>he was not</hi>
that Preacher any more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>God took him.</hi> This
points at that <hi>Eſtate</hi> which he paſſed into.
<hi>Good took him</hi> to Himſelf, <hi>God took him</hi> unto
all that Light, and Life, and Heaven,
which the Angels themſelves had before
the Aſcenſion of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>All that we have hitherto been told,
ſeems to be no more than what befalls every
<hi>godly Man.</hi> But no leſs an Interpreter
than the Spirit of God himſelf, by the
Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> has illuſtrated this Text
with a more ſurprizing Interpretation of it.
Conſult <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 5. and we have this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe
hereupon: Here it is ſaid, <hi>He was
not:</hi> There 'tis ſaid, <hi>He was not Found.</hi>
It ſeems that this Famous Prophet ſuddenly
<hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſappeared</hi> from the view of the World:
All Mankind with Wonder ſought, and
ask'd, and look'd after <hi>Enoch,</hi> as they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55562:53"/>
did after <hi>Elijah</hi> at another time; but they
could not <hi>find</hi> him. Why? What vvas
become of him? Here 'tis ſaid, <hi>God took
him:</hi> There 'tis ſaid, <hi>God had tranſlated
him, that he ſhould not ſee Death.</hi> This was
a very marvellous Providence! He had
born a zealous <hi>Witneſs</hi> for the Worſhip,
and the Truths, and the ways of God,
againſt a wicked World. God vvould
make them ſee that he own'd the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
and the Converſation of this vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
Man. Hence, though <hi>Abel</hi> was <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi>
for his Piety, <hi>Enoch</hi> ſhall be <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated</hi>
for his: He was immediately <hi>fetched,</hi>
and <hi>changed</hi> into the Circumſtances of the
Glorified. Thus he became, as <hi>Tertullian</hi>
ſays of him, <hi>A Candidate of Eternity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Doctrine</hi> which we are hence allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
an Application of, is,</p>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <head>
                        <hi>DOCT.</hi> To be taken by God from a Mortal Eſtate
on Earth, to a Glorious Eſtate in
Heaven, is the Priveledge of them
that Walk with him.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="proposition">
                        <head>PROP. I.</head>
                        <p>They that Walk with God, ſhall be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55562:53"/>
                           <hi>Taken</hi> by God from their <hi>Mortal Eſtate on
Earth.</hi> The Scholars of the Colledge at
<hi>Bethel,</hi> ſaid once unto <hi>Elijah,</hi> in <hi>2 King.
2. 3. Knoweſt thou that the Lord will take away
thy maſter from thy head to day? And he ſaid,
Yea, I know it.</hi> In like manner it may be
ſaid unto the <hi>Body</hi> of the Chriſtian; <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
thou that the Lord will take away thy Maſter,
thy Spirit from thy Head, into another ſtate
one day?</hi> Every Believer may reply, <hi>Yes,
I know that it will be ſo.</hi> Our <hi>Estate</hi> in this
World, is an Eſtate of <hi>Tryal;</hi> God is
here <hi>Trying,</hi> and <hi>Framing,</hi> and <hi>Shaping</hi> of
us, in order to everlaſting <hi>Happineſs</hi> or
<hi>Miſery.</hi> And it is an Eſtate of <hi>Trouble</hi> too:
Our Fall from God, is the occaſion of the
many <hi>Diſtreſſes</hi> that belong unto it. This
<hi>Mortal Estate</hi> of ours, the Lord will one
day take us from. <hi>One day,</hi> but on <hi>what
day</hi> ſhall this Deliverance be? Truly at our
<hi>laſt day,</hi> at the Day of our Death, at the
day that we are moſt ready to tremble at:
On that Day the Lord will <hi>deliver us from
the hand of all our enemies,</hi> and <hi>from the hand
of ſin.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> God will <hi>take</hi> the Believer from
the <hi>ſtate</hi> of a Sinner here. The dolorous
Anguiſhes of the beſt Men alive, are like
thoſe of the Apoſtle in <hi>Rom. 7. 24. O wretched
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55562:54"/>
man that I am! who ſhall deliver me from the
body of this death?</hi> Soul, I will tell thee
what ſhall do it; <hi>The Death of this Body
ſhall.</hi> That, that will do the deed. The
Believer is now lamenting, <hi>My iniquities
are more than the hairs of my head;</hi> he is
now lamenting, <hi>My wounds ſtink, and are
corrupt, becauſe of my fooliſhneſs.</hi> But we
ſhall not always be complaining ſo; <hi>God
will take</hi> us from all our Corruptions; <hi>God
will take</hi> us from all our Diſorders; <hi>God
will take</hi> us from the reach of ſo much as
one <hi>vain Thought</hi> for evermore. I may
ſpeak after <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deut. 12. 8. Ye ſhall not
do after all the things that we do here this day;</hi>
though <hi>ye are not as yet come to the reſt which
the Lord your God giveth you.</hi> When the
Walls of this Clay Tabernacle are batter'd
down, all the <hi>Leproſie</hi> which now cleaves
unto us, will be done away. We ſhall
ſhortly take an eternal farewel of every
<hi>Luſt,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Be gone, thou vile thing,
be gone, I will never ſee thee more.</hi> Indeed,
it was the curſed Womb of <hi>ſin,</hi> from
vvhich <hi>Death</hi> at firſt came into the World.
But O the Myſtery of Divine Wiſdom!
The <hi>Daughter</hi> deſtroys the <hi>Mother,</hi> and
by <hi>Death</hi> ſhall <hi>ſin</hi> go out of the World
again.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:55562:54"/>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> God will <hi>take</hi> the Believer from
the <hi>ſtate</hi> of a <hi>Mourner</hi> here. There are many
and mighty <hi>Temptations,</hi> which now cauſe
us to vex, as <hi>Rebeckah</hi> did at her Annoyances,
in <hi>Gen. 27. 46. I am weary of my life!</hi> Yea,
but vvhen thy <hi>life</hi> is expired, they ſhall
never <hi>weary</hi> thee any more. <hi>God will take</hi>
us from all <hi>ſeducing Temptations,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
all <hi>Evil Counſellors</hi> from our preſence
for ever. The <hi>fiery Darts</hi> of the <hi>Devil</hi>
ſhall not reach us and wound us as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
We ſhall not be put upon ſaying,
<hi>Get thee behind me, Satan;</hi> for <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall
be far enough <hi>below us.</hi> The time will
come, when we ſhall march as Conquerors
thorough theſe Territories of the <hi>Prince of
the Power of the Air;</hi> and at the utmoſt
Borders thereof, we ſhall give ſuch a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant
Shout, <hi>Adieu, foul Fiend, adieu!
The Son of</hi> David <hi>will never let me come into
thy devouring Jaws again.</hi> We ſhall go
likewiſe from the Intanglements of the
<hi>World.</hi> The <hi>things</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> we ſhall
turn our backs upon, as upon poor <hi>Trifles,</hi>
poor <hi>Nothings,</hi> and miſerable <hi>Comforters;</hi>
and vve ſhall ſay, <hi>To the Fire I leave you all.</hi>
The <hi>Men</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> vve ſhall be no
more <hi>flattered</hi> or <hi>terrified</hi> vvithal; but laugh
at all the <hi>Favour</hi> and all the <hi>Fury</hi> of thoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55562:55"/>
poor Worms, and ſay, as our Saviour to
the Jews, <hi>Whither I go, you cannot come.
God will take</hi> us from all <hi>afflicting Temptations</hi>
too. As for our <hi>Spirits,</hi> we ſhall not weep
as we do now, under our <hi>Doubts</hi> and our
<hi>Fears,</hi> nor any more ſay, <hi>God counteth me
for his Enemy.</hi> As for our <hi>Bodies,</hi> we ſhall
drop them; and all the <hi>Ails,</hi> and all the
<hi>Pains</hi> of them, as <hi>Elijah</hi> did his Mantle of
old. As for our <hi>Names,</hi> we ſhall be gone
from the <hi>ſcourge of the Tongue;</hi> there ſhall
be no <hi>Shimei</hi> to curſe us in the <hi>New-Jeruſalem</hi>
which we go unto. No <hi>Loſſes,</hi> no <hi>Croſſes</hi> will
then affect us; nor <hi>Cain</hi>'s Club of Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ever lay a blow upon us any more.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God will take the Believer from
the <hi>ſtate</hi> of a <hi>Waiter</hi> here. It is the Voice
of all good Men, in <hi>2 Cor. 5. 2. We groan
earneſtly deſiring to be cloathed upon with our
houſe which is from Heaven.</hi> Our laſt <hi>groans</hi>
will put a period unto thoſe <hi>groans. God
will take</hi> us from our <hi>Faith,</hi> and from our
<hi>Hope;</hi> it ſhall be turned into <hi>Sight,</hi> and
<hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> World without end. We
ſhall, e're long, leave looking for <hi>the Reſt
which remaineth for the People of God:</hi> Leave
looking for that <hi>City, whoſe Builder and
Maker is God:</hi> Leave looking the <hi>Crown of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55562:55"/>
Life, the Crown that fadeth not away.</hi> We
ſhall <hi>have</hi> what we have been <hi>looking</hi> for;
and we ſhall be <hi>taken</hi> from our humble,
prayerful, careful <hi>Expectations</hi> of it. We
ſhall no more be <hi>panting</hi> after the <hi>Promiſe,</hi>
and ſaying, <hi>O when will it come unto me!</hi> All
the <hi>ſure Mercies</hi> of the Covenant will ſay
unto us, <hi>We are come, we are come; we are
now thine for evermore.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="proposition">
                        <head>PROP. II.</head>
                        <p>They that Walk with God, ſhall be
<hi>taken</hi> by God unto a <hi>glorious Eſtate in Heaven</hi>
too.</p>
                        <p>We ſhall be <hi>taken</hi> by God, when we are
<hi>taken</hi> by Death. But unto what ſhall we
be <hi>taken?</hi> A New <hi>Sight</hi> will chiefly conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
the New <hi>State</hi> vvhich God will take us
to. In ſhort, we ſhall be <hi>taken</hi> to a <hi>Full,
Refreſhing, Transforming ſight of God in
Chriſt, among the Righteous for ever.</hi> I
ſhall give but a <hi>touch</hi> at theſe things; we
do but ſtammer and ſtumble vvhen we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
a Deſcription of them. Indeed,
I know not vvhether I had beſt offer at
any Deſcription of this <hi>glorious Eſtate;</hi> or
inſtead thereof, only ſay as he ſaid unto
<hi>Nathanael</hi> once, <hi>Go and ſee.</hi> Yet however,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55562:56"/>
this little Cluſter of Notions we may carry
with us to the <hi>heavenly Countrey,</hi> from
vvhence they were brought unto us.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> God will <hi>take</hi> the Believer unto
a <hi>ſtate</hi> wherein he ſhall be immediately
<hi>beholding of himſelf in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> We
ſhall come into the Preſence of our Lord,
and behold our <hi>Joſeph,</hi> our Jeſus, <hi>in all his
glory.</hi> There ſhall then be fulfilled that
part of our Lord's Interceſſion, in <hi>Joh. 17.
24. Let them be with me, where I am, that
they may behold my glory. God will take</hi> us,
where we ſhall ſee the Countenance, and
hear the Conference too of that Man, in
vvhom <hi>dwells the fulneſs of the Godhead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.
God will take</hi> us into the Embraces
of him vvho has <hi>loved us, and waſhed us away
from our ſins in his own blood.</hi> And when
we ſee him, we ſhall ſee <hi>God</hi> in him. I
ſuppoſe that he is the large Golden Veſſel
full of <hi>God,</hi> from which the heavenly Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
of God are to be derived for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.
Our Felicity ſhall be that in <hi>Mat.
5. 8. They ſhall ſee God. God will take</hi> us,
vvhere we ſhall be made ſenſible of his <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes</hi>
and <hi>Perfections,</hi> in a meaſure that
we are not us'd unto. <hi>God will take</hi> us,
vvhere we ſhall not ſo much in any Creature
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55562:56"/>
as in the <hi>Mediator, ſee him that is Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> God will <hi>take</hi> the Believer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
a <hi>State</hi> wherein he ſhall be wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>Conformed to Himſelf and Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
The Children of God have His <hi>Nature,</hi>
His <hi>Image</hi> now upon them, they ſhall
hereafter arrive to the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of it, and
be <hi>filled with all the fulneſs of God:</hi> The
Pſalmiſt could ſay, in <hi>Pſal. 17. 15. I
ſhall be ſatisfied, when I awake with the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of God. God will take</hi> us vvhere our
<hi>Knowledge</hi> will be enlarged like the <hi>ſands</hi>
on the Sea-ſhore: Where our <hi>Vertue</hi>
ſhall be compleated into <hi>an Heart after
God's own Heart: God will take</hi> us, vvhere
the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> will repleniſh us
with bright <hi>Beams</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi>
until we <hi>be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as
he is.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God will take the Believer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
a <hi>State,</hi> wherein he ſhall enjoy the
beſt <hi>Society</hi> of moſt <hi>Righteous</hi> Ones. We
ſhall be able to ſpeak after the manner
of the Apoſtle, in <hi>Heb. 12. 22. I am come
to an innumerable company of Angels, and to
the general Aſſembly of the firſt-born.</hi> The
<hi>Angels</hi> they are our <hi>Guardians</hi> now: <hi>God
will take</hi> us, where they ſhall be our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55562:57"/>
                           <hi>Companions.</hi> We ſhall move and
live among thoſe <hi>morning Stars:</hi> The <hi>Firſt-born,</hi>
they are our <hi>Familiars</hi> here; we
covet their being ſo, notwithſtanding all
the <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> and <hi>Ill humour</hi> that
is often in them: <hi>God will take</hi> us, vvhere
we ſhall aſſociate our ſelves with all that
ever feared God, and not one breach of
<hi>Charity,</hi> ſhall ever diſturb our Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
there.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>State</hi> which God will
take the Believers into the Comforts of,
will be an <hi>Eternal State. God will take</hi> us
to an <hi>Houſe;</hi> but what a one? We read
in <hi>2 Cor. 5. 1. It will be an eternal Houſe.
God will take</hi> us to a <hi>Glory:</hi> But of what
ſort is it? We read in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 10. It
is an <hi>eternal glory. God will take</hi> us to
an <hi>Inheritance;</hi> But how long ſhall it laſt?
We read in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 15. It is an <hi>Eternal
Inheritance.</hi> Truly it is a <hi>Life Eternal</hi>
which our God will <hi>take</hi> us to. We
ſhall be in it as many Millions of Ages
as there are <hi>Drops</hi> in the Ocean, or <hi>Atoms</hi>
in the Univerſe; yet Believer thou ſhalt
ſay, <hi>My Heaven will infinitely outlaſt as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Ages more:</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="proposition">
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55562:57"/>
                        <head>Prop. III.</head>
                        <p>There is a <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> uſed
by God in his thus <hi>taking</hi> of them that
Walk with him.</p>
                        <p>The Lords <hi>taking</hi> of Men is, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
by his <hi>changing</hi> of them, it is by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
that they <hi>ſhall not be:</hi> Not an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilation,</hi>
but a vaſt <hi>Alteration</hi> happens to
Believers; when it ſhall be ſaid of them,
<hi>They are not!</hi> And then they are <hi>taken</hi> by
the Lord: And in particular it is mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
three ſuch ways as theſe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is by <hi>Dying;</hi> when we <hi>Dye,</hi>
then we <hi>are not.</hi> The Dying Man may
ſay, as in <hi>Pſal. 39. 13. I go hence, I am
no more.</hi> The Dead Man <hi>is not</hi> a Man in
ſuch a <hi>place,</hi> he <hi>is not</hi> a Man of ſuch a
<hi>Thought,</hi> he <hi>is not</hi> acting upon ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
as he was before. When a Man is
ready to Dye, we perceive it by <hi>Changing,</hi>
as we call it, of the Man; much more,
when a Man is dead he is a <hi>changed</hi> Man.
Then it is that we are <hi>taken</hi> by the Lord:
Thus it is ſaid, in <hi>Iſa. 57. 1. The Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
is taken</hi> away. The <hi>Spirit</hi> is then <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi>
to all the Delights and Pleaſures that
a <hi>ſeparate Soul</hi> can feed upon.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55562:58"/>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is by <hi>Riſing.</hi> When vve
<hi>Riſe</hi> at the laſt day, then vve <hi>are not;</hi> vve
<hi>are not</hi> ſuch feeble vvretched things as
we are this day. The <hi>Reſurrection</hi> will
bring a marvellous <hi>Change</hi> on the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
of it: It is the Speech of <hi>Job,</hi> in Ch.
14. 14. <hi>If a man dye, ſhall he live again?</hi>
He ſeems to refute vvhat he did recite
juſt before as the Opinion of too many
Men, and ſay now, <hi>Yes, that he ſhall find.</hi>
And hence it is added, <hi>I will wait all the
Dayes of my appointed time until my Change
come.</hi> What <hi>Change</hi> is that? I will not
exclude or oppoſe the common ſenſe of
it; yet I would humbly ſuggeſt, vvhy may
it not be the <hi>Change</hi> which the next
Words referr unto? <hi>Thou ſhalt call and
I will anſwer thee; thou wilt have a deſire
to the work of thine Hands.</hi> At the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi>
it will be ſo; God will then have
a <hi>Deſire</hi> to ſee our once Curious, but novv
Rotten <hi>Body,</hi> ſet in order again, he ſhall
then call, <hi>Ariſe, ye Dead, where are you?
Ariſe!</hi> And we ſhall ſtart out of the Duſt,
as it were, anſvvering, <hi>Lord! I come!</hi> This
the <hi>Departed Soul</hi> is to keep <hi>waiting</hi> for.
It ſeems more than a <hi>Moment,</hi> it may
ſeem a <hi>long while</hi> to the Soul 'till this be
accompliſhed: Then it is alſo that we are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55562:58"/>
                           <hi>taken</hi> by the Lord: with ſome reſpect unto
this our Lord ſaid unto his Diſciples, in
<hi>Joh. 14. 3. I will come again, and take you unto
my ſelf:</hi> The <hi>Body</hi> is then alſo <hi>taken,</hi> to be
an <hi>Incorruptible,</hi> a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and a <hi>Powerful</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
of the Soul in all the motions of it.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is another <hi>Taking</hi> that
ſome have Experience of, and that is by
<hi>Tranſlation.</hi> There are ſome Perſons, in
whom the <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between their <hi>ſpirits</hi> and
their <hi>bodies</hi> never is diſſolved; by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
of Angels they are both in <hi>ſpirit</hi> and
in <hi>body</hi> too made capable of a preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<hi>into the Kingdom of God,</hi> and ſo
thoſe vvinged Meſſengers of Heaven carry
them avvay, vvithout any more ado. This
vvas the Prerogative of <hi>Enoch</hi> before the
Law, and of <hi>Elijah</hi> under it: I believe this
would have been the Caſe of all Men, if
<hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinned vvhen he did; and
there are many thouſands of Pious People
vvith vvhom it will yet be ſo. At the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
Coming</hi> of our Lord, there will be
multitudes of Chriſtians in the World;
vvhat vvill become of them, vvhen the Fire
of God ſhall be flaming and raging as far as
<hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood did extend of old? How ſhall
they get out of the vvay of that horrible
Fire that ſhall conſume and carry all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                              <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="application">
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:55562:59"/>
                        <p>be? Hear <hi>Davids</hi> Anſwer to that Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
in <hi>1 Chron. 28. 15. Our days on Earth
are as a Shadow, and there is none abiding:</hi>
Let <hi>James</hi> anſwer it, in <hi>Jam. 4. 14. What
is your Life? it is even a Vapour, that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
for a little time, and vaniſhes away:</hi> Let
<hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> anſwer it, in <hi>Job. 9. 25. My dayes are
ſwifter than a Poſt; they are paſſed away as
the ſwift Ships; as an Eagle that haſtens to the
Prey.</hi> Our Age is now contracted into <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty</hi>
Years, and how few reach to <hi>Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
in compariſon of them that never ſee
<hi>Twenty</hi> of them! Beſides, a big part of
our <hi>few dayes</hi> are already paſt and gone
with many of us: How many may ſadly ſit
and ſigh and ſay this day, <hi>I have been here
but a little while, yet I cannot now be ſo long
more, as I have already been!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Conſider, 2. If <hi>God</hi> then <hi>take</hi> us not,
<hi>who will?</hi> I have read of a profane Monſter
who on one ſide of his Sword had the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
of <hi>Christ,</hi> on the other ſide the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
of the <hi>Devil;</hi> with this Motto under
it, <hi>Si tu non vis, iſte rogitat:</hi> If <hi>He</hi> won't
<hi>Take</hi> me, here's <hi>One</hi> that will. Horrid
Creature! But that Frenzy is almoſt equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
among us, by thoſe that wiſh the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
to <hi>take</hi> them every day: Alas! that,
that will be the horrible Deſtruction of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55562:59"/>
them that ſhall not be <hi>taken</hi> by the Lord.
It is a fearful Curſe upon the wicked
Man, in <hi>Pſal. 109. 6. Let Satan ſtand at his
right hand:</hi> Thus, O thus it will be.
When the Soul of a wicked Man is going
away, a <hi>Devil,</hi> a Dragon ſtands by his
Bed-ſide, and will <hi>take,</hi> and hold, and
wound that miſerable Soul. Yea, there
is a more aſtoniſhing Vengeance to come
upon ſuch a Man. If a Man be not <hi>taken</hi>
by the <hi>ſaving</hi> Hands, he will be <hi>taken</hi> by
the <hi>damning</hi> Hands of <hi>God</hi> himſelf. The
<hi>Hands</hi> of the Great and Terrible God,
will for ever <hi>take</hi> thoſe that fall thereinto;
and <hi>ſmite</hi> them and <hi>ſlay</hi> them with imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
Impreſſions of his Fiery Wrath.
But what ſayes the Apoſtle, in <hi>Heb. 10. 31.
It is a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of
the living God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>What, what ſhall now be done by us?
in ſhort; let us be <hi>Walking</hi> with God,
and we ſhall be <hi>taken</hi> by God. Say now,
every Soul, as in <hi>Mic. 4. 5. We will walk
in the Name of our God for ever and ever.
Elijah</hi> was <hi>taken</hi> as he was <hi>walking:</hi> Let us
<hi>Walk</hi> thus, and God will <hi>take</hi> us: Be ſure
God will <hi>take</hi> us, if we <hi>take</hi> Him. Let
us <hi>take</hi> him as our <hi>Lord; take</hi> him as our
<hi>End; take</hi> him as our <hi>exceeding great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
                           <pb n="42" facs="tcp:55562:60"/>
Thus <hi>take</hi> Him in our <hi>Walk,</hi> and
He will <hi>take</hi> us from our <hi>Walk</hi> to our
<hi>Crown.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="application">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE II. Conſolation.</head>
                        <p>Let it be our <hi>Joy,</hi> that when we <hi>are not,</hi>
we ſhall be <hi>taken by the Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Behold a Cordial here, againſt three
ſorts of Exerciſes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> Againſt all the <hi>Troubles</hi> of this <hi>Life.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>We are apt to be diſcouraged at the
Difficulties of this Evil World: But the
Voice of our God unto us, is that, in
<hi>Luke 21. 28. Lift up your Heads, for your
Redemption draweth nigh.</hi> E're long you ſhall
<hi>not be;</hi> and then your Afflictions too, they
ſhall <hi>not be:</hi> God will <hi>take</hi> you from them
all. And what ſays <hi>Paul</hi>'s Calculation, in
<hi>Rom. 8. 18. For I reckon</hi> (he ſpeaks like an
Arithmetician, or an Accomptant) <hi>that
the ſufferings of this preſent time, are not
worthy to be compared with the Glory which ſhall
be Revealed.</hi> When two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,
one that was <hi>Blind,</hi> another that
was <hi>Lame,</hi> were leading to be Burned,
they ſo cheared one another, <hi>Well fare we,
we ſhall need our Crutches and our Guides no
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55562:60"/>
more after this.</hi> Thus let us in all our Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als
think, <hi>When I am beyond the Stars, I
never ſhall be under the Clouds any more.</hi> Have
you any <hi>Sorrows</hi> hard to bear? Are you
afflicted in your <hi>Friends?</hi> Haſt thou like
<hi>David,</hi> a <hi>Son</hi> that makes thee ſay, <hi>My
life is ſpent with Grief?</hi> Haſt thou like <hi>Jeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tah,</hi>
a <hi>Daughter</hi> that makes thee ſay, <hi>Alas!
thou haſt brought me very low, thou art one
of them that trouble me?</hi> Haſt thou <hi>Job</hi>'s
or <hi>Abigail</hi>'s Yoke upon thee? O think, <hi>I
ſhall ſhortly be gone from the Light and Senſe
of ſuch things as theſe.</hi> Are you afflicted in
your <hi>Names?</hi> Are you like <hi>Elijah,</hi> count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
a <hi>Troubler of Iſrael?</hi> or like <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
a <hi>Man of Contention;</hi> or like <hi>Paul,</hi> a <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Fellow,</hi> and a <hi>mover of Sedition?</hi> O
think, <hi>I ſhall meet with none of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches
where I am going?</hi> Are you affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
in your <hi>Bodies,</hi> or your <hi>Eſtates?</hi> Are
you like <hi>Timothy,</hi> cruciated with <hi>often In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities?</hi>
Or like <hi>Naomi,</hi> going out <hi>full,</hi>
and coming home <hi>empty</hi> of Temporal
Goods? O think, <hi>I ſhall quickly be where
a Spital or an Alms-houſe, tbere never was
any occaſion for.</hi> Are there any <hi>ſnares</hi> that
you are too often trepan'd into? O think
of the Time when all this <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall be
to you as an <hi>Inviſible point;</hi> think, <hi>The
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                                 <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55562:61"/>
Dy'd;</hi> and ſee how they <hi>Covenanted,</hi> and
<hi>Walked</hi> and <hi>Lived</hi> with the Lord. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks
theſe do now call unto us, as in
<hi>Luk. 23. 28. Weep not for me, but weep for
your ſelves:</hi> Does <hi>Jacob</hi> ſay, <hi>Joſeph is not?</hi>
Does <hi>Rachel</hi> ſay, <hi>My Children are not?</hi>
Why, has God <hi>taken</hi> them? they belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto Him. 'Tis ſaid, in <hi>Joh. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>.
Jeſus wept over Lazarus:</hi> One of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients
affirms, it was not becauſe he was
<hi>Dead,</hi> but becauſe he was about to be
made <hi>Alive</hi> again. I do not juſtifie the
Gloſs; but I am ſure our departed Ones,
as it were call unto us, from the lofty
Battlements of Heaven, <hi>We would not be
with you again for all the World.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let us then riſe, and waſh and change
our Apparel, and ſay, <hi>I will go to them, they
ſhall not return unto me.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:55562:61"/>
                  <head>THE
DUTY
AND
INTEREST
OF
YOUTH:
OR,
The Thought of an Elder, on the
Death of a Younger Brother.
Uttered Octob. 28. 1688.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>Eccl. XII. 1.</bibl>
                     <q>Remember Now thy Creator in the dayes
of thy Youth.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THE great Emperor, <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> making
an Oration to his mutinous Army,
began it with that ſurprizing Expreſſion,
<hi>Audite ſenem, Juvenes quem Juvenem ſenes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55562:62"/>
audierunt;</hi> when I was a <hi>young</hi> Man, <hi>old</hi>
Men counted me worthy to ſpeak unto
them; now I am an <hi>old</hi> Man, methinks
<hi>young</hi> Men ſhould not refuſe to mind what
I ſay: Truly, ſuch might the Speech of
our <hi>Solomon</hi> be, by way of Preface to the
Text now read unto us; ſurely this <hi>old</hi>
Preacher deſerves the attention of every
<hi>young</hi> Perſon among us all. It is a Paſſage
uttered by this matchleſs and inſpired
Prince, in <hi>Prov. 22. 20. Have not I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
to thee excellent things?</hi> It is by ſome
rendred ſo, <hi>Have not I three times written
for thee?</hi> He hath indeed ſo; we have <hi>three
Books</hi> compoſed by that Royal and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
Pen; one of which wears the <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>
of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> becauſe that <hi>ſuch</hi> was
the <hi>Author</hi> of it. We are told of ſome
in <hi>2 Chron. 11. 17. They walked in the way
of</hi> David <hi>and of</hi> Solomon: What <hi>way</hi> is
that? It was the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> that he
ſinn'd, he fell, he diſhonoured God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly,
but he ſoon Repented and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered,
and then by writing the <hi>fifty firſt</hi>
Pſalm he gave an Evidence of his doing
ſo. This was the way of <hi>Solomon</hi> too; he
departed from God with a wonderful Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy,
but being reclaimed and reduced
from his Wanderings, he now Publiſhes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55562:62"/>
a Teſtimony of it unto all the World.</p>
                  <p>This Book is a ſacred and ſolemn Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,
<hi>concerning the chief good of Man:</hi> It
contains the Holy and Humble <hi>Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
of a famous Monarch, who had <hi>ſought</hi>
where he could not <hi>find</hi> the ſatisfaction of
an Immortal Soul; he had got up to the <hi>top</hi>
of all ſublunary Felicity, and from thence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
poor Men toil and ſweat unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
to get up the rocky ragged <hi>Hill</hi> after
him, with a loud Voice he now calls unto
them all, <hi>You are miſtaken, there is nothing but
Vanity and Vexation here:</hi> Upon this the
wiſe Man aſſures us all, That in the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance</hi>
and the <hi>Enjoyment</hi> of God alone
is all our Happineſs; and in the inculcation
of it, <hi>Young Men</hi> are particularly apply'd
unto: We have a <hi>Dehortation</hi> given to
them in the concluſion of the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and an <hi>Exhortation</hi> in the beginning
of this: In the former is a ſharp <hi>Sarcaſm,</hi>
but a grave <hi>Counſel</hi> in the latter. Two
things make up the <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> A <hi>Duty</hi> enjoyned, <hi>Remember thy
Creator;</hi> in the Hebrew 'tis <hi>Thy Creators,</hi>
which notes a plurality of Perſons in the
adorable Godhead.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> A <hi>Seaſon</hi> adviſed, <hi>In the dayes
of thy Youth:</hi> It intimates not that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55562:63"/>
                     <hi>paſt</hi> their <hi>Youth</hi> are exempted from this
Command, but that Perſons <hi>in</hi> their <hi>Youth</hi>
are peculiarly engaged herein; wherefore
the <hi>Doctrine</hi> before us, is,</p>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Doctrine.</hi> It is the Duty of <hi>All</hi> Men, and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly
of <hi>Young</hi> Men, to Remember
their Creator, ſo as to acknowledge
Him.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="proposition">
                        <head>Prop. I.</head>
                        <p>The Bleſſed God, who is <hi>Father,</hi> and
<hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> is the <hi>Creator</hi> of Men:
Unto <hi>Man</hi> about <hi>God</hi> it may be ſaid, <hi>He
is thy Creators.</hi> Indeed in God there are
more <hi>Perſons</hi> than one. In the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
that <hi>Myſtery</hi> of a <hi>Trinity</hi> is more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
inſiſted on. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> of old
would ſay unto them that had any Doubt
about the <hi>Trinity, Go to Jordan, and you
may ſee what you ſeek.</hi> On the Banks of
<hi>Jordan,</hi> at the Baptiſm of our Saviour,
in <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 16, 17. we have a Glorious
Repreſentation of it. But in the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi>
too, the <hi>Miſtery</hi> of a <hi>Trinity</hi> is not
concealed from the Church of God; the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55562:63"/>
                           <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> alone may be enough
to give a mention of it: We find <hi>God</hi> the
<hi>Creator,</hi> we find a <hi>Creating Word,</hi> and we
find a <hi>Creating Spirit</hi> there diſtinctly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
of. The very <hi>firſt Clauſe</hi> in the Bible
is, <hi>In the Beginning God Created:</hi> The Name,
<hi>God,</hi> is in the plural Number, but the
Verb, <hi>Created,</hi> is in the ſingular; which
intimates, that though there be but <hi>one
God,</hi> yet there is more than <hi>one Perſon</hi> in
Him. The like Intimation is given to
us, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. Where <hi>God ſaid, Let us
make Man in our Image.</hi> It is impious to
ſuppoſe that the <hi>Angels</hi> are <hi>conſulted</hi> or
<hi>invited</hi> for the making of Man; 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
ſaid, <hi>God made him:</hi> Nor in any
Caſe would the Moſt High ſpeak to <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentul
Cauſes</hi> in the <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſt Perſon</hi> plural
ſo. The fond and blind Jews are put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
wretched ſhifts, when they would ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
their Notice of a <hi>Trinity</hi> from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
thus plain and clear. Now this great
God, who is thus <hi>Three in One,</hi> is the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi>
of the World. The moſt <hi>High God</hi>
who is the <hi>Poſſeſſor,</hi> is alſo the <hi>Creator</hi> of
Heaven and Earth. It is true, that in
ſome ſort the Work of <hi>Creation</hi> belongs
moſt properly to the <hi>Father,</hi> but the <hi>Son</hi>
and the <hi>Spirit</hi> alſo are not excluded from
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55562:64"/>
a glorious concurrence in it: Unto him is
every Man to aſcribe his own <hi>Creation</hi> and
<hi>Original:</hi> We are thus called upon in
<hi>Pſal. 100. 3. Know ye that the Lord he is
God, it is he that hath made us, and not we
our ſelves.</hi> That ſtyle, <hi>my Maker,</hi> that is
the ſtyle in which all <hi>Men</hi> that were not
far worſe than <hi>Devils</hi> have ever ſpoken of
the Lord.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="proposition">
                        <head>Prop. II.</head>
                        <p>It is the Duty of <hi>All</hi> Men to <hi>Remember</hi>
their <hi>Creator:</hi> It is a juſt matter of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry
here, <hi>What it is to Remember God?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Anſwer in ſhort is this, To <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
God is to <hi>Acknowledge</hi> God. Or,
Take <hi>Solomon</hi>'s own Explanation of it, in
our Context here: <hi>It is to fear God, and
keep his Commandments.</hi> There is both
<hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> imply'd in this
<hi>Remembrance:</hi> To <hi>Remember</hi> God is to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
all the Reſpect which we owe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
him, and to <hi>Render</hi> all that we <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
The Phraſe of Scripture is to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted
by ſuch comprehenſive Rules
as this. It is the Character of <hi>wicked</hi> Men,
<hi>to forget God.</hi> 'Tis ſaid in <hi>Pſal. 9. 17. The
wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55562:64"/>
Nations that forget God.</hi> So then, <hi>to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
God,</hi> this is the Character of <hi>Godly</hi>
Men: <hi>To be ſenſible of God,</hi> that, that is
to <hi>Remember</hi> him. There is a two-fold <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring</hi>
of a thing: There is a <hi>keeping</hi> of
it in our minds, and there is a <hi>calling</hi> of
it to our minds: This <hi>Remembrance</hi> we
are to acknowledge God withal. In ſhort,
we may obſerve that <hi>Solomon</hi> much imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
his <hi>Father,</hi> both in the matter and the
manner of his Preaching to the World;
particularly, what <hi>Solomon</hi> here ſays to
us, is but an Expreſſion of the ſame that
his <hi>Father</hi> ſaid to him, in <hi>1 Chron. 28. 9.
My Son, know thou the God of thy Father, and
ſerve him.</hi> In this manner we are to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> We ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> God by our
<hi>knowing</hi> of him: We are to <hi>Remember, That
God is,</hi> and, <hi>That he is a Rewarder of them
that diligently ſeek him.</hi> We are to <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi>
that there is a <hi>God</hi> who is <hi>Infinite</hi> in
his <hi>Power,</hi> his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and his
<hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and that his <hi>Kingdom ruleth over
all.</hi> It is ſaid in <hi>Jer. 51. 50. Remember the
Lord afar off:</hi> Part of the meaning is,
<hi>Know the Lord.</hi> Strictly, 'tis impoſſible for
a Man to <hi>Remember</hi> what he do's not <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</hi>
We ſhould <hi>know</hi> God in his <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience,</hi>
                           <pb n="54" facs="tcp:55562:65"/>
and <hi>Know</hi> God in his <hi>efficience;</hi> we
ſhould <hi>know</hi> God as repreſented in his
<hi>Words,</hi> in his <hi>Works,</hi> and above all, in the
<hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It was of old counted
a needful Counſel, <hi>Know thy ſelf;</hi> it is no
leſs important and pertinent, <hi>Know thy
God:</hi> This <hi>Knowledge,</hi> it hath <hi>Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi>
in it.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> God by
our <hi>Thinking</hi> on him. The Pſalmiſt could
ſay in <hi>Pſal. 63. 6. I Remember thee upon my
Bed, and Meditate on thee in the Night-watches.</hi>
We ſhould have a <hi>Remembrance</hi> of, with
a <hi>Meditation</hi> on the Holy God; awful
and ſerious <hi>Thoughts</hi> of God ſhould come
into our Hearts often in a day: We ſhould
often be <hi>Thinking</hi> of God as our <hi>Judge,</hi> and
we ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> with our ſelves, <hi>I am
now under the flaming Eye of God, and I ſhall
one day ſtand before the Judgment-ſeat of God.</hi>
We ſhould often be <hi>Thinking</hi> of God as
our <hi>End,</hi> and we ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> with
our ſelves, <hi>God has formed me for himſelf, I
ſhould ſhew forth his praiſe.</hi> We ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
be <hi>Thinking</hi> of God as our <hi>Good,</hi> and
we ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> with our ſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                           <hi>The
Lord is my portion, and I have a goodly heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi>
Briefly, what the Lord is in himſelf,
the ſame is he to be in our daily Thoughts
of him.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="55" facs="tcp:55562:65"/>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> God by
<hi>Turning</hi> to him: It is a Prophecy in <hi>Pſal.
22. 27. All the Ends of the World ſhall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
and turn unto the Lord.</hi> We ſhould
have a <hi>Remembrance</hi> of God, that ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<hi>Repentance</hi> for ſin: The Pſalmiſt has
communicated this Experience of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
us, <hi>I Remembred God, I was troubled:</hi>
O thus we ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> God, and be
<hi>troubled</hi> for our forſaking of him; be <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi>
for our provoking of him; and when
we are troubled for, we ſhould alſo be
<hi>turned</hi> from all our evil wayes. We are
to <hi>Remember</hi> God, ſo as to <hi>chooſe</hi> him, and
to <hi>take</hi> him for our God, and ſincerely ſay,
<hi>Lord! What have I any more to do with Idols?</hi>
ſincerely ſay, <hi>I will be now for the Lord, and
not for another.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Fourthly, <hi>We ſhould</hi> Remember <hi>God by</hi>
Living <hi>for him. It is the Profeſſion of
that good man in</hi> Pſal. 119. 55. I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred
thy Name, and have kept thy Law:
<hi>There ſhould an</hi> Obedience <hi>accompany that</hi>
Remembrance <hi>which we have of God. The
Prophet could ſay,</hi> I Remembred the Lord,
and my Prayer came unto thee: <hi>Thus we
ſhould be able to ſay,</hi> I Remembred the
Lord, and I ſought his Face: <hi>Be able to ſay,</hi>
I Remembred the Lord, and I heard his Word:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55562:66"/>
                           <hi>Be able to ſay,</hi> I Remembred the Lord, and
with my whole care I pleaſed the Lord. <hi>An</hi>
Honouring <hi>of the Lord, is the beſt</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring
<hi>of Him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fifthly,</hi> We ſhould <hi>Remember</hi> God by
<hi>Truſting</hi> in him. It was an Holy Triumph,
in <hi>Pſal. 20. 7. Some truſt in Chariots, and
ſome in Horſes, but we will remember the
Name of the Lord our God.</hi> A <hi>Remembrance</hi>
of God ſhould be with a <hi>Reliance</hi> on him.
<hi>That</hi> Believer could ſay, <hi>O my God, my
Soul is caſt down within me, therefore will I
remember thee.</hi> Are there <hi>Diſtreſſes</hi> on us,
that cauſe <hi>Dejections</hi> in us? We ſhould
then <hi>Remember</hi> that God who can do what
he will; then <hi>Remember</hi> that God who has
bid us hope in him: And when we <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
him,</hi> we ſhould ſtill joyfully ſay, <hi>My
help is in the Name of the Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Finally, Such a <hi>Remembrance</hi> of God as
will procure an <hi>Intereſt</hi> in God; ſuch a
<hi>Remembrance</hi> of God as will maintain a
<hi>Communion</hi> with God: This is the <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi>
that we are to endeavour for.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="proposition">
                        <head>Prop. III.</head>
                        <p>To <hi>Remember their Creator</hi> is a thing that
<hi>Young</hi> Men are very particularly oblig'd
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55562:66"/>
unto. Indeed <hi>Young</hi> Men are apt to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon
this the moſt <hi>improper</hi> and <hi>unpleaſant</hi>
Addreſs that can be made unto them, <hi>Do
thou Remember thy Creator:</hi> They judge it
fitter only for elder Men to hear of ſuch
a ſerious thing: But the Voice of God
is even to <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thee, O Young</hi> Man!
<hi>Do thou Remember me.</hi> There are two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
here ſet before us, evincing this
to be a moſt <hi>reaſonable</hi> thing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="argument">
                        <head>Argument 1.</head>
                        <p>'Tis thy <hi>Creator</hi> certainly: The <hi>Young</hi>
Man, be he never ſo <hi>young,</hi> has cauſe to
<hi>Remember</hi> him. It was but a rational Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal
in <hi>Pſal. 95. 6. O come, let us worſhip
and bow down, let us kneel before the Lord our
Maker.</hi> If God be thy <hi>Maker,</hi> it becomes
thee to be his <hi>Servant:</hi> Thou art wholly
beholden to God for all the <hi>Powers</hi> of thy
Spirit, for all the <hi>Members</hi> of thy Body:
Whom ſhouldeſt thou then firſt uſe them
for, but the Lord alone? It was a ſharp
Rebuke to <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in <hi>Dan. 5. 22. The
God in whoſe hands thy breath is, him thou
haſt not glorified:</hi> Even ſo, thy <hi>Breath</hi> and
<hi>Being</hi> is from the Lord, and ſhall it be
ſaid of thee, <hi>Him thou haſt not Remembred?</hi>
                           <pb n="58" facs="tcp:55562:67"/>
this were a very vile thing indeed! It is
a ſimilitude uſed, if I miſtake not, by
ſome of the Ancients, <hi>If any Man could
be ſo ingenious as to make an Engine able
to think or ſpeak, he might juſtly expect the
firſt work of that Engine ſhould be to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
the maker of it.</hi> Thus, <hi>Young Man,</hi>
it was but lately that thou camoſt out of
the Hands of <hi>God;</hi> the firſt <hi>rational</hi> Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of ſuch an one, ſurely ſhould be a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi>
Action. It cannot be too ſoon for
thee to <hi>Remember</hi> him, in whom thy <hi>liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
and thy <hi>moving,</hi> and thy very <hi>being</hi>
is.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="argument">
                        <head>Argument 2.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The Evil Dayes</hi> are coming, of which
thou ſhalt ſay, <hi>I have no pleaſure in them.
Old-Age</hi> is not a Time for the Service of
God to be begun in, or to be delayed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;
<hi>Youth, Youth</hi> is the only Time.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt, Old-Age</hi> is not a <hi>proper Time</hi> for
us to defer the <hi>Remembring</hi> of God unto.
It is an unworthy thing to deal with the
God of Heaven ſo: It is an <hi>abſurd</hi> as well
as a <hi>wicked</hi> thing. The Lord complained
of this, in <hi>Mal. 1. 13. Ye brought that which
was torn, and the lame, and the ſick, thus ye
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55562:67"/>
brought an Offering, ſhould I accept this of
your hands, ſaith the Lord?</hi> In like ſort,
<hi>Young</hi> Man, is it ſuitable that the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>
ſhould have the <hi>Prime</hi> of thy Strength?
And that God ſhould be put off with
a few <hi>lame</hi> and <hi>ſick</hi> Devotions after all?
Is it ſuitable that thou ſhould'ſt waſt
all thy very Marrow and Spirit upon
thy curſed Idols, but bring unto God
a few <hi>Torn</hi> crazy <hi>Howlings,</hi> at the laſt?
<hi>Should I accept this of your hands, ſaith the
Lord?</hi> There is a Story of one who did
attempt to <hi>Repent</hi> in <hi>Old-Age,</hi> after a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
and ungodly <hi>Youth;</hi> but heard
ſuch a Voice from Heaven as that, <hi>Des
illi Furfurem cui dediſti Farinam:</hi> The <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>
had thy <hi>Flower,</hi> and doſt thou think
to bring thy <hi>Bran</hi> to me? In thy <hi>Youth</hi>
wilt thou continue a <hi>Traitor</hi> and a <hi>Rebel</hi>
againſt the God of Heaven? And wilt
thou imagine to be <hi>received</hi> and <hi>protected</hi>
by him in the <hi>Age,</hi> when perhaps thou
haſt none elſe to go unto? When thou
art ſcarce able to ſin, at thy uſual rate,
ſhall that be the only <hi>Time</hi> for thee to
leave it off? <hi>Hear O Heavens,</hi> and <hi>give ear
O Earth;</hi> was there ever any thing ſo
Diſingenious?</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly, Old-Age</hi> is not an <hi>eaſie Time</hi>
                           <pb n="60" facs="tcp:55562:68"/>
for us to defer the <hi>Remembring</hi> of God
unto. Young Man, wilt thou not <hi>look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Lord, that thou may'ſt be ſaved;</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
thine <hi>Eyes</hi> are almoſt out? Until <hi>thoſe
that look out of the Windows be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</hi>
Wilt thou not <hi>lay hold on Eternal
Life,</hi> until thy <hi>Hands</hi> are ſhaking with a
Palſie? until the <hi>Keepers of the Houſe do
tremble?</hi> Wilt thou not <hi>Run the Race that
is ſet before thee,</hi> until thy <hi>Feet</hi> call for a
Staff? until the <hi>ſtrong men do bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?</hi>
Alas, theſe things will not be <hi>eaſie</hi>
then. Know, that thy <hi>Sin</hi> will then be
<hi>ſtronger:</hi> If it be hard for thee to part
with a <hi>Luſt</hi> now, what will it be then?
An <hi>old Tree,</hi> and an <hi>old Luſt</hi> are not eaſily
pulled up by the Roots: It is ſaid, in <hi>Jer.
13. 23. Can the Ethiopian change his skin,
or the Leopard his ſpots? then may you alſo
do good that are accuſtomed to do evil.</hi> An <hi>old
Cuſtom,</hi> and an <hi>old Diſeaſe</hi> are not eaſily
cured. We read of a <hi>Devil</hi> diſpoſſeſſed
with a wonderful Difficulty, in <hi>Mark 9.
25, 26. The Spirit cry'd and rent him ſore,
and he was as one Dead:</hi> What was the
cauſe of thoſe terrible convulſions? We
are told, the <hi>foul Spirit</hi> had been in that
Perſon, <hi>of a Child.</hi> An <hi>unclean</hi> Spirit, a
<hi>drunken</hi> Spirit, a <hi>profane</hi> Spirit, that has
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55562:68"/>
dwelt in a Man from his <hi>Childhood</hi> unto
<hi>Old-Age,</hi> O 'tis not eaſily driven away:
It is ſaid, in <hi>Heb. 3. 12. Exhort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to day, leſt any of you be hardned through
the deceitfulneſs of ſin.</hi> Deceitful <hi>Sin,</hi> tells
the <hi>Young</hi> Man, <hi>To morrow, to morrow will
be ſoon enough to leave thy evil wayes:</hi> But
the Heart grows <hi>harder</hi> and <hi>harder</hi> ſtill,
<hi>To morrow,</hi> than it was <hi>to day.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Know likewiſe, that thy <hi>ſtrength</hi> will
then be <hi>ſmaller.</hi> The Philoſopher truly
called <hi>Old-Age, the Winter of life:</hi> We
commonly ſay of <hi>Old-Age, It is it ſelf a
Diſeaſe, and attended with a thouſand more.</hi>
Then it is that, <hi>Pallor in Ore ſedet, Macies
in Corpore toto:</hi> A <hi>pale,</hi> a <hi>lean,</hi> and a <hi>feeble</hi>
State of Body comes upon us; and then
alſo the Mind grows more <hi>heavy</hi> and <hi>liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs:</hi>
It is as much as the <hi>Old</hi> Man can well
do, to encounter the manifold Infirmities
of his <hi>Age:</hi> And wilt thou never obey the
Lord until thou canſt not <hi>enjoy</hi> thy ſelf?
When <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto Old <hi>Barzillai, Come
thou over with me:</hi> The Old Man anſwering,
in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 34.—<hi>How long have I to live!
can I diſcern between good and evil? Can I taſte
what I eat or drink?</hi> No; let <hi>Chimham go.</hi>
Thus our <hi>David,</hi> our Jeſus, when he ſays
to an Old Man, <hi>Come over to me;</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55562:69"/>
may be: <hi>Alas, I have but a little while
to live; the Force of all my ſenſes is abated;
let the Young man go over to the Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly, Old-Age</hi> is no ſafe <hi>Time</hi> for us
to adjourn our Piety unto. The <hi>Young</hi>
Man allots upon <hi>Old-Age,</hi> as that which
he may very ſeaſonably grow ſober in:
But <hi>Young Man,</hi> what if thou ſhould'ſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
arrive to <hi>Old-Age</hi> at all? That is the
Hap of <hi>multitudes, multitudes</hi> every day:
The Sons of <hi>Job</hi> were all of them <hi>Young</hi>
Men, but they died ſuddenly, <hi>ſeven</hi> of
them at once. We have that Warning
often repeated unto us, in <hi>Job 21. 23. One
dyeth in his full ſtrength. Young</hi> Perſons of
both Sexes are liable to the Stroke of
<hi>Death:</hi> We read in <hi>Luke,</hi> about the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
of a <hi>Young Man,</hi> the Son of a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow:
We read in the ſame Evangeliſt,
about a <hi>young Woman,</hi> which <hi>lay a dying</hi>
when ſhe was but about <hi>Twelve years of Age.</hi>
The Arreſt of <hi>Death</hi> likewiſe falls upon
<hi>young</hi> Perſons of all <hi>Eſtates.</hi> The Son of
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> was a Gracious <hi>Youth;</hi> but he
<hi>dyes.</hi> The Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> were Vicious <hi>Youths,</hi>
and they <hi>dye</hi> too: So does the <hi>young man,
Abſalom,</hi> after his Brother <hi>Amnon.</hi> As
<hi>young</hi> as thou art, and as lively and as
luſty too; 'tis poſſible thou may'ſt like
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55562:69"/>
                           <hi>Eutichus</hi> fall down dead, before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
be diſmiſſed. Haſt thou a lewd
Dream of an <hi>Old-Age,</hi> to reſerve all Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
for? Alas, there are more die before
<hi>Twenty,</hi> than after <hi>Sixty</hi> Years of Age.
A Child once being obſerved to become
a very <hi>prayerful</hi> and <hi>penſive</hi> Child, gave
that Account of it, <hi>I was in the Burying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place
t'other day, and there I ſaw a Grave
ſhorter than my ſelf.</hi> Let the youngeſt of
us all go to ſuch a place, and ſee whether
there be not <hi>Graves</hi> of our Dimenſions
there? And what if now thy <hi>Death</hi> find
thee before thy Peace be made with God?
What if thy <hi>Death</hi> find thee a poor Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted,
Unregenerate Creature before
the Lord? It may be written on thy dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Grave, <hi>It had been good for that Perſon,
that he had never been Born.</hi> Infinitely more
than a thouſand Ages of Woes and
Plagues muſt be the Portion of ſuch a
miſerable Soul.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>young</hi> Man has many <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies</hi>
to excite and aſſiſt his <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi>
of the Lord. There ſeems to be
a ſort of Correſpondence between <hi>Youth</hi>
and <hi>Grace: Youth</hi> ſeems mightily adapted
and agreeable to the Exerciſe of that love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thing.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="64" facs="tcp:55562:70"/>
A <hi>quick Wit</hi> is one Prerogative of the
<hi>young Man:</hi> Well, how can he lay it out
better, than by doing like that <hi>young</hi>
Man, in <hi>Pſal. 119. 9. Taking heed unto the
Word of God?</hi> The <hi>Young man</hi> has a <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious
Memory:</hi> What can he do better
with it, than fill it with <hi>Divine Treaſures?
Warm Affections</hi> are ſtirring in the <hi>young
man;</hi> where ſhould he ſet them but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the <hi>things which are above?</hi> The <hi>Spirits</hi>
of <hi>young men</hi> are mettleſome; why ſhould
they not be <hi>fervent, ſerving the Lord?</hi>
The <hi>Bodies</hi> of <hi>young men</hi> are vigorous;
why ſhould they not be a <hi>living Sacrifice unto
God?</hi> There is a brave <hi>Courage</hi> in <hi>Youth;</hi>
how can it better ſhow it ſelf, than by <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming
the Wicked One? Youth</hi> is a <hi>merry</hi>
Age; let it then <hi>rejoyce in the Lord.</hi> O
nothing is more <hi>comely,</hi> or <hi>natural,</hi> than
that <hi>young</hi> Men ſhould <hi>remember God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="proposition">
                        <head>Prop. IV.</head>
                        <p>All the <hi>three Perſons</hi> in God are to be
diſtinctly conſidered by us, when we <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
him.</p>
                        <p>Not only our <hi>Creator,</hi> but alſo our <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi>
is to be <hi>remembred.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> We are to <hi>remember</hi> God the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55562:70"/>
                           <hi>Father.</hi> Him we are to <hi>remember</hi> under
that conſideration in <hi>Eph. 1. 3. The God
and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
Him as the Fountain <hi>from</hi> whence
all does proceed, and <hi>to</hi> which all muſt
Return. <hi>Remember</hi> Him as the <hi>firſt cauſe</hi>
and ſo the <hi>laſt end</hi> of all things. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
Him as the <hi>Father</hi> of thy Lord, and
go to Him for a <hi>Fathers Bleſſing</hi> in His
Name. O <hi>remember</hi> Him, and let the
outery of thy Soul be; <hi>Let this Father be
my Father for evermore.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> We are to <hi>remember</hi> God the
<hi>Son;</hi> Him we are to <hi>remember</hi> under that
Conſideration, in <hi>Act. 5. 31. A Prince and
a Saviour, to give Repentance unto Iſrael, and
Remiſſion of ſins. Remember</hi> Him as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<hi>in whom all fulneſs dwells. Remember</hi>
Him as the Jeſus <hi>who delivers from
Wrath to come. Remember</hi> Him as a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer
able to ſave unto the uttermoſt,</hi> and
go to Him for that Salvation; entreat
Him to be thy <hi>Prophet,</hi> and thy <hi>Prieſt,</hi>
and thy <hi>King</hi> for ever.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We are to <hi>Remember</hi> God the
<hi>Spirit.</hi> Him we are to <hi>Remember</hi> under
that Conſideration, in <hi>Pſal. 143. 10. The
good Spirit that leads into the land of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs.
Remember</hi> Him as the <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
                           <pb n="66" facs="tcp:55562:71"/>
of them that were <hi>dead in Treſpnſſes and
Sins. Remember</hi> Him as the <hi>Comforter</hi> of all
that <hi>mourn.</hi> Remember Him as the <hi>Inhabitant</hi>
of the <hi>Contrite</hi> and the <hi>Humble</hi> Heart; and
ſeek to be <hi>led</hi> by Him, World without end.</p>
                        <p>Thus are we to <hi>Remember</hi> our <hi>Creator</hi>
in the dayes of our <hi>Youth.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="application">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE I.</head>
                        <p>Let them that have not <hi>Remembred</hi> their
<hi>Creator</hi> in the days of their <hi>Youth,</hi> now in
the days of their <hi>Age</hi> be aſhamed of it, and
afflicted for it.</p>
                        <p>There are two ſorts of Aged People to be
now treated with: There are ſome that
are <hi>Converted</hi> unto God but late: They
ſquandered away moſt of all their <hi>Youth,</hi>
before they <hi>turned their feet unto the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
of the Lord.</hi> It becomes theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
now, as they <hi>Remember</hi> their <hi>God,</hi> ſo
likewiſe to <hi>Remember</hi> their <hi>Sin:</hi> You make
that your daily Prayer, in <hi>Pſal. 25. 7. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
not againſt me the ſins of my youth.</hi>
Be aſſured that God's dealing with <hi>you</hi>
will in many regards be quite contrary to
your dealing with your <hi>Sins.</hi> If you <hi>love</hi>
them, he will <hi>hate</hi> you: If you <hi>ſlay</hi> them,
he will <hi>ſave</hi> you: If you would have God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:55562:71"/>
not <hi>Remember</hi> them, O then do you <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
them your ſelves: 'Tis ſaid in
<hi>1 Cor. 11. 3. If we would judge our ſelves, we
ſhould not be judged of the Lord.</hi> Well then,
every one of you, like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Butler,
now ſay, <hi>I remember my faults this day.</hi> O
Remember all the <hi>lying,</hi> all the <hi>idleneſs;</hi>
all the <hi>profuſeneſs</hi> and <hi>profaneneſs</hi> of thy
<hi>Youth.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>young</hi> Man, he
had an hand in Abuſing and Murdering an
Eminent Miniſter of God, but he <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred</hi>
it with ſorrow all his dayes: O! ſaid
he many Years after; <hi>When the Blood of
Stephen was ſhed, I was conſenting to it.</hi> Come
now and ſit down in the Duſt this day
before the Lord; come, and lament it,
and bewail it, that you <hi>ſo long</hi> lay out
from God, and that you <hi>ſo long</hi> did the
things, for which the Wrath of God
comes upon the Children of Diſobedience.
Be able to ſay, <hi>My Soul has this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
and is humbled in me.</hi> But perhaps
there are ſome of you that never yet were
<hi>Converted</hi> unto God at all: As they ſaid
in <hi>Jer. 8. 20. The Harveſt is paſt, the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
is ended, and we are not ſaved;</hi> thus
may too many confeſs, <hi>Our youth is paſt,
and we are not Renewed.</hi> Surely 'tis Time,
'tis high Time for you to <hi>Remember</hi> your,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55562:72"/>
God, yet at laſt, before you go hence and
be no more: Let this <hi>encourage</hi> you, That
it is not <hi>too late</hi> as yet for you ſo to do.
The Lord ſaid in <hi>Jer. 3. 1. Though thou haſt
play'd the Harlot with many Lovers, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
unto me:</hi> Even ſo, thô thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<hi>many ſins;</hi> thô thou haſt been ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<hi>many years; yet return unto me, ſaith
the Lord.</hi> There was in this very Land,
one that had lived a carnal, ſtupid, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
Perſon for about an hundred years,
and yet became a <hi>ſerious Chriſtian</hi> before
he dyed. Unto the <hi>Oldeſt</hi> Enemy of God
among us all, I this day proclaim the <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi>
of the Lord: O let this break thy
heart, and cauſe thee to come and ſay,
<hi>I will do Iniquity no more.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But let this alſo <hi>Terrifie</hi> you, it will be
<hi>too late</hi> for you e're long: It is ſaid in
<hi>Pſal. 6. 5. In Death there is no Remembrance
of thee.</hi> Thy <hi>Death,</hi> thy <hi>Death</hi> is juſt ready
to ſeize upon thee, and there is no <hi>work,
no wiſdom in the Grave, whither thou art
going.</hi> Then thy cry, will be like that of
Deſpairing Ones, <hi>All too late! All too late!</hi>
God prevent ſuch a miſcarriage of thy
never-dying Soul.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="application">
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:55562:72"/>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE II.</head>
                        <p>Let us that are in our <hi>Youth,</hi> Now <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
our <hi>Creator</hi> in it.</p>
                        <p>There are a multitude of <hi>young</hi> Perſons,
to vvhom the Word of God may reach
this day. Now the Almighty God make
this Word of his, <hi>Quick and powerful, and
ſharper than a two-edged Sword</hi> within their
Souls! Hear, O Young People; <hi>Hear that
your Souls may live:</hi> It is reported of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham,</hi>
in <hi>Judg. 9. 7. He ſtood in the top of
the Mount, and he lift up his voice and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and ſaid, Hearken unto me, that God
may hearken unto you.</hi> Thus would I do,
thus would I ſpeak this day. Here I
<hi>ſtand</hi> in the Name of God that made you
all: I would lift up my voice, and <hi>cry,</hi>
and ſay, <hi>O Remember your Creator now, in
the dayes of your youth.</hi> If you will not
<hi>hear</hi> this Call of God now, God will not
<hi>hear</hi> your cry to Him another Day. God
will be deaf to the <hi>Words of thy Roaring,</hi>
in the dayes of thy <hi>Age,</hi> and of thy <hi>Death,</hi>
and of thy <hi>Wrath,</hi> if thou art now deaf
to the <hi>Words of his Counſel.</hi> The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
(and it is wholſome Counſel) of our
God now unto us, is, <hi>Remember me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times:</hi>
                           <pb n="70" facs="tcp:55562:73"/>
In order thereunto, theſe things
are to be done.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="rule">
                        <head>Rule I.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>Remember that</hi> which will help us
to <hi>Remember God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt,</hi> Remember thy <hi>Death,</hi> and thou
wilt Remember thy <hi>God.</hi> A Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
of <hi>Death</hi> will produce in a Man a
ſerious and godly frame of Spirit. One
that was Remarkable for his Devotions,
gave that Reaſon of it, <hi>O I muſt Dye! I
muſt Dye!</hi> If a Young Man would awful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
realize unto himſelf that thing, <hi>I muſt
dye!</hi> it would highly promote an Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
between God and him: And <hi>young
Man,</hi> it is not too ſoon for thee to have
the Apprehenſions of it. There was a
<hi>young Man</hi> in this Land, that left behind
him in Writing, <hi>Meditations to promote Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
for Death.</hi> O that every <hi>young man</hi>
would be no Stranger to ſuch prudent <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let every <hi>young</hi> Perſon <hi>Remember</hi> this:
<hi>I ſhall dye very certainly:</hi> As <hi>Job</hi> could ſay,
in Ch. 30. 23. <hi>I know that thou wilt bring me
to Death:</hi> So let the <hi>young</hi> Perſon ſay, <hi>I
know that I muſt e're long look the King of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55562:73"/>
Terrors in the Face; and I know that e're
long I ſhall go thither, whence I ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</hi>
Often look upon that Scripture,
in <hi>Heb. 9. 27. It is appointed unto all Men
once to dye.</hi> Often look upon that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
in <hi>Pſal. 89. 48. What man is he that
liveth, and ſhall not ſee Death?</hi> And let
theſe warnings make a deep Impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
thy Mind. There was a <hi>Prince</hi> who
gave a Penſion unto a Perſon, that he
might once a day come and ſay unto him,
<hi>Remember that thou art a Mortal Man:</hi> Do
that office unto thy ſelf every Day. Look
upon <hi>Death</hi> as the way <hi>of all the Earth;</hi>
And Remember, <hi>I muſt go that Way:</hi> Look
upon <hi>Death</hi> as the <hi>End of all men;</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<hi>I ſhall have that End.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
there is <hi>no diſcharge in that War.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let every <hi>young</hi> Perſon alſo <hi>Remember</hi>
this, <hi>I ſhall dye very ſpeedily.</hi> While we are
<hi>young,</hi> we ſtrangely promiſe our ſelves to
live <hi>long.</hi> Do not harbour that miſtake;
but rectifie it by that Premoniton, in <hi>Jam.
4. 14. What is your life? It is even a Vapour,
that appeareth for a little time, and vaniſheth
away:</hi> Rectifie it by that Premonition,
in <hi>1 Chron. 28. 15. Our dayes on the Earth
are as a ſhadow, and there is none abiding.</hi>
What are the poor <hi>Seventy years,</hi> that the
Life of Man is now contracted into! Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:55562:74"/>
they are winged things, they
fly away, with a marvellous Velocity.
We are truly told of them, in <hi>Job</hi> 9. 25.
that they are ſwifter than a <hi>Poſt;</hi> yea,
more than ſo, ſwifter than a <hi>Ship;</hi> yea,
more than that, ſwifter than an <hi>Eagle
haſt'ning to the Prey.</hi> Beſides, <hi>Remember,</hi>
'tis poſſible, that <hi>half</hi> of thoſe <hi>years</hi> may
be all that thou ſhalt ever ſee; it hath
been well ſaid, <hi>That an old Man has Death
before his Face; but a young Man has Death
behind his Back:</hi> Perhaps, <hi>Death</hi> may
ſtrike thee down before him that is old
enough to be thy Father. <hi>Remember</hi> that
there are <hi>Skulls</hi> of all ſizes in <hi>Golgotha.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> Remember thy <hi>Soul,</hi> and thou
wilt Remember thy <hi>God:</hi> Thou haſt a
never-dying <hi>Soul</hi> within thee; a <hi>Spiritual
and an Immortal Subſtance, able to diſcern,
and argue, and affect with a wonderful Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion.</hi>
How frequently and fearfully
do <hi>young</hi> Perſons forget that they are
Owners of ſuch a <hi>Jewel.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let every <hi>young</hi> Perſon <hi>Remember</hi> this,
<hi>The ſtate of my Soul is miſerable. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
the guilt and filth, which thy <hi>Soul,</hi>
by it's becoming a conſtituent Eſſential
<hi>part</hi> in one of <hi>Adams</hi> Children, ſoon was
defil'd withal. <hi>Remember</hi> what a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Anger and Vengeance of God, thy
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55562:74"/>
                           <hi>Soul</hi> by thy <hi>ſin</hi> is expos'd unto. <hi>Remember</hi>
that Character of thy <hi>Soul,</hi> in <hi>Gen. 6. 5.
Every imagination of the thoughts of the heart,
is only evil continually. Remember</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
of thy <hi>Soul,</hi> in <hi>Eph. 2. 12. Without
Chriſt, a ſtranger from the Convenant of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
having no hope, and without God in the
World. Remember</hi> what thou haſt been
doing unto thy <hi>Soul,</hi> ever ſince thy <hi>Birth:</hi>
It is ſaid in <hi>Prov. 8. 36. He that ſinneth
wrongeth his own Soul.</hi> O Remember what
<hi>Wrongs,</hi> what <hi>Wounds,</hi> thy own Soul has
had from thy own hand; and <hi>Remember</hi>
what an ever-gnawing <hi>Worm,</hi> what an
ever-burning <hi>Fire,</hi> is now ready to ſeize
upon that poor <hi>Soul</hi> of thine: Thou art
mindful of thy <hi>Body,</hi> of thy <hi>Eſtate,</hi> of thy
<hi>Credit,</hi> and mindful of almoſt every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
which thou art concerned in. Thy
<hi>Soul</hi> now begs of thee, <hi>O Remember me!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let every <hi>young</hi> Perſon likewiſe <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
this, <hi>The worth of my Soul is invaluable.</hi> A
Great Man was well adviſed once every
day, to <hi>remember</hi> that Sentence of our Lord,
in <hi>Matt. 16. 26. What is a man profited, if
he gain the whole World, and loſe his own
ſoul?</hi> Thou canſt not <hi>Remember</hi> a more
important thing. <hi>Remember</hi> the Glorious
Faculties and Endowments of thy <hi>ſoul. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
what a price, what a vaſt price,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55562:75"/>
the Lord Jeſus counted not too much for
thy <hi>ſoul. Remember</hi> how deſirous the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>
are to aſſiſt, how deſirous the <hi>Devils</hi>
are to deſtroy that <hi>ſoul</hi> of thine. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
theſe things, when thy Enemies are
bartering for thy <hi>ſoul.</hi> When our Lord
was betrayed for a <hi>little Money,</hi> He ſaid
in <hi>Zech. 11. 13. A goodly price was I valued
at of them! Remember</hi> that as the voice
of thy Soul, when thou art under Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
to evil things. When thy Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
would have thee ſell thy <hi>ſoul</hi> for a
<hi>ſong:</hi> When they would have thee pawn
thy Soul for a <hi>Cup,</hi> or an <hi>Oath,</hi> or a <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
or indeed for the beſt thing in this
World, now <hi>Remember</hi> that Expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of thy own <hi>ſoul; Am I worth no more
than ſo? A goodly price am I valued at!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Remember the <hi>Word,</hi> and thou
wilt Remember the Lord: The <hi>Word</hi> of
God <hi>Written,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of God <hi>Preached,</hi> is
vouchſafed unto us: <hi>Remember</hi> that, and
be able to ſay after the Pſamiſt, in <hi>Pſal.
119. 16. I will not forget thy Word.</hi> Let
our <hi>Memories</hi> be full of <hi>Truth,</hi> and they
will be full of <hi>God.</hi> Our <hi>Memories</hi> are a
coſtly, curious Cabinet; it is pity that
there ſhould be only vile <hi>rags</hi> and <hi>ſhreds</hi>
laid up therein: We can <hi>Remember</hi> too
well, <hi>old ſongs,</hi> and <hi>old wrongs.</hi> Our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories</hi>
                           <pb n="75" facs="tcp:55562:75"/>
are too like the Walls of the Houſe
which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 10. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>creeping things,</hi> and <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
Beaſts,</hi> and curſed <hi>Idols,</hi> were <hi>pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd</hi>
all round about. For theſe things
we may ſay, as one ſaid unto his Friend,
that offer'd to teach him the <hi>Art of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory;</hi>
Sir, (ſaid he) <hi>If you would teach me
the Art of Forgetfulneſs, I ſhould be more
pleaſed with it:</hi> But for the things of God,
there our <hi>Memories</hi> ſhould <hi>ſerve</hi> us, there
our <hi>Memories</hi> do fail us wonderfully. I
have read of a <hi>young</hi> Man, whom all the
pains in the World would not make to
<hi>Remember</hi> the letters of the <hi>Alphabet:</hi> Such
lamentable <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> in the Sacred and
Solemn things of another World, are
<hi>young</hi> people too ſubject unto. It is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. 51. that he
called his Firſt-born Son, <hi>Menaſſeh,</hi> or
<hi>Forgetfulneſs.</hi> Such, O ſuch a Name <hi>young</hi>
Perſons may often put on their own Souls,
when the <hi>Word</hi> of God is brought unto
them; their Souls are ſo many <hi>Menaſſeh's,</hi>
O how <hi>forgetful</hi> are they, when God has
been ſpeaking to them! Our Lord ſaid
unto his Diſciples, in <hi>John 15. 20. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
the word that I ſaid unto you.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
time you read a <hi>Chapter,</hi> or hear a
<hi>Sermon,</hi> then <hi>Remember</hi> that the Lord ſays,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55562:76"/>
                           <hi>Remember this:</hi> The Apoſtle ſo ſpeaketh,
in <hi>Heb. 2. 1. The things which we have heard,
we ſhould not let them ſlip:</hi> 'Tis an alluſion
to a <hi>Leaky Veſſel. Young</hi> People, the Great
God is pouring his <hi>Commandments,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi>
and <hi>Threatnings</hi> into your Souls every
day; O do not ſuffer them to <hi>leak away.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
in your own Souls, the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi>
of the things that you <hi>hear from God the
Lord:</hi> It is ſaid in <hi>Rev. 3. 3. Remember how
thou haſt received and heard.</hi> When thou
haſt <hi>received</hi> and <hi>heard</hi> a meſſage from the
God of Heaven; give thy Soul now that
charge, <hi>Remember this, O my Soul, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
it.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Remember <hi>Eternity,</hi> and thou
wilt Remember <hi>Him that inhabiteth Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi>
It is ſaid in <hi>Eccleſ. 11. 8. Let a man
Remember the days of darkneſs, for they ſhall be
many:</hi> Thus would I ſay, <hi>Let a young man
remember the dayes of Eternity, for they ſhall
be endleſs.</hi> The Pſalmiſt has that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
in <hi>Pſal. 77. 5. I have conſidered the
years of Ancient Times:</hi> There are who ſo
render it, <hi>I have conſidered the years of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
O <hi>Remember</hi> that Eternity which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
hour brings thee a Step nearer to, than
thou waſt before. <hi>Remember</hi> that <hi>Eternity</hi>
wherein thou ſhalt enjoy inexpreſſible
<hi>Happineſs,</hi> or endure intolerable <hi>Miſery</hi>
                           <pb n="77" facs="tcp:55562:76"/>
World without end. A Perſon of Quality
having ſpent ſome Time in <hi>unlawful Games,</hi>
at Night could not ſleep; giving this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
to one that required the Reaſon of it;
<hi>Yeſterday, I caſt my Eye occaſionally on a Book,
wherein I ſaw that Word, ETERNITY; and
that word has broke my Heart within me:</hi> O
that thing, <hi>Eternity, Eternity!</hi> the <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi>
of it will <hi>Awe</hi> thy Heart, if it will
not <hi>break</hi> thy Heart within thee. <hi>Remember</hi>
that thou art going to an Eſtate of <hi>Weal</hi> or
of <hi>Woe;</hi> and that thou ſhalt remain in that
Eſtate, fixed like a Rock, for infinitely
more than a thouſand Million of Ages.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE II.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>Abandon that</hi> which would hinder
us to <hi>remember God.</hi> There are ſome fatal
things that are called in <hi>Job 13. 26. The Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities
of youth:</hi> And in <hi>Jer. 31. 19. Tbe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
of youth:</hi> An <hi>Entanglement</hi> in thoſe,
will ſpoil a <hi>Remembrance</hi> of God. To all
<hi>young</hi> Perſons now is that Call of Heaven, in
<hi>2 Tim. 2. 22. Flee youthful Luſts.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To particularize,</p>
                        <p>(1.) <hi>Abandon</hi> the Sin of <hi>Ill Company-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
that you <hi>remember</hi> your Creator. Be
able to ſay with him, in <hi>Pſal. 26. 4. I have
not ſat with vain perſons.</hi> Many an hopeful
<hi>young man</hi> has been ruined, by falling into
the Society of the Profane: Never was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55562:77"/>
there a more bloody Murderer of Souls than
<hi>that</hi> Society. The very Heathen could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,
and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> quotes the
Speech of an Heathen Poet for it, <hi>That evil
Communications corrupt good manners.</hi> Now
they are <hi>Evil Companions</hi> with whom thoſe
<hi>evil Communications</hi> are. <hi>Young man,</hi> doſt
thou ſee others, that will <hi>Drink,</hi> and <hi>Game,</hi>
and <hi>Swear,</hi> and <hi>Scoff?</hi> I would call upon
thee, as <hi>Moſes</hi> upon them in <hi>Num. 16. 26.
Depart from the Tents of theſe wicked men, leſt
ye be conſumed in all their ſins.</hi> Do not ſo
much as begin a needleſs familiarity with
<hi>Wicked men:</hi> Don't <hi>Walk</hi> with the <hi>ungodly,</hi>
leſt you come to <hi>ſtand</hi> with the <hi>ſinners,</hi> and
at laſt <hi>ſit</hi> with the <hi>ſcornful: Remember</hi> that
bad Companions will cauſe you to <hi>ſin</hi> with
them. The <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon</hi> grew very cold
in the matter of Building the <hi>Houſe</hi> of God.
Why ſo? Their dwelling among the lewd
and wild <hi>Babylonians,</hi> procur'd this indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency.
I have thought, how came <hi>Corah,</hi> a
Levite, to hook in <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi>
and the <hi>Reubenites</hi> into a Conſpiracy with
him? I find that the <hi>Levites</hi> of <hi>Kohath,</hi> and
the <hi>Reubenites</hi> pitched their Tents near to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
on the South-ſide of the Tabernacle.
So they infected one another: <hi>Remember,</hi>
that bad Companions will cauſe you to dye
with them too. I pray how came <hi>Ahaziah</hi>
                           <pb n="79" facs="tcp:55562:77"/>
to meet with his <hi>Death</hi> before his <hi>Time?</hi>
It was by viſiting a debauched bigotted
Idolater, the infamous <hi>Jehoram.</hi> When you
fall into a Knot of Impious Men, you
are like the Man Travelling to <hi>Jeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho,</hi>
who fell among <hi>Thieves</hi> that <hi>ſtripped</hi>
him, and <hi>wounded</hi> him, and <hi>departed</hi> leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
him <hi>half-dead.</hi> Some Perſons going out of
the World, have comfortably pleaded that
with God, <hi>Lord, let me not be with wicked men
for ever, for I never cared to be with them here:</hi>
Sad is the Caſe of them who cannot plead
ſo. O that every young Man would <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
that ſaying in <hi>Prov. 1. 10. My Son, if ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
entice thee, conſent thou not; walk not thou
in the way of them;</hi> and <hi>remember</hi> that
ſaying in <hi>Prov. 13. 20. He that walketh
with the wiſe ſhall be wiſe, but a Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> What ſhall
I ſay more? In fine, <hi>Remember,</hi> young
Man, that on thy <hi>Death-bed</hi> thou wilt gnaſh
thy Teeth at the ſight of ſuch <hi>Companions,</hi>
thy groan will then be, <hi>O gather not my
ſoul with ſinners!</hi> and one of them in thy
<hi>Chamber</hi> would then be thy <hi>Torment</hi> there.
Well then, <hi>ſave your ſelves from this unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Generation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>(2.) <hi>Abandon</hi> the Sin of <hi>Sabbath-breaking,</hi>
that you may <hi>Remember</hi> your Creator. It
is the Command of God in <hi>Exod. 20. 8.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55562:78"/>
Remember the Sabbath-day to keep it holy:</hi>
Men are like to <hi>Remember</hi> God himſelf,
if they <hi>remember</hi> this day of the Lord as
they ought to do. If you look through
the World, you ſhall ſee that Mens <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi>
is as their <hi>Sabbath</hi> is. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> is
the <hi>Engine</hi> by which, by the <hi>Bible,</hi> true
Remembrance of God is kept alive. It
is the Deſcription which the Lord gives
of all good Men, in <hi>Iſa. 56. 4. They that
keep my Sabbaths, and chooſe the things that
pleaſe me.</hi> Young Men, this is the Day,
to which all other days may ſay, <hi>Thou
art worth Ten thouſand of us:</hi> Of this Day
it ſhall evermore be ſaid, <hi>O thou Day that
is highly favoured, the Lord is with thee, bleſſed
art thou among the Dayes, and curſed is he
that deſpiſes thee!</hi> Young Perſons are apt
on this day to be <hi>vain</hi> in their Thoughts
and Words, and <hi>Idle</hi> in their whole Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour:
But labour thou to ſpend this Day
as a <hi>Market-day for thy Soul;</hi> ſpend it in
Holy Duties, and in thoſe things that may
prove both a <hi>Cauſe</hi> and a <hi>Sign</hi> of thy <hi>Reſt
among the People of God</hi> for ever: Do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to that in <hi>Iſa. 58. 13. Call the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
a delight, the holy of the Lord, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</hi>
Do not abuſe this high Day of
God; as the Prophet ſaid unto <hi>Gehazi, Is
this a Time to receive Money?</hi> ſo let me ſay,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:55562:78"/>
                           <hi>Is this a time to be making of Bargains, or to
be ordering of Journeys?</hi> Much more, <hi>Is
this a time for Rioting and Drunkenneſs, for
Chambering and Wantonneſs? or for ſuch
things as are never ſeaſonable?</hi> No, 'tis not
ſuch a <hi>Time:</hi> To the young People that
make it ſuch a <hi>Time,</hi> I would ſay as in
<hi>Neh. 13. 18. You bring Wrath upon Iſrael
by profaning the Sabbath:</hi> Such Perſons are
the meer <hi>Achans</hi> of the Land they live in.</p>
                        <p>Finally, There are many other ſins of
<hi>Youth,</hi> eſpecially that ſin of <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi>
which we muſt avoid, and forſake, if we
would <hi>Remember</hi> God: Let no Young Man
allow himſelf in thoſe curſed things.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE III.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>Remember</hi> the <hi>virtuous Example</hi> of
them that have been <hi>good betimes,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
the <hi>Holy Pattern</hi> of the <hi>Holy Jeſus.</hi> It
is ſaid in <hi>Heb. 13. 7. Remember them whoſe
Faith is to be followed:</hi> So it may be urged,
<hi>Remember them whoſe Youth is to be followed:</hi>
If we <hi>remember</hi> them, we ſhall <hi>remember</hi>
God. There have been <hi>young</hi> Perſons that
have had the <hi>Grace</hi> of Forty at the <hi>Age</hi> of
Twenty in them. Sometimes a <hi>young</hi> Man
has given up himſelf to God by a <hi>Covenant
never to be forgotten.</hi> A <hi>young</hi> Man has main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
a courſe of daily <hi>ſupplication,</hi> and
beſides often had his <hi>extraordinary Dayes</hi>
                           <pb n="82" facs="tcp:55562:79"/>
of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe;</hi> a <hi>young</hi> Man has up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
a courſe of daily <hi>Meditation,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
accuſtomed himſelf to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
with ſuch Attention, as to fetch a
<hi>Note</hi> and a <hi>Wiſh</hi> out of every <hi>Verſe</hi> before
him, ſuch an one I have lately follow'd
unto the <hi>Grave:</hi> Many more ſuch Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of <hi>Early Piety,</hi> perhaps a Young Man
here and there may afford unto us: O now,
<hi>Go thou and do likewiſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But above all, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt
calls for our Imitation: It is ſaid of Him,
in <hi>Pſal. 110. 3. Thou haſt the Dew of thy
Youth:</hi> In his <hi>Youth</hi> it ſelf a <hi>Dew of Grace</hi>
was to be ſeen upon him; in his <hi>Youth</hi> he
fulfilled the whole will of God; in his
<hi>Youth</hi> he was always <hi>about his Fathers buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi>
He now ſays to <hi>Young</hi> Men, what
he ſays to <hi>All</hi> Men in <hi>Joh. 13. 15. I have
given you an Example, that you ſhould do as I
have done.</hi> O then ſtudy Chriſt Jeſus, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
Chriſt Jeſus, follow Chriſt Jeſus; ask,
<hi>What was the Behaviour of Chriſt Jeſus in his
Youth?</hi> and, <hi>Be as he was in the World.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="rule">
                        <head>RULE IV.</head>
                        <p>Let us <hi>remember</hi> the <hi>profitable Inſtruction</hi>
of them that wiſh well unto us.</p>
                        <p>There is a twofold <hi>Inſtruction</hi> which
<hi>young</hi> Perſons among us are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
of: There is <hi>Paſtoral</hi> Inſtruction, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:55562:79"/>
there is <hi>Parental</hi> Inſtruction, under which
you ſit. Regard this <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> leſt you <hi>mourn</hi>
at laſt, and ſay, <hi>How have I hated Inſtruction,
and not obeyed the voice of my Teachers!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You enjoy <hi>Pastoral</hi> Inſtrnction, O deſpiſe
it not! You have with Sermon after Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
been publickly and ſolemnly called
upon to <hi>Remember God.</hi> Beſides this, I have
<hi>perſonally</hi> treated with ſome ſcores of you,
about your <hi>Eternal Welfare,</hi> and I hope I
may live to viſit <hi>every one</hi> of you for this end,
earneſtly and urgently <hi>beſeeching of you to be
Reconciled unto God.</hi> It was of old enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in <hi>Deut. 31. 12. Gather the People toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
Men and Women, and Children, that they
may hear, and learn, and fear the Lord:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
the <hi>Children</hi> as well as the <hi>Adult</hi> have
been adviſed here, to <hi>Remember the Lord.</hi>
What is now the effect of it? I will for
once wax bold with you, and ſay as Dying
<hi>Bolton</hi> ſaid unto his Children, <hi>Children, let
any of you meet me at the day of Judgment in
a Christleſs unregenerate eſtate if you dare! I
will teſtifie againſt you,</hi> I ſay again, <hi>I will teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
againſt you before the Lord Jeſus, if you do.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You enjoy <hi>Paternal</hi> Inſtruction too; O
refuſe it not! Does not thy <hi>Father,</hi> or thy
<hi>Maſter,</hi> or thy <hi>Mother,</hi> charge thee to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
God?</hi> Did they never charge thee to
read the <hi>Word,</hi> and ſeek the <hi>Face</hi> of God,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:55562:80"/>
and to make Conſcience of thy Wayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Then, <hi>My Son, hear the Inſtruction of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and forſake not the Law of thy Mother.</hi>
What befell the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> thoſe Sons of
<hi>Belial?</hi> in <hi>1 Sam. 2. 25. They hearkened not
to the Voice of their Father, becauſe the Lord
would ſlay them.</hi> Art thou a <hi>young</hi> Perſon,
counſelled by a good <hi>Parent</hi> to <hi>Remember</hi>
the Lord? <hi>The Lord will ſlay</hi> thee; yea, <hi>The
Lord will Damn</hi> thee, if thou doſt not <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi>
thereunto.</p>
                        <p>Thus are we to <hi>Remember God:</hi> And, O
who among you are more than <hi>almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded</hi>
hereunto? Let a few Conſiderations
more add weight unto thoſe that have alſo
beſpoke it of you.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="consideration">
                        <head>CONSIDER. I.</head>
                        <p>The God of Heaven has <hi>Commanded</hi> you
to <hi>Remember</hi> him; you have this <hi>Command</hi>
in a <hi>ſhadow</hi> under the Law of old: It was
required in <hi>Exod. 22. 29. Thou ſhalt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay
to offer the firſt of the ripe fruits unto me.</hi>
The Lord thus calls, <hi>Bring me the firſt of thy
Age,</hi> and, <hi>Bring me the firſt of thy ſtrength:</hi>
How dareſt thou then carry it unto the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>
inſtead of him?</p>
                        <p>This <hi>Command</hi> is yet more expreſs, where the Lord
calls for a <hi>preſent</hi> Repentance, a <hi>preſent</hi> Obedience from
us; ſaith he not in <hi>Jer. 25. 5. Turn ye now every one from
his evil way?</hi> ſaith he not in <hi>Pſal. 95. 7. O that ye would
hear his Voice to day?</hi> ſaith he not in <hi>Pſal. 147. 12. Both
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55562:80"/>
young Men and Maidens, old Men and Children, O Praiſe
the Lord?</hi> Young Man, do not venture to ſlight the
<hi>Command</hi> of that God who can <hi>ſpeak</hi> thee into Hell for
ſlighting it: Do not offend and provoke that God who
can with hot Thunder-bolts avenge thy doing ſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="consideration">
                        <head>CONSIDER. II.</head>
                        <p>'Tis for your own <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Benefit</hi> now to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
God.</hi> It is impoſſible to reckon up all the
Advantages of <hi>Early Religion:</hi> Indeed, <hi>Godlineſs is
profitable for all things;</hi> but <hi>Early Godlineſs,</hi> that,
that is it which brings moſt <hi>profit</hi> unto the Owners of
it: It is truly ſaid in <hi>Lam. 3. 27. It is good for a man that
he bear the Yoke in his Youth. Young Man,</hi> Remember
God, and it will <hi>pleaſe Him.</hi> It was very <hi>pleaſing</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
God, when <hi>Abel</hi> brought the <hi>Firſtlings</hi> of his Flock
unto Him: The Lord ſaid in <hi>Jer. 2. 2. I Remember
the kindneſs of thy Youth.</hi> If we <hi>Remember God</hi> in our
Youth, God will <hi>Remember</hi> the ſeriouſneſs of our
Youth, the ſavourineſs of our Youth, and the <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
of our Youth a great while afterwards. It was
the Speech of God in <hi>Hoſ. 11. 1. When Iſrael was a child
I loved him.</hi> When Perſons are in their <hi>Childhood</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
and gracious, and ſuch as <hi>Remember</hi> Him, ſuch
perſons are <hi>loved</hi> exceedingly by Him that <hi>loveth the
Righteous.</hi> When <hi>little Children</hi> were brought unto the
Lord Jeſus, <hi>He bleſſed them:</hi> What will the Lord then do
for them that <hi>Remember</hi> to come themſelves unto Him?
He will <hi>bleſs</hi> them, for they <hi>pleaſe</hi> him exceedingly.</p>
                        <p>Remember God, and it will alſo <hi>ſave thee:</hi> O what
a matchleſs Promiſe is there ſet before thee, in <hi>Prov.
8. 17. They that ſeek me early ſhall find me!</hi> Thou ſhalt
find <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and find <hi>God,</hi> and find the <hi>Pearl of great
price</hi> by the <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ly ſeeking</hi> thereof: Whoever does miſs
of mercy from God, yet unto the <hi>Young</hi> Perſon, the
Lord ſaith, in <hi>1 Chron. 28. 9. If thou ſeek him he ſhall be
found of thee.</hi> This is a certain way to find <hi>Grace,</hi> to
find <hi>Glory,</hi> to find <hi>every good thing;</hi> ſeek <hi>early</hi> for it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
they are not only <hi>centain Finders,</hi> but alſo <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi>
                           <pb n="86" facs="tcp:55562:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <hi>Finders,</hi> Eminent and Tranſcendent <hi>Finders,</hi> that
are <hi>Early Seekers</hi> of the Lord; they are the <hi>Joſephs,</hi> and
the <hi>Samuels,</hi> and the <hi>Davids</hi> of the World.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="consideration">
                        <head>CONSIDER. III.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remember God</hi> Now, or there is Danger that you
never will at all: As he ſaid in <hi>Joh. 3. 4. How can a
Man be born when he is old?</hi> ſo, <hi>How can a Man be
New-born then?</hi> It ſeldom is. Our Text ſays, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
thy Creator in the days of thy Youth;</hi> It may be
rendred, <hi>In the days of thy Choice.</hi> You now make your
<hi>Choice:</hi> If you <hi>chooſe</hi> God in your <hi>Youth,</hi> Well; but
if you now <hi>chooſe</hi> Luſt and Sin, a thouſand to one
but God will confirm that <hi>Choice;</hi> the Lord may ſay,
<hi>Let him that is filthy be filthy ſtill,</hi> and, <hi>Let him that is
wicked he wicked for evermore:</hi> Beſides the <hi>Mortality,</hi>
there is alſo an <hi>Obduration</hi> which thou art in danger
of: It is a direful Menace of God in <hi>Gen. 6. 3. My
Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive.</hi> If thou doſt now <hi>reſiſt</hi>
the <hi>ſtrivings</hi> of the Lord, thou doſt as it were <hi>ſmother</hi>
them and <hi>baniſh</hi> them; 'tis to be fear'd that they will
take an Eternal Farewell of thy forſaken Soul. Doſt
not thou Tremble at this, O thou Heart of <hi>Adamant?</hi>
If this horrible thing ſhould be the Portion of thy
Soul, <hi>Down, Down, Down</hi> thou goeſt into the Pitt,
among them that <hi>cannot hope for the Truth of God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>God prevent ſo great an Evil! God make every <hi>young</hi>
Perſon among us a <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that <hi>While he is yet young, ſhall
ſeek the Lord.</hi> God make every <hi>young</hi> Perſon among us
an <hi>Abijah,</hi> that while <hi>young</hi> ſhall have in him <hi>ſome good
thing toward the Lord.</hi> God enable every <hi>young</hi> Perſon to
ſay as <hi>Obadiah</hi> did, <hi>I fear the Lord from my Youth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now, unto thee, O God, I bend my knees, with my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
that thy Converting Grace may produce multitudes
of ſuch tender Grapes in this Vineyard of the Lord.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
